<topics>
	<topic>
		<id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-belle-gunness-murder-farm</id>
		<results>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86090383/1908-05-06/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=body+La+Belle+Porte+Gunness+bodies</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Find Three More New Graves on the
Place of Mrs Belle Gunness To
day Woman Missing
der the surface and have the appear
ance of having been buried about a
year
Chicago Interested
Special to the Herald
Chicago 111 May 6 The coroner
declared today that he would examine
the body of Max Sorenson the first
husband of Mrs Belle Gunness to de
termine if possible the cause of
death
Fiendish Deeds
La PorteInd May 5 With five
bodies already unearthed Sheriff
Smuizer and Coroner Mack will con
tinue their search tomorrow for
other alleged victims of Mrs Belle
Gunness who to all indications was
one of the most fiendish murderesses
of the century and who was recently
killed with her three children through
the burning of her country home one
mile northeast of La Porte
Of the bodies so far unearthed two
have been identified They are the
bodies of Andrew Heldgren a wealthy
bachelor of Aberdeen S D and Miss
Jennie Olsen 11yearold stepdaugh
ter of Mrs Gunness The other three
bodies are so badly decomposed as to
make identification impossible
The discovery of the bodies was
brought about by the appearance of
John Heldgren of Aberdeen S D
brother of Andrew Heldgren in La
Porte in search of the missing man
With the infromation that his brother
Andrew had come to La Porte to wed
Mrs Gunness that he had turned over
his property to her he became con
vinced that his brother had been the
victim of foul play While question
ing Joe Maxson a hired man on Mrs
Gunness farm he learned of the mys
terious digging of holes by him all
of them being filled up at a later date
by Mrs Gunness He led Heldgren
and the officers to the spot where the
holes had been drug about 150 feet
from the house and there after dig
ging a few minutes was uncovered
the body of Heldgren The remains
were only a few feet under the
ground and were Inclosed in a gunny
sack The legs and arms had been
dismembered but were with the
trunk
About thirtyfive feet further the re
mains of four other persons were
found
Cleveland Improving
Special to the Herald
Lakewood N J May G Mrs
Cleveland made the following state
ment today Mr Cleveland Is stead
ily improving and is now on the way
to complete recovery We have not
yet decided how long we shall remain
here
Get the Habit Cook With Gas
K iS rf
J t li TL v
TINE DllLY HERALD
PALESTINE TEXAS WEDNESDAY14FTERN00N MAY 6 1908
POLICE ARE MYSIIFIEDIIG FIRE IN HOUSTON
Special to the Herald
La Porte Ind May 6 Three more
new graves supposed to contain the
bodies of murder victims were found
on the place of Mrs Belle Gunness
today The sheriff and a number of
deputies are digging out these graves
to get at their secrets The belief is
general that Mrs Gunness is not
dead but that another body has been
substituted for her and that she is
probably on her way to Norway The
headof the body supposed to be Mrs
Gunness is missing The sheriff holds
to the opinion that some of the bodies
already unearthed here are victims
of murder in Chicago and that they
were shipped here to hide the crimes
Anton Olson today identified the
body found yesterday as that of his
daughter Jennie The head had been
cut from the trunk and the body was
badly mutilated
Mrs Christoforson a neighbor of
Mrs Gunness told the sheriff today
that three men who had lived at the
Gunness home within the last year
had disappeared The neighbors sus
pected foul play at the time but in
each case Mrs Gunness told the
neighbors that the men had answered
matrimonial advertisements and that
she was not pleased with them The
officers now hope to have Roy Lamp
her confess shortly He is said to
have admitted running from the Gun
ness farm shortly after the fire start
ed
A later report says the sixth body
was found on the Gunness farm this
morning The lastbody was found at
the side of two holes dug yesterday
and in which five bodies were found
The sixth body was found under cob
ble stones buried about two feet un
Today Destroyed Much Property Be
llJIeved Three People Have Been
Burned to Death
E gclal to the Herald
Houston Texas May 6 Fire today
i the Shaw building caused a fifty
thousand dollar loss and it is be
lieved that a woman and two girls
have been incinerated A search is
being made for the bodies The
Hotel occupied the second
aTyi third floors of the building and
the guests had a very narrow escape
ina hy cases Otis Williams jump
Itifrom the third floor to an awning
d escaped with a broken foot
now</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85052114/1908-05-08/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=body+Matrimonial+Belle+matrimonial+Gun+bodies</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Matrimonial Agents in Chicago
ArrestedSince Gunness Exposure I
I
IIMoro
More Bodies Brought to Light l
Buried on Farm of Female
Blue Beard Near Laporte
IndChicago
Chicago May Sl1nltell States
District Attorney Sims ordered the ar
rest of every manager of any matri
monlal bureau In Chicago following
tho revelations made In connection
with the Gunnesa house of horror
at LaPortc
latorteIllgghig
Illgghig III Chicago
The police department today began
diggmg In the yard of the place occu
pied J y Mrs flounces while she lived
here at 618 Alma street t expecting to I
end bodies It Is bsiloved she prac
tired her profession here
Chicago May 8Mrs Belle Gun
ness of nportc l Ind bought her
poisons In Chicago
She wns positively Identified from
several of her pbotosrapliH and her
official description as a woman who
was frequently seen In the neighbor
hood of Wubash avenue and Harrison
street us recently as four months ago
and who attempted t1 l purchase mor
phine In u drug store at No 309 Wn
burti avenue
avenueMor
lore HiHllcH Found
Iaporte Ind May 8Shorll nf
tar tho search for bodies burled nt the
Gunmss farm was resumed today an
ether skeleton making the tenth on
earthed since Tiu eday was discovered
It I Is Impassible to determine the sex
of tho victim Another confuted
maw or bones was found later The
sheriff believes the gravo contains two
bodies Decomposition has gone so
far It Is difficult to tell whether there
are one or two bodies In the grave
Several bones of another body were
found shortly before noon two foist
from thoeo first found today This
makes three bodies uncovered today
and twelve since Thiirmlay
Ilrsldn the last Imnch I of bones
which showed burns sips a nictnl
frame of a womans pocketbook All
efforts are being made today to find
the skull of the woman body In the
ruins tr the house Ashes In the cel
for are to be screened In the jPort to
find rome part of tho skull
MaxFon a farm hand rays Mrs
GunncsM had planned to have a power
garden this year on the coot hlo
most of the bodies were found
The first skeleton lay In n wooden
box thrle feet under the surface
Other bones arc a few feet jt wny A
pair of womans shoes were In the box
They were heavy fart l of the shoos
were burned Some bones showed
signs of lire The body In Iho box
had been dismembered exactly In the
same way ns thaw pond before Dig
THE REV B S HARR
ADDRESS ATSGI
Writes Here Accepting Inv
vitation and Inquiring
Whether Class is Composed
of Boys or Girls
A letter was received this morning
from the Rev E S IJarrls accepting
Iho Invitation to deliver the High
school commencement address DrHar
DrHllr1rls
rls has not announced lute subject and
explained that ho did not know whoth
er Iho class was ono of toys or girls I
or both Ho will bo Informed and
then will announce his subject
llllslll SH Till lkH
Next wett tho series of business
talks by the business and professional
men will be continued at tho High
choolt Monday morning tho usual
devotional exercises ylll ho l held and
Tuesday morning Mr Saunders A
Fowler becrctnry of tho Commercial
I dub will mako an address Wednes
day morning tho Rev J II Hcnrj
pastor of tho Kentucky AvEnue Pres
byterian church will speak Thurs
day morning John T Donovan gob
oral agent of the Illinois Central will
speak on Tho Relation of Railroads
to the Public Friday morning E
W Whlttomoro wilt speak on Meal
HOljgetatc
ICetate I
Tt9u hers Sleet I
This Afternoon thp i teachers of tho i
heldtheir
public schools held their regular
monthly meeting Tho schools were I
Dismissed at noon and the pupils had
a holiday Superintendent Carnagey
will explain to the teachers tho now
rule adopted bf tho school hbard of
having physical examinations before u
teacher may teach In the schools
In thl1 Schools
Tho High school boys have post
poised their mock trial from tonight
until Tuesday The defense asked 1
w J f ft h
I
gers have found three moro depres
tstone These are In addition to more
than a dozen which are yet opened
Olaf Limbo who came from Nor
way to marry Mrs Gunness Is be
lieved jo bo ono of the early victims
Ho arrived here shortly after her sec
and husband died Ho disappeared
suddenly niter being here two weeks
Tho woman said ho returned to Nor
way A school teacher Jennie Gar
wood said Myrtle Dimness told her
that her mother whipped her became
she went to the basement of tho house
This happened tho day before the
fire
Nothing In Trunk Story
Sheriff Smutzer has been investi
gating the trunk question Mrs Gun
ness was supposed to havo received
numerous trunks from Chicago ex
pressed and checked to her
IlverymeaIn
In La Porte said the sheriff find the
railroad stations and express offices
after having had every driver In the
city Interrogated and the records of
the express companies n examined close
ly I can find proof of only one deliv
crt having been made to Mrs Gun
new home This was a bushel of JMJ
tatoes a year and a half ogo
1 I am convinced that these mur
dent were committed In her house und
by her
herThis
This seems to bo tho reasonable
theory and tho Idea of a connection
between Mrs Gunness and some sort
ot a society for human slaughter In
Chicago appears highly Impracticable
PBc Is known to havo killed at least
one and probably four of her own
household not mentioning her second
husband whom she saw fit to bury
In LnPorte cemetery Jnstead of her
garden She Is known to have had
many visitors and a succession of
form hands whoso dlsappoarotitpj
arc not accounted for
The Lure of Drtitli
La Porto Ind May 8 Following
Is Mrs Gunnels matrimonial nd1
with which victims were lured to
deathPersonalComely
Personal Cornell widow who
owns largo farm in one of tho finest
districts In iJiPorto l county Indiana
desires to make tho acquaintance of
gentleman equally well provided with
views of Joining fortunes No replies
by letter considered unless sender Is
willing to follow answer with per
sonal visit I
During tho sheriffs absence twp
men thought to bo front Michigan
City caused considerable apjireheri
slon by breaking Into the carriage
home on tho Guinness farm whoro
thin nlno cadvcrs havo been kept
since their exhumation Tho men I
raised a window of the building and
ono of them had already mado his
way Into the morgue when dlscov I
Continued on Page Eight f
IS WILL DELIVER</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063756/1908-05-08/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=farm+Belle+death+Gunness</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Eleven Bodies Found Buried in
Farmhouse Yard.
HAD BEEN MURDERED.
Anxiety of John Helgelein Over Dis
appearance of His Brother Leads
to Discover}- of Murdered Bodies
of Two Men, a Woman juid Two
Children in Yawl of Woman Re
cently Burned to Death.
A dispatch from Laparte, Ind., s?/s
one of the most grewscme murder
mysteries ever unearthed in that sec
tion of the country came to light
Tuesday when the bodies of five per
sons, all of Urem murdered, were
found in the yard in the home of
Mrs. Belle Gunness, who, wittr three
of her children was burned to death,
on the night of April 28:
So far only two of the bodies have
been identified. These are Andrew
Helelee, who came to that city front
Aberdeen, S. D., for the purpose of
marrying Mrs. Gunness, whose ac
quaintance he had made through a
matrimonial bureau. Tht other is
that of Jennie Olson GunneSs, a-Chi
cago girl, who had been adopted by
Mrs. Gunness. She disappeared in
September, 1906, and it was said had
gone to Los Angeles to attend school.
The other bodies were those of a.
man and two children, apparently 13
years old.
The body of Helgenein was dis
membered and the arms, legs, trunk
and head were buried in different
parts of th yard. It is believed by
the authorities that Guy Lamphere,
who has been under arrest since the
burning of the Gunness home, on
the charge of murdering Mrs. Gun
ness and her family, committed the
Helgelein crime, Lamphere is a car
penter and the manner in which tho
body of Hlgelcin was dismembered
leads to the belief that it was done t
by somebody familiar with the use
of a saw.
In some quarters it is believed that
Mrs. Gunness may have known some
thing of the murderers of the five,
people.
A possible solution of the Gunness I
farm mystery, which was deepened
Wednesday when four additional bod
ies were found in the barn yard, de
veloped Wednesday night. Evidence
tending to show that the nine dis
membered corpses une arthed Tues
day and Wednesday had been ship
ped to Laporte, probably from Chi
cago, came to light. The testimony
of draymen who had carted trunks
and boxes to the Gunness home lent
color to this supposition. The La
porte police also received information
that two trunks, consigned to ,'Mrs.
Belle Gunness, Laporte, Ind." are
help in an express office in Chicago.
Two of the nine mutilated bodies
were identified with reasonable cer
tainty. Anton Olson, of Chicago,
viewed the body supposed to be that
of Jennie Olson, 16 years old, foster
daughter of Mrs. Gunness, and pro
nounced it to be that of his daughter.
A sister of the girl, Mrs. Leo Olan
der, of Chicago, confirmed the
father's identification.
Ask K. Helegein. whose inquires
regarding his missing brother, An
drew, led to the first dscovesies on
the death haunted farm, became sure
that the largest and best preserved
of the corpses is that of his brother.
Against this identification, however,
is the result of the autopsy perform
ed on this body by Dr. J. H. Meyer.
He found conditions which, to hia
mind, proved that the man perished
long after Andrew Helegein disap
peared last January. Dr. Meyer said
the corpse showed evidence of having
been in the ground less than two
weeks. Ask Helegein, however, re
fused to be convinced by these find
ings, and hisNcertainty led the coroner
to accept his 'Identificatlcn for the
-present.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1908-05-10/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=murder+murderer+Belle+Gunness+murdered+MURDER+human+Murder+bodies</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>IM DIGUP W MURDER M MURDERResidenfis ORDER GADM GADMEesidcnts GAltDENResi
Eesidcnts Resi ents of f laporte Expect 1 C t toFinrMore to toFind toFind
Find FinrMore More Bodies BodiesHistory BodieslIhtory BodiesIhtory
History of Strange Woman and andScene andScene aiidScenci
Scene Enacted at Her Home Com Coming ContIng Cornlug
ing to Light Ltgl1tCJ1Rrncter Character Study of ofthe ofthe ofthe
the Murderess for Revenue OB n Re Revealcd Raealet ItOvealed

vealcd ealet l by y Neighbors oIIibox Who for forYears f forYeur r rYears
Years Had Shunned Htir HtirLaporte UtIILaporte Et EtLaporte
Laporte Ind May Iq SL 9There There te no bet better better better
ter way wa of indicating the th demoniacal demoniacalqualities demonlclqualities emofflc1quaftU
qualities quaftU s now no generally ascribed Orbed to Mrs MrsBelie 1118Belle MrsBelle
Belle Gunness hereabouts titan th by saying sayingthat aylngthat sayingthat
that that when it was announced at nightfall nightfalltoday nlghtfaIltoday nightfalltoday
today that no more bodies had been dug dugup dugup iugup
up in that garden gard ot death on the Gun Qtnvnese GunnS Gunne
nese nS ne place everybody in Laporte was sur surprises surprhie surprie
prises prisesAlways prhieAlways prieAIwys
Always in her lifetime Jl etlnae suspected and andfeared andfred andfenred
feared the woman has now ow become in the thepublic thepublic thepublic
public mind a perfect paragon of blood bloodlust blCHdluI b1odILt
lust luI craft and nd treachery Apparently Apparentlynobody Atp Anparentinobdy re Uy UyO
nobody O Y would be surprised to leant that thatevery thate thatevery
every e lT square yard of r her ie ftftyacre farm farmis farmIs frrnI
is I sown with the bodies bod of her victims victimsMeantime victimMeantime vlctfmeMelLtIme
Meantime where is Belle Gunness Are Arethose Aretboe Aree Arefragments
those fragments of a female body that thatlie UNitlie thatHo
e
lie in the morgue charred past recogni recognition recognition rognition
tion tion really hers hers or are re they tbetthe the remains remainsof rem remainsof Ju Juor
of some one more of t her beclettms victims fJetIIM intended intendedto
to throw dust in the th eyes of the police policeuntil policeunUI policeuntil
until the multimurderer multlmu er makes good her herescape herI herescape
I
escape pe
Mystery Mystor Is 1 Xot ot Cleared ClearedThere ClenrctlThere ClearedLbsre
There are so many drcumwances to tosupport toqpport toiPPOrt
support iPPOrt either theory that the case re remains re remains reflalns
mains today ae mysteriof myeter1uas ae it was last lastTuesday JutTueadQ lastTuesday
Tuesday when the murder garden yielded yieldedup yieldedup Yieldedup
up its first grim fruit fruitMeanthna fruitMIDtfma fruitManthnn
Meanthna certain things thIa stand nd out as asfacts astacbrhanl astactsbax1
facts tacbrhanl hard and brutal facts that cannot cannotbe e JlltOtbe rnwt rnwtbe
be explained expl led away awaySince awarSlnca awaySince
Since little Dun Hudson and ad Joe Max Maxson Muson Maxson
son got to work with their pinks and andspades andspades I
spades spad five day days ago they ha hevs re dog d g ap apwhat wPbat upwhat
what bat the doctors s y are re tile remnants reeinan of often otlen often
ten human hoW bodies bodiespit bodiespour I IlWr
pour of them Wit Jit 1 1lilt laj lajpit
pit about tour 1ty byOnly ay s vfyft vfyftOnly it itOnly
I I1Itd
Only three of them have been identi identified identifled
fled with any certainty The first was wasAndrew wasAndrew wasAndrew
Andrew K Ii I Heigelltn HIiIU a mWdJesged Nor Norwegian Norwectan Norwegtaii
wegian lured from his home botM at Alter Aberdeen Alterdeen Aerdent
deen S Dak by the expectation of mar marriage marriare marrIie
riage with the welltodo widow widowTh wtdowThe widowThe
Th The second was as O C Budsberg an anelderly anelderly 11 11elderly
elderly farmer from lola Wis The same samebait amebait samebait
bait brought him to his death The last lastof Jutof lastof
of the three identified J nttled bodies was Jennie JennieOlson JennieOl8on JennieOlson
Olson an eighteenyearold ei bteenJear I girl and od the theadapted theadeptH thede
adapted de daughter of Delta GtaRn ua tunasua a All AJ1the Allthe 1 1tbe
the remaining six whose ho bodies bod this tb tr trrinla tar11b18 tsrriNe
rinla little garden has yielded were men menwith menwith
4 with a single sinr exception and when that that1s thatis
1s 1 said sal ia all that is known of them has hasbeen basbeen hasbeen
been stated
statedAH
AH Ten ici Are Slain SlainThat SIuluThat SlainThat
That all ten of these were murdered murderedthere murderedthete murderedthere
there IB no doubt As 4 to the four whose whosebodies whoHbodies whosebodies
bodies were found foa buried beneath the theruins theruins theruins
ruins of the house on the morning of ofApril ofApril ofArt1
April 28 2S there is some doubt Three of ofthem orthem ofthem
them were children of this JJueretta Bor Borgia Borgia Borgte
gia of Laporte Laportetwo two girls and a boy boyMyrtle boyMyrtJe boyMyrtle
Myrtle aged a eleven Lucy nine and andPhilip andPbllip andPhilip
Philip five In the identity of the fourth fourthlies fourthlies fourthlies
lies the solution of t the problem problemMurder problemurder problemMurder
Murder urder for revenue only was apparent apparently
j ly the passion that consumed Belle BII Gun Gunness GunneaL Ginacm
ness That several of her victims were werepersons werepersons werepersons
persons from whose death she could got gotprofit getprofit gotprofit
profit in a pecuniary p way in no man manner manner mannet
ner controverts c ntrover8 this statement In every everycase everycue everycase
case of wholesale murder there have hll been beensome bMnsome beensome
some victims who died because their theiralienee theirstlen theirsilence
silence stlen e was deemed more precious than thangold thangold thangoki
gold In such a position Jennie J nne Olson Olsondoubtless 0150ndoubUea Olsondoubtless
doubtless found herself This adopted adopteddaughter lutOptOOdaughtfr nooptoddaughter
daughter was a simpleminded quiet girl girlwho girlwho girlwho
who was known to the neighbors Jlet bors chiefly chieflybecause cbiefi30auae chieflybecause
because auae she did more work than any anyhired anyhired anyhired
hired man She was liS BoDe Gunness pret pretty pretty pretty
ty slave And yet the mistress feared the theslave Utelave theslave
slave lave So the slave died and vs buried buriedin burledIn buriedin
in quicklime in the same death garden gardenthat gardenthai gardenthat
that had received the bodies of others otherswho othersr otherswho
r who died because they had money moneyNot moneyNot moneyNot
Not Attractive Personally PersonallyWhat Pcronnllyat PersonallyWhat
What at sort of woman was this Astound Astounding stoundlug
in lug murderer That is a hard question questionand questfoand questionand
and yet something can be done toward towardanswering towardaDIIWertDl towardanswering
answering She Sh was a Norwegian who wholacked wholacked wholac
lacked lac ed about two years of the halfcen halfcentury haItcentury halfcontury
tury mark She Sb was born in Norwayf1MI Norway Norwayend Norwayand
end came ean to America as a young girl In InMocfo InQqo Inhi
Mocfo Qqo m In uji she married Max l x Soren Sorenson Sorenson Sorenson
son fellowcountryman He died sud suddenly suddenly cuddenly
denly In UM UMTwo 1MTwo IISOTwo
Two years later she married Gunness GunnessHe GunnessHe GunnessS
S He also died suddenly as will be seen seenDeath sennt
t 1 Death De th sudden and mysterious attended attendedBelle attend attendedBells d dBelle
Belle dimness for many years When Whenshe Whenshe Whenshe
she came to Laporte six years ago with withGunnesfi withGo withOjinnees
Go Gunnesfi nn ees Mrs Gunnass was a a fat coarse coarsefeatured coareefeatured coarsefeatured
featured woman who stood about five flvofeet tlvofeet fivefeet
feet seven and nd welShed about 230 pounds poundsShe poundsShe poundsShe
She had a big heavy head a mop of ofcoarse ofeoarse ofcoarse
coarse hair of a muddy brown little eyes eyesthat ayestbat eyesthat
that just missed being black huge hands handsand handsand handsand
and arms but feet grotesquely small for forthe forthe forthe
the burden burd n they they had to o support Every Everybody Everybody Everybed
body bed who knew her agrees that she was wasffcr wasfar wasfar
far from attractive attractiveMost attractlnMost attractiveMost
Most of her acquaintances desorlbe her heras herf heras
f as repulsive repulsiveSomo Some of her neighbors go gofurther gofurther gofurther
further Moro a devil than a woman Wmanwas womanwas womanwas
was the way William Desslelen put it itand 1t 1tand itand
and he ought to know because bis hlstarm hlstarmis farm farmis
is next to tho Gunness place placeCordial placeOortllal placeCortIlal
Cordial at First Only OnlyMy OnlyMy OnlyMy
My aunt was always a strange strangewoman strangewoman strangewoman
woman her nephew John Lawson told toldthe toldtile toldthe
the police 1 the other day When you youfirst yoUfirst youfirst
first knew her she would be very V ry cordial cordialThen cordialThen cordialThen
Then she would get offish offishShe offishShe oflishShe
She has alweys been offish to say the theleast theleast theleast
least in Laporte Her home for years yearsContinued yoorS yoorSontln yearContinued
Continued ontln ed on Pope 3 Column S SSome SSome 5Some
Some lumber firms 1Jrm say ay times vrlUBooa vrlUBooabe wlUsoobe 11100 11100be
be better and are holding up pricea prl prIccsh
h
0
THE THER9LL ROLL OF DEATH DEATHIN DEATHIN DEATHIN
IN THE GUNNESS CASE CASEFeJteving CASEFelleMn CASEFellewin
FeJteving Fellewin u is the roster of bodJes BO far farfound farfo farf
found f d at the t e murder m rdw factory r of Mrs 1rt Gun Gunness Gunneeta Gunne5
ness neeta ne5 IB Laporte Ind IndMYRTLE IndIYRTL lad3IYRTLB
MYRTLE IYRTL SOUEXSON teed eleren elerendaughter elenDdaUhter eletendaughter
daughter of Mrs In Gunnws burned to death deathin deathIn th thIn
in the Gumesj Gum aa home brcheLUCY homeLUCY borneLUCY
LUCY SORBNSON SORB SON tged red nine joungost joungostdaughter J ouneat ouneatdaughter DfIst DfIstdaughter
daughter ef a Mrs Gmmess who likewise likewisewas Itkew1Jwas ltkewiaaras
was ras burned to death in the fire firePHILIP fi fiPHILIP firePRILIP
PHILIP GUNXfcSS GUNN SS aged fire the son on of ofMra orMu ofMrd
Mra GwneM GIi burned in the destruction of ofthe ofthe ofthe
the Gai GUDeM e house bouseANDREW 1MaueANDUBW houseANDIIIW
ANDREW HBLGELEIN aged fifty fiftybachelor fertrlIae futybatheior
bachelor lIae elor of Aberdeen S S Dak tuitar for ftrMB ferMI8 forMa
MB Onions GI II8M1 bend who came to Laporte LaporteJaiwarj LaporteJanlu LaporteJanuary
January Janlu 5 5 1903 100a I9O and disappeared three vwfcs ueea ueea3aer vwfcskter
kter after drawing J3flQO 3Ocfl from bank bankJENNIE hankJBNNIE bankJSN8E
JENNIE OLSON aged seventeen filnteen daugh daught daugittN
tN t r of Anton Olson of Chicago wham rh a Mrs MrsGvMaasa Mrsteok 1ra 1raOvabeM
GvMaasa teok to alas vltea eight years 8US of ofage ofa ofOLE
age a
ageOLE
OLE 014 B BUDSBERG who came from fromIota fromJoIa frernlola
Iota Wk about a year ago in answer to toa toa toa
a matriiwatel mairim rnatr nenisl l adratfceoynt adrertJ5e nt aad wbe he drew drewJl drewfrem drewL5O
Jl L5O DO fi horn m t6 borne bask baakUaUwttiM 1MaIlLU baskUnitlintifiM
UaUwttiM U l body headless of a raman ramansupposed ImnADMIfPtSed wetmamicesed
supposed at that to be Mrs GtiffittM Ou telt teltwfciab ttwld t twhi
wfciab wld nay rne be th tile body of a tlqtlm glaced glacedto J ared aredto ed edto
to delede InTestieaton InTestieatonUnidentified Ine5U fnTettigutonUnklaufteed tOlB tOlBUBdetfliled
Unidentified skeleton doabtkta that of f a aman aman arnan
man manDHWeatifled manU
DHWeatifled U aU cd skeleton supposedly that of ofa ofa ofa
a woman discerned dlio T in sama HD 9 spot as abate abateUaWaHtifl abeuUaUdaUfitd sinceUnMeatiflid
UaUdaUfitd UaWaHtifl d bedy sax ex undetermined undeterminedfwod 1IooetenntedflMlDd undeteenisedfeend
fwod in a Uweefoet hole beteUBWeattfled holeUBWe hoeUnIdeaUfid
UBWeattfled UBWe Ufted bode s HX undetermined wasIad wasfeend was wasfwad
fwad in the the Mme hole holeUnidentified holeUaldenUt1ed holeUnidentified
Unidentified body bed sex undetermined wu wufMBd s sIlid
fMBd ia the same Hm hole holeU holethttdettatd holeUidestlfied
U thttdettatd M itied body dismembered Mlppe seipeasedto pp d dto wd wdto
to be that of a man fwm earn Chicago totted fWDdbteg fOtt fOttbtag tottedlylag
bteg face downward dGnmudin in hxsbm tax buried te been bwaIK 1MIn1let beenlot
IK X XUnidentified
letUnldllfttiW
Unidentified body pawlMf scan of middle middleag middleaPt rnlddleage
aPt ag T Jt1C8t9nd corered from barnyard b fI 0mT craTe hi ad adraaetd adTaaoed adasasd
raaetd asasd state of d disintegration dblnupa6oUnldeetiied disintegrationUntdeatkd tntesrftOoa tntesrftOoaUnidefitifted
Unidefitifted body probably ably womaa FoaaH takes UkeeTrith bte1rlth takeswith</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn95069780/1908-05-14/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=murder+Lamphere+Gunness+Gun+guns+CHRONOLOGY+murders+Guns</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Wholesale murder murder more
ruthlessly premeditated and diabolical
ly executed than the famous Holmes
castle crimes in Chicago was revealed
at Laporte Ind. Tuesday when five
mutilated bodies were dug up in the
back yard of the home of Mrs. Bella
Gunness who together with her three
children are supposed to have met
death when their house burned one
week before.
Fifteen persons already have a place
on the list of known or probably slain
and circumstances point to Mrs. Gun-
ness as the arch-conspirator in at least
twelve of the crimes. Until this time it
i had been accepted as true that she and
j her three children had met death in the
fire that destroyed their home but now

the suspicion arises that the bodies that
p
were found in the smoldering ruins
were brought from some hospital or
medical school for the purpose of cre-
j ating the belief that Mrs. Gunness and
her family had pas.sed from existence.
Ijixt of l\uo\vii A'iotims.
ITclgoloin. Andrew 40 years old. bach
elor. Aberdeen S. D. suitor for Mrs.
Guunoss hand who came to Laporto in
January and disappeared ono mouth later
after loaning the woman $1.500 body
dug up to-day.
Gunness Jennie Olson. 16 years old
adopted daughter of Mrs. Gunness disap
peared in September IfXKi. ostensibly to
attend school at Los Angeles body dug
up to-day.
Unidentified man believed by Sheriff
Smul/cr to have been an admirer of the
woman.
Unidentified boy. apparently 8 years
old mutilated body in gnnnysack.
Unidentified girl about 7 years old
mutilated body in gunnysaek.
Gunness Joseph husband of Mrs. Gun-
ness whose death at Laporte four years
ago had always remained a mystery.
Sorensen Mads woman's first hus
band who died under mysterious circum
stances in Chicago eight years ago.
Gunness Mrs. Bella believed to have
been burned to death in fire which de
stroyed lier home.
Sorensen Myrtle. 11 years old eldest
daughter of Mrs. Gunness thought to
have perished in the fire.
Sorensen Lucy Q years old another
daughter also believed to have been a
victim of the fire.
Gumiess. Philip 5 years old. youngest
child said to have been killed in the tiro.
Lindblom. Olaf. 35 years old. of Wis
consin employed by Mrs. Gumiess on the
farm. When ho. disappeared Mrs. Gun-
ness gave it out that he had gone to
Norway.
Gorhalt Eric. 40 years old. of Wiscon
sin worked five months for Mrs. Gun-
ness then he disappeared.
Man from Ohio. 50 years old. name
not learned worked on the farm and
owned a horse and buirny. Dis-appoarod
and Mrs. Gunness fell heir to the horse
and buggy.
la the arrest of liay Laniphere a
CHRONOLOGY OF INDIAHA
JrlULTI-MUKDER MYSTERY.
Mads Albert Sorensen Austin. 111. dies
mysteriously V.OO His widow col
lects $8,500 insurance.
Candy store at Kli/.aboth btreet and
Grand avenue. Chicago owned by Soron-
sons burns. Insured.
Two peculiar files in Austin home. In
surance collected.
Widow marries Joe Gumiess- Moves
to Laporto farm. Adopts Jennie ONn
Gumiess killed (1001) Widow s.i\
meat ck-aver fell on his head. Collo'-ts
o,500 insurance.
Ray Lamphere goes to work for Mrs.
Guiltless as hired man.
Widow sets dogs on visitors.
Neighbors see lanterns on farm n 2
a. in.
Jennie Olson disapprs. Real pircnts
are told she is in Ix s Angeles school but
can not find her J1KXJ
Andrew llolgelein Aberdeen S. 1)
aii-swors matrimonial ad and arrive.t
Laporte farm. Loans Mrs. Gunncs 1.-
500. Disappears with like amount in
pockot. Widow says lie wont to Noiw i\
Mrs. Gunnevj HT tolls shonff
strange man killed a child in woods near
farm. Sheriff finds only empty gra\
Ray Lamphere arrested for annoing
Mrs. Gunnels.
Widow tells lawyer April 251 tint
Lamphi'ie intends to kill her. Draws up
will.
Home burns April I'.G. Bodies of thro
children and headless woman found in
ruins.
Lamphere arrested in hollow tiv. h d
in r.
M.iA. K. ib-it'li in Im i- li ill- of
brother bunod near hoii o. Jennie 'SCM\
body also found.
Nine unidentified bodies of men and
ihihlron are found buried near house.
Most bodies lie on mattresses under four
feet of earth.
May j. Joe Ma\soii. farm hand tolls
police he dus holes on orders of Mrs.
Gumiess. but never filled them.
J-Xpres mon toll jx lko of mysterious
arrhal at farm of many bis trunks.
former servant of the woman. Sheriff
Smulzer believe some liirht may be
thrown upon the circumstances sur
rounding the deaths of at least some
of the victims.
Lamphere before the fire had trouble
with Mrs. Gunnos.s. Uo had declared
about town she was trying to "iret rid"
of him because he knew too much. He
has told several conilictini stories
concerning his relation with the wom
an and his presence in the neighbor
hood of the Gunness home the night it
burned.
The discovery of the Ixnlies led ex-
pressim'ii to tell of the delivery of five
trunks to the Guiines-s farm during the
last six months. This fact has caused
the authorities to incline to the theory
that the place may have been a "clear
ing-house" for murders. They suspect
that wealthy person after being lured
to Chicago and killed may have l een
packed into thc-c trunks sent to La
porte and disjio etl of there. Lamphere
in his cell declared Mrs. Gunness fre-
nivntly asked him to buy poison for
her. She wanted chloroform he said.
Four of the bodies were found buried
in a refuse pile about 150 feet from the
house while another body was duir
up within a few teet of the ruined
home. It is he opinion of Coroner
Mack and physicians who examined the
bodies that th 'y were burned after
death. Ilelirelein was easily identified
by his brother although the remains
had been badly mutilated. The body
of the other man show- red mustache.
The discovery of the bodies primarily
was due to the efforts of Mr. llelge-
j
AXDIUEW
HELOGOEJ
JO UN
HELDfinitf

T cr @ft i
'teF feaiJ
lein of Mansliehl SD. brother f
Andrew The lormer bad known of
bis brother"- i rn sp ndence with Mrs.
Gtmness and of the latter's trip to
LaP H-te. When the brother armed
in I.ajKjrte he demanded a thorfnuh
.search of the CJunness' premises. Two
weeks- ago he had been informed in a
letter written by Mrs. Gunness that
his brother had gone to Norway.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84028490/1908-05-22/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=murder+Belle+Gunness+murdeiess+Insured+murders+Insurance</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Laporte, Ind., May 20. Acting on
private information, Mayor Darrow, of
counsel for Ray Lamphere, who will
be indicted for the murder of Mrs.
Belle Gunness and her three children
and Andrew Helgoleln, of Aberdeen,
S. D tonight entered Into communi
cation by cable with the police ot
Scotland Yard, London, and the au
thoritles in Canadian cities, advising
ttKsm of tho reward of $1000 which
will be paid by Laporte county for tha
finding of tho murdeiess Following
his declaration that tho teeth Identi
fied as those of Mrs. Gunness are in
too perfect condition to have been In
the fierce blaze which destroyed the
head, and charred, baked and burned
the rest of the body, Mayor Darrow,
also took steps to consult with experts
upon whom he relies to disprove tho
identification of tho teeth. Coronor
Mack added the weight of his opinion
that Mrs. Gunness' body was that
found In the ruins of tho charnel
house when ho tonight officially de
clared: "It is my verdict that the body su
viewed is that of Belle Gunness; that
she camo to her death through felon
ious homicide; and that the perpetra
tor thereof Is to me unknown."
Coroner Mack says that so far as
Andrew lfelgelein, of South Dakota;
Ole Budsberg, of Iola, Wis and Jen
nie Olson, the adopted daughter ot
Mrs. Gunness, aro concerned his ver
dict will be that their bodies wero
properly Identified, that they came tn
their death from unnatural causes,
that they were burned to cover up
murder and that Mjrs. Gunness had a
motive for killing them and was guil
ty either alone or with accomplices
of murder.
Mrs. Henry WItzer of Toledo, walk
ed among the dead at the morgue this
morning hoping that there might bo
somo mark of identification on onn of
the skeleton forms which would prova
that her daughter was one of the vic
tlms of the house of tragedy. Tears
rioursed down tho mother's cheeks as
she looked upon the headless and dls
membered bodies. There was no Iden
tification, but the Toledo woman, hop.
ing that some tragedy might solve
the mystery of her daughter's strange
disappearance, came to Laporte like
scores of others, In the hope that the
Gunness murders would unfold th3
mjstery which she has vainly labored
to solve since 3902, when Frances
Witzler, young and pretty, a college
graduato with life before her, left
her home never to return.
Mrs. Witzler believes her daughter
met death in the charnel house.
The grand jury is making splendid
progress In the taking of evidence.
Theie is a disposition on the part of
the stato's attorney, Smith, to conclude
the labors of tho body of inquisition
not later than Friday, when the 'ndict
ments against Ray Lamphere w '11 un
doubtedly be returned.
With tho reading of tho Swedish
committal service tho skeleton of Jen
nie Olson, was this afternoon lowered
Into a grave at Patton's cemetery.
The plot of giound in which she lies
adjoins tho burial place of Andrew
Helgoleln.
Dr Martin received tort? from
Washington a letter descrlb o. wo-
.id be.
TWO DAY TICKETS
TO
1
3 T3jR.fjHJ' TKP- 5
JJk I
ash nit: whcvumij.
EVERY SATURDAY AND SUNDAY.
T&amp;0 ROUND
JB.I
man seen on tne street in'
lioved'by tho writer to b -4 o. Gun
ness. The man does .five his
name, but says he saw oman ho
describes on tho oven y if May 13,
at 15th stivet and .cot, before
he ever saw a pictu o tho l-aporte
murderess. ij
Attorney Worde the defense, la
still a firm bolievei tho theory that
Mrs. Gunness made her escape. Ho
claims tha a woman to thoroughly
ei&amp;ed with the instincts of criminal
ity, as she, would resort to such!
means of diverting suspicion "She
could very easily havo a dentist re
movo those plates from her mouth,"
ho declares, "and leave thorn as sho
left tho lings, near the bodies found
In" tho basement ot her house."
The searching of tho debris today
brought another gold ring to light.
It bears the initials "S. B., May 28,
1907," and It may prove a factor in
solving the identltv of another body.
States Attorney Smith stated to
night on emerging from tho ;rand
Jury room that he would ask for tho
lndlrtment of Ray Lamphere on six
counts. Four for the murder ot Mrs.
Gunness and her three children, ono
us accessory in tho Wiling of Andrew
Helgeleln and one for arson.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86069458/1908-05-28/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=fire+BELLE+GUNNESS</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>RAY LAMPHERE, WIDOW GUNNESS' FARM HAND.
Hay I.ainphere under arrest (it LuMrte, lud on suspicion of U'lng concerned
Iij tin burning of tliu farmhouse of Mrs. Belle Gtinness nnd the murder
of the Gunnes children nnd tlielr mother, formerly wns employed us ii fnnn
baud by the Widow Ounness. It Is ulleged thnt he made love rli her nnd wn
repulsed, Mrs. Ounness twlng on the trull of men with money who were
Vengeance and Jealousy an- alleged an motive for burning
the house and destroying the fnmll.v Lniuphere stoutly asserts his Innocence
nnd declare that lie "always thought there was something wrong at
that place." inetttdng the Outlines fann He toltl the authorities thnt aUmt
two yenn ago a large man caiue to the farmhouse who was wild by Mr.
Gunnes to lx) a BUltor for the hand of her adopted daughter. Jennie Olsen,
and flint he never kneu uhnt Uiiwie uf the man. Miss Olson's tvly w:im
one f Uhm found burled n the premium, along with eight others. When
CHiiitht I jiii phetv wrm hiding In a hollow tree.
t
X
RUINS 0? GUNNESS HOUSt, LAFORTE.
I'ie inrinliiui of Sirs Belie Gtmtic a n.i e frem Luporte. Iml., was
totally destroyed by lire on the night of April 1!7 This lire led to the discovery
of the nine IhmIIos of munler tlrtlms burled on the premises and developed a
crime mystery which linn horrllled the nation. The house was built of brlok,
with an addition built of lumber. Joseph Muxson, the hired man, slept In n
room nlKivM the wooden kitchen, nnd he says thnt lie nuoke nlniiit -1 o'clock
In the timmlui; stlilel by smoke which was pouring out of the brick part of
the house He tried to enter thnt pnrt but could not. Several neighbors who
arrived shortly nIo were driven back by tlntnes The charred bodies of
three children found In the ruins were IdeiitlllHl as thoce of Mrs Guntiess.
while the Ixxly of a woman, from which the head was missing, either burned
off or decapitated prior to the fire, wap believed at first to be that of Mrn.
(Junnosi. Kulweiiuent disclosures ns to the "murdt r farm" lead some to
believe thnt Mm. (jiinness plnccd the headless trunk of n murdered woman
In the house to serve nn a blind In effecting her own escne from Justice.
w
JOStrt, .viAaSON, WHO WAo EMPLOYED BY MRS. GUNNESS,
Josupti Muxhon, who was employed ab man of all work around tho house
and farm of Mm. Helle Ounness near Luporte, lud., poluted out to the authorities
certulu Hpots In the yard of the burned farmhouse where, he said, he hud
bceu Instructed by Mrs Gutfliesa from tlmo to time to deposit such rubblah
ns was to be thrown nway. The nine bodies of persons supposed to bur
Oecu murdered by Mrs. dunness were dug up at points Maxson Indicated.
-Jl
T l" i-
tH .ii.)-"
HH9t$M sis1
MI. I MI tfysi
BWPBBff StEP Wf;. fWp 'iff j&amp;mKk 4
UVKKSKmi
K0&amp;J;fcl2?imfij
nntHjiUM
Bw 1ft
iBofH
ASSv VT7"
rag
SS24"
18? KUCKilg r"
3
'v&amp;3 ossa a
MRS. BELLE GUNNESS, OF LAPORTE'S MURDER FARM.
Mrs. Jlelle Ounness, tho widow mispWed of the murder of the persons
whose iKvlles were dug npffroui Uio premlsi of her burnwl home n mile from
Luporte. IntL, waa n Norwegian woman whoso mnltlen name was Tnulson.
She was married first to Mar SorwiHcn, who died under suspicious
Her second husband. Philip Ounness, dlisl under similar
It wnfl'reiwrted at first that the body of Mrs. Ounness was found
with thoso of her threo children In the ruins of her houses. The head of tho
charred remains of tho woman found in the rulas was missing, which fact
caused the Authorities to suspect that Mrs. Ounness herself hnd killed her
children nnd set tire to tho dwelling after placing In the house the decapitated
liody of one of her ndult women rlctlms in nn effort to cause the belief
that sho had perished in the fire. Mrs. Ounness hnd lind an enormous quantity
of gold work done on her teeth The grewsome mystery of the missing
head, It was said by those who held the theory of the flight of Mrs. Ounness,
was explained by the woman's r t! :it 'o left her substitute's head on
the body It would be evident thai k..o her- s not a victim of the fire.
til ''?t
I
IP Ct' v?lK iV'eisJKf.
If 1 Sff
It,9 I Vvife ',mM
IIHwl&amp; vtfHilsEtiyBB
STATE
AT"iu.... ..Of U.
SMITH.
V
f
ANDREW HELGELEIN, ONE OF MRS. GUNNESS' VICTIMS.
One oi tie ...e uhiIi.s disinterred from the premises of Mrs. Belle Ounness,
near Luporte, lud., wns Identllled as thut of Andrew llelgeleiu, a wealthy
stockman of Aberdeen, S. D., forty yours of age. Ho wus a Norweglsui, as wiu
Mrs. Ounness. who had advertised for a prospective husband with means.
Helgeleln stnrtetl for Luporte Jan. .'5, since which date nothiug was heard from
him by lib relatives, who were aware that ho hud gone to the Indiana wldowa
home with matrimonial Intentions. It wns known also that he had drawn
$3,000 from his Aberdeen bank account after arriving at Luporte. The theory
Is that Mrs. Gunness killed Helgeleln to get his money.
MRS. GUNNESS AND HER THREE CHILDREN.
Mrs. Ilelle Gunness, the Indiana woman who Is believed by the police to
have lured to her farm home near Laporte several men on mntrlmonlal pre-1
tenses nnd then murdered them for their money, is said to have been qulto
fond of her three little children, whose charred bodies were found In tho ruins
of tho Gunness farmhouse, along with the headless trunk of n woman, who i
was supposed at first to be the body of tlielr mother. The children wero
Myrtle Sorensen, aged eleven, and Lucy Sorensen, aged nine, daughters of
Mrs. Gunness by her first husband. Max Sorensen, and Philip Gunness, aged
five, namesake of his father, who. like Sorensen. Is said to have died under
suspicious circumstances.
DH. C. F. MACK, CORONER, TAKING NOTES.
Shortly after the discovery' of the first bodies that had been burled on the
premises of tho Widow Gunness near Laporte, Ind., Dr. C. F. Mack, the
coroner, arrived on the scene nnd wns busy taking notes for official use. The
nine bodies of murdered men and women dug up In the yard near the ruins of
the burned farmhouse passed under Dr. Mack's close scrutiny, as did also
those of the three children and the woman found In the ruins. A Jury composed
of physicians thoroughly examined the charred remains of the children
nnd the woman nnd arrived at the conclusion that they were those of Mrs.
Belle Ounness nnd her little ones. It wns Impossible to determine the sex of
five of the bodies disinterred, they hnvlng been dismembered and also partially
disintegrated by quicklime. Mr. Mack made copious notes for reference
In future efforts to solve the horrible mystery nnd Identify the victims, most
of whom are believed to have been men who were lured to the place by tho I
matrimonial advertisements of Mrs. Gunness, who described herself as m
rich widow wanting a husband with some money.
mmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmmjmmmmammmmmmmmmmmtmmmmmfmmmmmmmmmm
JOHN HhLGELEIN, BROTHER Ui- JrJh 0- THE VICTIMS.
Suspicion against Mrs. Belle Ounness was first aroused In Indiana by the
.i,..,i n n.uri,i nt Toim i n n N'orweirinii from Mansfield, S. D.,
who came to investigate the disappearance of his brother, Andrew Helgeleln,
of Aberdeen, S. U. Andrew Helgeleln wus known to hare answered oue of
Mrs. Ounuesa' adrertisements for a husband with money. lie leri Aueruceu
on Jan- 3 to visit Mrs. Gunness nt her home near Laporte. After his arrival
lu Laporte ho had drawn $3.0fX from Ills bnnk in Aberdeen. John Helgeleln,
becoming worried because nothing further was heard from his brother, wrote
to Mrs. Gunness, who replied that Andrew had departed for a visit to Norway.
John Helgeleln Identified we of the first bodies found as that of hH brother.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085190/1908-07-11/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=FARM+Belle+DEATH+Gunness</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>THE LA FORTE MURDER FARM.
There Read
Like a Story- of the Mid-Centuries.
Like a chapter from the bloody rec
ords of the mid-centuries is the ter-
rible story unfolded by the authorities
of La Porte, Ind., where wholesale mur
der was done for years without anyone
knowing or suspecting It. Criminal rec
ords contain nc parallel of the grew
some story revealed in the finding of
the clearing house for murders kept by
Mrs. Belle Gunness near the Indiana
town. Just how many persons met
their fate in connection with the bloody
business carried on there will perhaps
never be known. The skeletons dis
covered on her premises and the fact
that expressmen had many times de
livered to her boxes and trunks now
believed to contain human bodies form
the chief materials for the construction
of the strange story of her career. She
is supposed to have lured rich men to
Jier den by matrimonial advertisements
and then made away with them for
their money, and also to have run a
murder "fence" for the benefit of her
partners in the awful trade of human
slaughter, the latter operating in Chi
cago and sending the bodies of their
victims to her for burial. It is the
theory of the prosecution that Mrs.
Gunness deliberately lured men to
her farm by means of an advertisement
in a Chicago newspaper, in which she
represented herself as an attractive and
amiable widow looking for a mate. She
alleged that she was the owner of a
valuable farm and sought a well-to-do
farmer as a husband. After a visit
from such a candidate she generally in
duced him, it appears, to sell his farm
and come to her with the proceeds of
the sale, at which time she would de
liberately murder him and bury his
V>dy en the premises.
For years this strange woman Is
»«al(1 to have conducted her murder mill.
while her neighbors remarked upon her
good humor and her children mingled
with others of their age in the neigh
borhood. And the end of this record
of. crime and mystery is shrouded In
2*2 JI2I. WIL LIJS/I /TETTER^.
uncertainty. A fire which destroyed
the Gunness borne also disclosed the
fact that her three children had either
been murdered before the fire or that
they had perished in the flames.
In some respects the methods of Mrs.
Belle Gunness seem similar to those
of the infamous Bender family in Kan
sas. Yet it is doubtful if the blood
thirsty Kate Bender in her palmiest
dnjTß was over equal to the awful
crimes that are laid at the door of the
Gunness woman. The story of the La
Porte murder farm recalls the noto-
rioos doings of the Bender family in
Montgomery County, Kan., about forty
years ago, and the famous case of
Henry H. Holmes, who swindled insnr</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87062268/1908-11-27/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=LAMPHERE+ARSON+arson+guilty+GUILTY+RAY&amp;r=-0.436,0.405,1.358,0.491,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>RAY LAMPHERE
rOUND GUILTY
ONLY OF ARSON
Alleged Murderer of Mrs
Belle Gunness and Her
Three Children by Setting
Fire to Their Home Will
Appeal From Decision of I
the Court
By Associated Press
LaPorte Ind Nov 26Ray Lam
phere charged with the murder of
Mrs Belle Gunness and her three chil I
dren by setting fire to the Gunness
home on April 20th was this evening
found guilty of arson by the jury
which had the case since yesterday
Within five minutes after the verdict
was reported Judge Richter had sen
tenced the defendant to the state peni
tentiary at Michigan City for an inde
terminate term of from two to twenty
cm years
Attorney AVorden for the defense
tonight said a inotion ora new trial
Will be made and should it be re
fused an appeal to the Indiana su
preme court will follow Worden de
clared the verdict ridiculous If he is
found guilty at all said he he is
guilty of murder He should be ac
quitted The motion for a new trial
will be based on the courts instruc
tions telling the jurors they coutt
find Lamphere guilt r arson under
the indictment</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058245/1908-12-03/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Belle+Gunness</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Belle Gunness and Children Gets
a Compromise Verdict
Has Been Sentenced to State Prison
for Indeterminate Term of From
Five to Twenty Years and
Fined 5000
Laporlo IndRay Lampherc
charged with the murder of Mrs
Hello Gunnoss and her three children
ly Bolting tiro to tho Gunness home</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89053729/1912-12-18/ed-3/?sp=6&amp;q=belle+gunness&amp;r=-1.419,-0.048,3.837,1.496,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>BELLE GUNNESS I
ISALIOESfIYS
Paroled Convict Asserts Mur
der Farm Proprietress Was
Not Burned.
i
LAPoRTE. IND., De. is b'urther
Investigation of tin murder farm of
Belle Gunness is being considered b>
attorneys interested in the ease follow
ing statement' made by Charles Mey
ers, a paroled convict Meyers was a
confidante of Ray Lampbere while in
prison and says Lamphei.- told him
Mrs Gunness did not dir in the fire that
desttoyed her home.
Instead, she fled at 3 o'clock ;r. the
4% QnSav in^s
No Needless
Red I ape Here
Red tape means useless detail and
formality. It's middle name is Incon-
enience.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84022137/1908-05-28/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=belle+gunness&amp;st=image&amp;r=-1.615,-0.082,4.231,1.649,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>May 22. "It Is my
rerdlct that the body so viewed is
that of Mrs. Belle Gunness, and she
eame to her death through felonious
homicide and that the perpetrator
thereof la to me unknown.
—**C. S. Mack, Coroner."
Such was the verdict rendered late
yesterday afternoon by the coroner.
The official declaration that the body
of the adult female found In the ruins
of the fire of April 28, which destroy
ed the home of Mrs. Belle Gunness,
was that of Mrs. Gunness Is the se
quel to the report Tuesday of Dr. I. P.
Norton, Mrs. Gunness' dentist, that
the bridges holding various false and
gold-filled teeth were those of Mrs.
Gunness. The official finding of the
eoroner will relieve the state's attor
ney of the necessity of proving in
court, should the occasion require,
that Mrs. Gunness is dead.
Other *erdlcts 8oon.
Coroner Mack expects to file ver
dicts in the other deaths in a few
days. This is the first official verdict
In the Gunness case.
All the officials continue to receive
freak letters.
Sheriff Smutzer and Miner Schultz
yesterday afternoon, in sorting the
tailings from the sluice box found a
gentleman's large gold band ring with
the following engraving: "S. B., May
28, 1902." Officers believe this be
longed to ono of tho first victims of
the woman.
Looking for T. Llnd.
Sheriff Smutzer received yesterday
from I. N. Youtsler of Casper, Wyo.,
a razor which he claims be was given
by Jennie Olson one night about a
year ago when he stopped over night
at the Gunness farm. The razor is an
old Swedish make and scratched on
one aide with a knife is the name "T.
Lind, Chicago," and on the reverse
side three links, evidently made to
represent the links of the Odd Fel
lows' emblem. The authorities have
started an inquiry to ascertain if Lind
was murdered.
On Friday, May 29, Executor Fogle
will hold public sale of the personal
property left by Mrs. Gunness. Mu
seum owners from all over the coun
try are clamoring for the things that
will be disposed of that day.
Seven True Bills Against Lamphere.
Laporte, Ind., May 24.—In return
ing seven true bills against Ray Lam
phere yesterday afternoon the La
porte county grand Jury also indicted
Mrs. Bella Gunness for the murder of
Androw Helgelein of Mansfield, S. D.
No warrant was issued for Mrs. Gun
ness, as she was declared officially
dead by the verdict of Coroner Mack,
but in order to vote a true bill against
Lamphere as an accessory in the kill
ing of Helgelein It was necessary to
indict Mrs. Gunness as the principal.
Lamphere now stands before the bar
of justice officially charged with ar
son, five murders and being an acces
sory in the Helgelein murdor.
Votes Separate Billa
Separate bills were votefl agafrist
Lamphere for the murder, in the first
degree, of Mrs. Bella Gunness and
her three children.
In charging Lamphere with the
murder of Andrew Helgelein tho in
dlctment say* that "Ray Lamphere on
J«H. 14, 1908, did unlawfully, felonl
onaly, purposely and with premeditat
ed malice, kill and murder Andrew
Helgelein."
Lampherp was not arraigned, and
this will probably not bo done until
the cases are set for trial. Bench
warrants were served upon Lamphere
In the jail last evening. He express
ed bat alight aurpriae, as the return
ing of the indictment had boon antic
ipated.
Will Bo Tried In June.
Prosecutor Smith said last night
fkat It would be Imposible to reach
tbe Lamphere casos until lata In
Juno.
The digging yesterday, under the
SborUf Smutxer, resulted
a human skull,
belonged to one
dug tip in the
two weeks ago. Long
S la const*
*8 was U|alt of a.
KlHad at Ball fernfe
l||qt tbo midst of
in Hasol-
i Z.
"T Vfr*
-i i*
MAN SEEKS LOST BROTHER
lola (Wis.) Mao Identifies Watch—Ar
kansas Man Says Mrs. Gunness
Escaped ia Male Attire.
Laporte, Ind., May 27.—Mrs. Ttetta
Gunness had accomplices. This was
satisfactorily learned last night when
Martin Gurhelt of Iowa, Wis., arrived
to investigate the disappearance of
his brother, Henry Gurholt, who left
lola in April, 1905, to go to Laporte
to work on Mrs. Gunness' farm. Mar
tin says that early in April, 1905, a
stranger came to lola. He formed
the acquaintance of Henry Gurholt.
The stranger talked of the beauties of
I.aporte, said he had a sister, Mrs
Eella Gunness, who was In need of
such a man on the farm. The result
was that Henry Gurholt left for Lap
porte.
Drops Out of Sight.
He arrived here on April 12, 1905,
He wrote home regularly to his par
ents, but after a letter written July
4, 1905, they heard no more from
him. He said nothing about leaving
Mrs. Gunness' farm, but in December,
when Martin Gurholt wrote and made
Inquiries for his brother, the woman
replied that he had left, had gone to
Chicago with some horse traders, and
if he had not returned home she fear
ed that he might have been waylaid,
murdered and robbed in Chicago, for
he had some money with him.
Identifies Watch.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063624/1896-12-05/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=muder&amp;r=0.081,0.304,0.77,0.295,0</id>
				<rel>0</rel>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045004/1899-02-28/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=muder&amp;r=-1.397,-0.082,3.795,1.456,0</id>
				<rel>0</rel>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82002441/1910-02-16/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=belle+gunness&amp;r=-0.012,0.47,1.159,0.445,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>IS IT MRS. GUNNESS?
MANKATO MAN LOCATES SUS
PECT IN KANDIYOHI CO.—
URGES ARREST.
SAYS SHE IS BROTHER’S SERVANT
jidiana Authorities Send An Officer
to Willmar to Attempt to Identify
Suspect as Famous
Murderess.
Willmar. —That Mrs. Belle Gunness
of the La Porte, Ind., murder farm
tame, is actually alive and within a
few miles of this city, is the allegation
of Samuel Kirby of Mankato. Further
more, Mr. Kirby believes that the wo
man Is now housekeeping in the family
of his brother, Gus Kirby, a prosperous
farmer.
Samuel Kirby arrived in this (Kan
diyohi) county last Thursday evening,
Intent upon securing the arrest of the
woman, who is known by the name of
Mrs. Vallie Casey.
The county officers do not put much
credence in the rumor.
Severa) reputable persons who have
seen the suspected woman are loath
to admit that she bore any resem
blance to Mrs. Gunness.
Samuel Kirby, senior, of Mankato, is
the only one who believes that the
housekeeper and the unaccounted for
murderess are the same. It is at Sam
uel Kirby’s instigation that Samuel
Ball, a representative of the police de
partment of La Porte, Ind., arrived
here with a warrant for the arrest of
Mrs. Gunness.
The detective is supplied with a de
tailed description of Mrs. Gunness and
made the first official comparison of
the physical characteristics of the two
women. The La Porte authorities did
not agree to run down the Willmar
rumor until Samuel Kirby had guar
anteed the expense of their transporta
tion.
Gustavus Kirby sold the Kandiyohi
county farm last week to Samuel Gar
ver of Willmar for SIO,OOO. Mrs.
Casey, the housekeeper was present
during the negotiations. It is said that
both she and her employer expressed
their intention of going to California
as soon as all of the property was dis
posed of. Sheriff Peter Bonde of this
county is not of th* opinion that Mrs.
Casey is the much-wanted woman.
In Willmar Samuel Kirby at times
refers to himself as a detective and
is prone to discuss the inability of the
police to catch criminals. He refers
to statistics and say that only two
murderers out of every 100 are evei
caught and that the country Is spend
Ing billions of dollars uselessly for
protection It does not receive.
Son Opposes Father’s View.
Mankato. —Samuel Kirby, Jr., ths
son of Samuel R. Kirby, the man who
claims that Mrs. Belle Gunness, th*
alleged La Porte mure .ess is em
ployed as a domestic on his brother’s
farm near Willmar, is inclined to be
lieve that his father is on the wrong
track and that the woman at Willntar
is not the much-sought Mrs. Gunness.
According to young Kirby his uncle
in Willmar engaged the housekeeper,
who is now in the limelight, at a St.
Paul employment agency.
About two months ago, mutual
friends of the two brothers wrote to
the brother residing at Mankato, and
insisted that he proceed at once to his
brother’s home.
Thinking the situation serious he at
once left for his brother’s farm and
remonstrated with him for keeping the
woman as a housekeeper. After re
maining at the farm for two days, dur
ing which time the brothers continual
ly wrangled, they parted in an angry
mood, the one remaining on his farm
and the other returning to Mankato.
Samuel R. Kirby, the father acci
dentally noticed the picture of Mrs.
Gunness recently in an old newspaper
and was immediately impressed by
what he thought a great likeness be
tween the La Porte woman and his
son’s housekeeper.</text>
			</result>
		</results>
	</topic>
	<topic>
		<id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-assassination-franz-ferdinand</id>
		<results>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Ferdinand</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Vienna. .Tune 28. The following de?
tails of the assassination of Archduke
Francis Ferdinand and his wife arc
now available. At 10 a. m. the arch?
duke, with the duchess, left the mili?
tary camp in an automobile for the
Town Hall. The car halted for some
minutes while a number of young
girls in festive attire greeted the heir
i.pparent and the duchess, who accept?
ed some flowers from them and spoke
a few kindly words.
The car moved on, but ?earctl'y had
it gone more than a few yards when a
man, who has since been identified as a
printer named Gabrlnovics, sprang out
from the crowd and hurled a bomb
full at the royal car. The archduke
himself warded it off w.th his arm
and it fell at the back of the car and.
rebounding on the roid, exploded.
The automobile had by this time
moved s?ve ?1 yari. and the full force
of the exp ision fell on the following
automobi.??, which contained four mem?
bers of the Archduke's suite. They
were Count Boos-Waldeck, Baron
Ilummerskireh, Countess von Lanjus,
lady in waiting, and Lieutenant Colo?
nel von Merizzi, aide-de-camp.
The last named received a splinter
in the neck and was badly hurt. The
royal chauffeur, at the direction of the
Archduke, immediately brought the
car to a standstill. In the mean time
the would-be assassin was seized by
the police, who 1k?1 the greatest diffi?
culty in saving him from the fury of
the crowd. The Archduke, after ascer?
taining the extent of the injuries to
his aide-de-camp and seeing that he
was being medically attended to, gave
the order to proceed, and the royal car
soon afterward arrived at the Town
Hall.
With his wife he spent half an hour
inspecting the Town Hall. The Arch?
duke then stated he was going to the
garrison hospital to see how Colonel
von Merizzi was progressing. Escorted
by the town councillors he descended
the step? leading to the entrance of
the buile g, re-entered the automo?
bile with his wife and drove off. The
car reached the corner of Franzjosef
and Rudolph sts. when two shots in
close succession rang out.
The first struck the Archduke in the
right cheek, inflicting a fhortal wound,!
while the second penetrated the body j
of the Duchess, severing a main artery.
She sank unconscious into the arms of
her husband, who a few seconds after?
ward also fainted. With all speed the
car was driven by the chauffeur to the
Town Hall, but almost before the doc?
tor could reach their side both had ex
pired.
The ar-sassin, who was a Servian stu&lt;*
dent named Gavro Prinzip, was seize?'!
and disarmed. The crowd made I
fierate attempt it? drug him from th?-!
protecting police, but the latter sue-,
ceeded in conveying him unharmed t&lt;*
the police station.
n.
Francis Ferdinand, Nephew of Emperor
Francis Joseph, Killed in Bosnian Capital
an Hour After Warding Off
Bomb Which Injures Score.
..LAYER A SERVIAN SOCIALIST
Volley from Revolver Hits Archduke and Ducheas of
Hohenburg as They Are Driving Together in .Automobile
in Town of Sarajevo?New Heir, Charles
Joseph, 27 Years Old.
i u i-?;.:. T?-* Tri'
Sarajevo, Bosnia, June 28.?The Archduke Francis Ferdinand.
h&lt; tir to the dual monarchy of Austria-Hungary, and his mor
g; natic wife, the Duchess of Hohenberg, were shot to death to-day
in the main street of this, the Bosnian capital. Bullets from a
m agazine revolver in the hands of an eighteen-year-old youth rid
dl id the heir apparent and his wife, and thus completed the grim
ta jk a madman had unsuccessfully attempted only a few hours
be fore by hurling a bomb at the royal automobile.
Another terrible chapter has thus been written into the tragic
ar id romantic history of the House of Hapsburg. and to-night the
ag td Emperor lies prostrated by the news in his summer place at
Is?:hl.
The flying bullets struck Francis Ferdinand full in the face.
O? le tore its way into the Duchess's body. Another pierced the
great artery in her throat. As the blood gushed from her neck she
fel I senseless across her husband's knees.
An instant later he. too, sank to the floor of the car i~. a heap.
Be rth were rushed with all speed to the palace. But no help was
of Bvail. They died a few moments after they arrived.
ASSASSINATION CAREFULLY PLANNED.
The assassination had been carefully planned. It was while
the? heir t? the Austrian throne and the woman he had loved so
well were on their way to the town hall that Nedeljo Gabrinovics,
a j ourneyman printer, slung a smoking bomb at the royal automo?
bil e. It was while they were returning from the hall, perhaps an
hour later, that Gavrio Prinzip, a high school student, stood at the
co rner of the Rudolfstrasse and poured his fusillade into the help
lesis couple. Again, an unexp.odcd bomb was found a few yards
aw fay from the scene of death. It had been flung in a corner by
an Dthsr madman after he had learned of the success of Prinzip's
attack.
ARCHDUKE WAS INDIGNANT.
After the bomb exploded the Archduke and the Duchess
pr oceeded to the City Hall. The automobiles were fleet and the
refws had not yet filtered through the crowd in waiting. Indeed,
th ere had hardly been time to telephone. So the burgomaster was
astonished when he met his royal guests at the door to have his
cu stomary address of greeting interrupted by the snapping words
of Francis Ferdinand:
"Herr burgomaster, we come to pay you a visit and bombs are
th rown at us. It is an insult!"
Then his princely dignity overcame his indignation, and he
pa used and said
"Now you may speak."
After the ceremonies the Archduke and his wife announced
th**at they would visit the wounded members of their suite in the
hcepitals on their way to the palace. They set out in their ?car,
th fcs time protected by a cordon of police. They drove rapidly
do wn the Franz Josefstrasse and were nearing the Rudolfstrasse
wl len Prinzip, a pale faced boy?indeed, a mere stripling, but with
all the zeal of a fanatic shining in his countenance?popped out, ?af
the front rank of the crowd like a seed from an orange. No one
seemed exactly to realize what he meant to do. It was as real and
ar.| unreal as a moving picture.
MAGAZINE REVOLVER USED.
Just as the automobile slowed up on the turn into the Fran*.
Ji .sefstrasse the boy raised his arm from his side. The sunlight
si ruck on the dull steel of the magazine revolver and soldiers
1? aped to grab, the youth, but before they reached him he had ac
c*omplished his deed. It was with extreme difficulty that he was
ni ?scued from the infuriated crowd.
The first attack was filled with all the dramatic intensity and
suddenness with which the successful and unsuccessful attempts
an the lives of European monarchs have been attended. Sarajevo
V 'as en fete to welcome Francis Ferdinand and his wife. It was
a triumphal procession. Flags fluttered in the soft wind and gar?
lands hung from the windows. A great throng of picturesquely
??lothed peasants pushed and shoved against the detachment of
[(soldiers that held them good naturedly in check at the railway sta
l-tion where the couple were expected.
HEIR APPARENT UNGUARDED.
?There was no especial military preparation, however, as the
heir to the throne had always been regarded as so popular that no
particular precautions were necessary. In -fact, the general feeling
that he would without doubt in the near future succeed to the
throne through the death of his uncle had clothed him with a sort
of affection that seemed to protect him.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045474/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=carriage+electrical+franz+ferdinand</id>
				<rel>0</rel>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Bosnia+EMPEROR+Emperor+Ferdinand+Franz+Josef+Sarajevo</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>AUSTRIAN HEIR AND HIS
WIFE SHOT TO DEATH
AETER ESCAPING BOMB
Archduke Franz Ferdinand and Morganatic Spouse Assas
sinated by Youth in Streets of Sarajevo After
Infernal Machine Hurled by Anarchistic
Compositor Fails to Explode
Until After They Pass.
COURTS OF EUROPE PLUNGED INTO MOURNING j
AGED EMPEROR MAY NOT SURVIVE THE SHOCK
Ej-t Cable to The Ws -r Bcnld
Sarajevo, Bosnia, June 28. The Archduke Franz Ferdinand, heir
to the throne of Austro-Hungary, and his morganatic Avife, the Duchess
of Hohenberg, were assassinated while driving through the streets of
this city this morning. They were shot to death after escaping a bomb
that was thrown at their motorcar and warded off by the archduke's
own arm.
They were on their way to a reception at the town hall when
the bomb was thrown. It did not explode until after the archduke's
car Tiad passed and the occupants of the next car, Count Boos Waldeck
and Col. Morizzi, the archduke's aid de camp were injured slightly.
Among the spectators six persons were more or less seriously hurt.

Trie perpetrator was a news
paper compositor named Cabrino-
vitch from Trevinje.
Angered by Attack.
The archduke ordered his car halted,
but after he had found out what had
happened he continued on his way to the
town hall, where the councillors with the
mayor at their head awaited them. The
mayor was about to begin bis address of
welcome when the archduke Interrupted
him angrily saying:
"Herr Buergermelster. It Is perfectly
scandalous. We have come to Sarajevo
on a visit and a bomb has been thrown
at us."
The archduke paused for a moment and
then said:
"Now you can go on."
Thereupon the mayor delivered his ad
dress to the archduke who made a suit
able reply. The public which by this
time had heard of the bomb attempt,
burst into loud cries of "hurrah."
Miots Rlns list
After going around the town hall for
half an hour the archduke started for the
Garrison Hospital to visit Col. Mori-xl.
who had been taken there after the out
rage. As the archduke reached the cor
ner of Rudolf street two pistol shots were
fired in rapid succession by a young man
named Gavro Prlnxlp. The first shot
struck the Duchess low down on the right
side, while the second hit the archduke
in the neck near the throat and pierced
the Jugular vein.
The duchess became unconscious imaii
diately and fell across the knee of ner
husband. The archduke also lost coi.
sciousness in a few seconds. The motor
car In which they were seated drove
straight to the palace, where army sur
geons rendered first aid. but in vain.
Neither the archduke nor the duchess
gave any sign of life, and, the head of
the hospital could only cerUfy that both
were dead.
Frared Second Attack.
The authors of both attacks, who wera
arrested promptly, are born Austrian-.
Cabrinovltch worked for a few weeks In
the government printing works at BU
grave. He returned to Sarajevo as a
Servian Chauvinist and made no conceal
ment of his sympathy with the king uf
Servla. Both he and the actual murdeicr
expressed themselves to the police in
most cynical terms about their crimes.
It appears that after the first attempt
on their lives the duchess did not want
the archduke to enter the motercar
again, but the governor of Bosnia. M.
Potlorek. said: "It's all over now. We
haven't got more than one murderer In
Sarajevo."
At this the archduke decided to enter
the car again.
Before their departure from Vienna on
the Journey to Sarajevo the archduke
and duchess went to the chapel In the
palace and spent a long time In prayer.
Recently the archduke has declared
more than once his conviction that he
would not die a natural death.
The mayor of Sarajevo Issued a procla
mation to Inhabitants denouncing the
crime and declaring that the confession
of the murderers proves beyond all
doubt that the bomb came from Bel
grave f.
Darta from Behind House.
The youth Prlnxlp, who fired the fatal
shots. Is only nineteen. He fired at the
archduke's head and must have been well
Instructed, for he apparenUy was aware
of the well-guarred secret that the arch
duke always wore a coat of silk woven
obliquely, which no weapon or bullet
could pierce. This fabric Is used for au
tomobile tires and Is puncture proof.
Later, details show that the assassin
darted from his hiding place behind a
house and actually got on the motorcar
In which the archduke and his wife were
sitting and took close aim. first at tne
archduke and then at the duchess.
The fact that no one stopped the as
sassin and that be was allowed to per
petrate the dastardly act Indicate that
that the conspiracy had been carefully
CONTINUED OX PAGE XHBJ,
LINER CALIFORNIA ON
ROCKS OFF IRISH COAST
Ship with Over 400 Aboard Reported
in Dangerous Position on
Toy Island.
WARSHIPS ARE STAND.NG BY
S-dI Citle u Tho Wuhi-fton Hftrnld.
Londonderry. Ireland. June It The
Anchor Line steamer California bound
from New Tork to Glasgow wa- ground
ed tonight on the rocks of Toy Island,
off the coast of Donegal In a dense fog
which rendered the Island Invisible.
"S O. S- calls from the steamship
brought speedy assistance from several
gunboats and torpedo boats, whlrh -r
ratrolllng the cusat for Ulster gun-runners.
According to the latest adices reached
here, the California is hard aground, but
In no immediate danger, although her
bows are badly stove In and she Is tak
ing water through two breaks in the fore
and second holds.
The California lies In five fathoms of
water forward and seven fathoms astern.
The passengers and crew have decided
to remain aboard over night.
Meanwhile several vessels which re
sponded to the wireless calls, are stand
in by ready to transship the passengers
If necessary.
COURTS OF EUROPE SHOCKED.
Aua-slamtlbn of Austrian Heir and
Wife Shock. Ilulrra.
j-ne s. ine terriDie news
from Vienna has thrown all courts of
Europe into mourning. King George.
who only last November entertained the
unfortunate Austrian heir and his wife
at "Windsor, was distressed greatly, and
sent a private message of sympathy to
Emperor Franx Josef. He then Issued
a command that the court shall wear
mourning for one week for his imperial
and royal highness the late Archduke
Franx Ferdinand of Austria.
The lord chamberlain has been com
manded by the King to- announce that
the state ball arranged to take place
Monday evening Is postponed "on ac
count of the lamentable death of Arch
duke Franx Ferdinand of Austria and
the Duchess of Hohenberg."
Berlin, June SI Kaiser Wllhelm re
ceived the news of the tragedy by a
fast destroyer while on board his yacht
racing through the Baltic Sea, In con
nection with the Kiel regretta. His
majesty ordered the race stopped, and
Immediately returned to the steam yacht
Hohenzollern. where he announced:
"The regatta will continue. As for
myself I will return to Berlin."
The Kaiser was deeply affected as he
had been the guest of the murdered
prince early In the present month at
Konopslcht, Bohemia,
Rome, June 28. When the news of the
-Maes! nation of Archduke Francis Fer
dinand and his wife was received here
this afternoon. Pope Plus was In his pri
vate library conversing with his sisters
and niece. Cardinal Merry Del Val gen
tly broke the news.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn92053934/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+archduke+Austro+Austro-Hungarian+Bosnia+emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungarian+principal+Sarajevo</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Vienna. Jur. 23. From all parts of
the dual monarchy most of the foreign
countries' message poured in today,
testifying to the painful impression
nroduced on the world by the as assln-
atloa nf Archd'ike Ferdinand and the
PucheM of Hohenberg. When the em
peror arrived at the suburban t-tation
from IschI this morning he was greet
ed with cheers from larg crowds. He
drove in an open carrlaee to the cas
tle. He appeared in the bet of
health an1 was received by the royal
palace by .Archduke Charles Francis
Joseph, new heir apparent to the
throne. Although today Is a holiday,
the newspapers appeared to devote
J V their columns exclusively to jester
f j clay's traeic event and paid warmest
tributes to the late archduke and his I
wife. The general impret-Mon is given
by the press to the conviction that the
people's dual monarchy would rally
round the venerable emperor.
Martial Law Proclaimed.
Sarajevo, Bosnia. June 20. Marital
law has been proclaimed both in the
city and in the district of Sarajevo in
consequence of the assassination yes
terday of Archduke Ferdinand and the
Duchess of Hohenberg.
Death masks of the archduke; and
duchess uere taken today and their
bodies placed in the catafalque of the
chapel of the palace, surrounded by a
terrod the Austrian authorities are
contemplating severe measures
against the Serbs among the inhabi
tants of Austria and Bosnia. These
measures are likely to further embit-
I ter the relations between the two
countries, as well as those between
Austria and Russia, protector of all
the Serbs.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand. It was
asserted today, was well aware of the
danger he was running during his tour
cf Bosnia, which he undertook as in
spector-general of the force's of the
empire. This title was conferred up
on him last year by the emperor. His
chief task was to inspect the Austrian
army wbi-h guarded the Servian fron
tier in the recent Balkan wars and
prevent encroachments by Servian
troops. The Servian minister of Vien
na told Ferdinand of the peril of his
visit to Sarajevo at the present time.
When the archduke and duches3 ar
rived in Sarajevo Saturday some signs
of hostilities were shown by the Serb
portion of the population.
Fly Servian Flags.
Just before the couplo passed
through the city the authorities got
rid of a great display of Servian flags
which people had hoisted Instead of fly.
ing the Austrian colors. Bitterness of
feeling, however, was carried to the
extreme when In the Bosnian diet. I
called to express sorrow over the
death of the archduke, four Servian
deputies appeared in light suits, in
contrast to the sombre black of their
fellow deputies.
Plans of the assassins contemplated,
it Is said. Mowing up of the royal
train when the archduke and his wife
were leaving Sarajevo in case the at
tempt by Gavrico Prlnzip failed. It Is
WATER IN THREE HOLDS
Help Reaches Ship Quickly and
Passengers Transferred
to Another Boat.
floral emblems from all parts of the t learned several bombs were found
country. According to a semi-official
report when Prlnzip f red the fatal
shots Field Marshal Potiorek. gov
ernor of Bosnia, was seated in the
archduke's motor car. Count von
Harrach was standing on th foot
board of the car acting as a shield to
the occupants, of a horn he constituted
Llmself special body guard, after a
bomb hid been thrown a short time
be!ore by Nedeljo Gabrinovich. The
archduke was Joking with the count
about his precautions hen several
shots rang out.
Mortal Wound by Each Bullet. j
The aim of the a-sasin was so true
that each of the bullets inflicted mor
tal wounds. Lieutenant Colonel Mer-
along the Sarajevo railway over which
the arcbdu.and hia wifewpuld have
traveled. Prinzlp's own plans were
carefully laid. He secreted himse'.
behind a building at a spot where It
was necessary for the archduke's car
to slacken speed. Some accounts sar
Prlnzip actually stood on the steps of
the ducal car as he fired the shots.
In Prinzlp's rooms the police today
found a large sum of money which
they say is further proof that he was
the paid assassin of some Servian or
ganization.
Live Only Few Minutes.
Sarajevo, Bosnia. June 29. Arch
duke Francis Ferdinand, heir to the
Austro-Hungarian throne, and the
izzl. wounded by a bomb in the f.rst t Duchess of Hohenberg, his morganatic
attack, was today prrmoiinced out of were shot dead yesterday by a
danger. The LHurv suffered l,v fnum Mudent in the main street of the
Von P-oos Waldeck is insignificant. "osnian capital a short time after they
Croatian students here lodav made i 11 escaped death from a bomb hurled
several attempts to
troops were called
pun:.-h Serbs, but
and maintained
at the royal automobile.
They were slain while
passing
order. Gabricovich was expelled from through the city on their annual visit
to the combined annexed provinces or
Bosnia and Herzegovina.
The archduke was struck full in the
face and the duchess was shot through
the abdomen and throat.
They died a few minutes after reach
ing the palace, to which they were
hurried with all speed.
Bomb and Pistol Used.
Those responsible for the assassina
tion took care that it should prove ef
fective, as there were two assaults, the
Sarajevo two years azo. but recently
was permitted to return throueh the
Intervention of a socialist member of
the Bosnian diet.
Some Servian students here, when
they heard the news of the assassina
tion, shouted: "Thank God, we need
not do it ourselves." They were ar
rested as accomplices of the assassins.
Bomb Thrown.
A bomb thrown by a youth stand
ing on the corner of the main fctreet
f't the Bosnian capital was the signal
th; morning for a serious anti-Servian
cuthreak, wihch troors found consider.!
b!e difficulty in quelling.
The only damage- was slight injury
to a parsing milkman. Th rougher
element siez-d the incident as an ex
cuse for a demonstration. They were
Joined by a n'imbr of Crotiari stud'-nts
cd
ton
clubs, schools and houses and looting
with a
iae head and attacked every thing
Jaa un'il overwhelmed by the police.
London. Eng. June IS. Every dis
patch today from Sarajevo and Vienna
brought add.tlonai evldeice that the
Mass-nation of Archduke Francis
Prd:nejid and the duches of Hohen-
Contlnued on Page Two.)</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Austro+Austro-Hungarian+Bosnia+BOSNIA+emperor+Emperor+Ferdinand+Hungarian+Hungary+PRINCIPAL+principal</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>CONDOLENCES FROM ALL POINTS
POUR INTO AUSTRIAN CAPITAL
A.M..intion of Archduke Franci. Ferdinand and Comort,
Duche of Hohenburg Produce. Profound Impression
Throughout World-Newspaper, Pay Warmest Tri
butes to Heir to Throne and Wife Venerable
ft tmperor Arrives and Is Warmly Greeted.
MARTIAL LAW PROCLAIMED IN BOSNIA
Servian Students Thank God That Assassin's Bullets Rang
t True and Are Arrested as Accomplices Blowing Up of
Royal Train Planned Bombs Placed Along Track
New Heir to Throne Popular Among People
'S Country Prays for Life of
Francis Joseph.
Vienna. June 29 From all parts of
the dual monarch), as well as from
moBt foreign countries, messages
poured in today testifying to the pro
foundly painful impression produced
throughout the world by the assassi
nation of Archduke Francis Ferdi
nand, heir to the. Austro-Hung jrian
throne, and his consort, the Duchess
of Hohenberg
The newspapers pay the warmest
tributes to the late archduke and his
wife, and reflect the sorrow and sym
pathy evoked among all classes by
their death.
Emperor Francis Joseph Arrives.
When the old emperor arrived at a
suburban station from Ischl at 11
o'clock this morning, he was greeted
with cheers by large crowds. His
majesty droe in an open carriage to
Schoenbrunn Castle accompanied by
a full staff of brilliantly uniformed
officers He appeared to be in the
best of health. He was received at
Ihe palace by Duke Charles Francis
Joseph, new heir apparent to the j
throne.
Although today was a holiday, the
newspapers appeared and deoted
their columns exclusively to yester
day's tragic event. AH of them dwelt
on the devotion to duty of the late
archduke and to the important sen
ices he rendered to the army and
navy, while touching reference was
made to the family relations of the
archduke and his consort, which had
been marked by undisturbed happi
ness. General expression was given by
the press to the conviction that the
peoples of Hie dual monarchy would
rally round the person of the vener
able emperor.
Future of Austria.
The opinion has gained ground in
1 authoriathe circles here that the fu
ture of Austria-Hungary now, more
than ever, depends on the health of
the venerable emperor, Francis Jo
seph. It was pointed out in high political
Circles that if the emperor is per
mitted to reign only a few e3rs
more everything may continue as
usual and Archduke Francis Ferdi
nands death will have little lasting
material effect on the foreign or do
mestic affairs of the dual monarchy
It was argued that should a youth
ful and Inexperienced ruler like the
I Archduke Charles Francis Joseph,
e son of the late rchduke Otto, sud
ig denlv be called on to take the reins
M of government, a period of anxiety
id might supervene
to Young Archduke Popular,
r- The young archduke and his wife.
ie who was Princess Zita of Parma, are,
)X both extremely popular among all
ie classes of society and everybody from
m the emperoi down is said to be pre
pared to do ins utmost to help them
ty In every way to rise to the responsible
I position so suddenly thrust on them
is The suggestion put forward in
or some quarters that Archduke Fran-
er cis Ferdinand s death is likely to
io cause a political upheaval is said not
to to have anv real foundation as the
iff old emperor has kept the reins of
ce government in his own hands. dele-
It gating as little power as possible to
his late nephew
er Much mystery always had existed
it in Austria-Hungary regarding the late
u hedr'g real and political claims. He
to Waa credited with being an ardent
e- Catholic and the chief supporter oi
ig the power of the Christian-Socialist
id or anti-semltlc party In Austria It
ts Wan known ho was not in sympathy
st with the Magyar regime in Hungary,
r- nor was he as pro-German in Austria
e- as some of the German nationalist
,vr A' faction, desired him to be.
of I Favored Three-fold System.
9n The late archduke. It is believed.
8t really favored some form of three
6t fold system for tho future govern
or merit of the Austro-Hungarian empire
jl. to take the place of the present dual
n- regime of Germans in Austria and
ed Magyars in Hungary It in sild he
o- deslied to see the great Slavic popu
ln latlon In the two halves of the em
irt hire and forming a very powerful pro
cr, Portion of the Inhabitants, giveu
nt sonic definite share In the goern
ment of the country Indeed, It Is de
i5 i
clared. he made clear promises in
that direction to certain leaders of
the Slav parties a few months ago
His death removed all these possi
bilities and will, it is understood,
prove a serious blow to the domi
nant power and to the anti-scmites.
As far as the new heir presumptie
is concerned, his political opinions
may almost be said to be non-extinct.
In foreign policy it is to be quite
certain that the Archduke Charles
Francis Joseph will have a strong
supporter in Germany and of the
Triple Alliance The influence of his
i uncles, the kings of Bavaria and Sax
ony and the future king of Wuerttem
herg, will, it is argued, certainly keep
him attached to the German empire
The bodies of the murdered couple
are expected to reach here tomorrow
and will be burled next week at An
stetten. upper Austria, in accordance
with the archduke's wishes. Already
the city is draped in mourning.
It has been decided the bodies are
not to lie in state in the court chape!
here as the duchea. was not regarded
as a member of the imperial family.
The lving-in-state therefore will take
I place either at St Stephens cathedral
or the Vavedier chapel
The bomb thrown by Nedeljo Gabri
OOVlci at Sarayvevo yesterday is re
ported to have been made at the Ser
vian gun factory at Kraguyevatz
Martial Law Proclaimed,
Sarayevo, Bosnia, June 29 Martial
law was proclaimed today, both in
the city and the District of Sarayevo
In consequence of the assassination
yesterday of Archduke Ferdinand and
the Duchess of Hohenberg.
Death masks of the Archduke and
the Duchess were taken today and
the bodies placed on a catafalque in
the chapel of the palace and sur
rounded by a magnificent display of
wreaths and other floral emblems
from all parts of the country.
According to the semi-official re
port of the tragedy, when Gavario
Prinzip, the young assassin, fired the
fatal shots, Field Marshal Oskar Po
tiorek, governor of Bosnia was seat
ed in the archduke's motor car Count
Francis Von Harrach was standing on
the footboard of the car acting as
a shield to the oocupant3 of whom he
constituted himself the special body
guard after ihe bomb had been
thrown a short time before by Nedcl
jo Gabrinovlcs
The archduke was joking with the
count about his precautions when the
reports of several shots rang out
Aim of Assassin True.
The aim of the assassins was so
true that each of the bullet? inflicted
a mortal wound.
For an instant arter the attack
Field Marshal Potiorek thought the
archduke and the duchess seated op
posite him had again escaped. Nei
ther the archduke nor the duchess ut
tered a sound, but a moment after
ward it was seen they had been hit
Lieut. Colonel Krik Mcrizzi, who
had been wounded by tbe bomb in
tho first attack, was today pronounc
ed out of danger, while the injury
sustained by Count Von Boos-Wa!
deck is said to be insignificant
Troop Suppress Students.
The Croatian students here today
mi.de several attempts to punish the
Serbs but the troops were called in
and maintained order
Gahrlnovlcs, it was learned today
had been expelled from Sarayovo two
vears ago, but hod been recently per
'mined to return through the Inter
ventlon of a Socialist member of the
Bosnian diet.
Some Servian students here, when
they heard the news of the assassina
tion shouted:
"Thank God we need not do it our-
They were arrested as accomplices
of the a-sasslns.
Servian Youth Throws Bomb.
Sarayevo, June 29 A bomb thrown
bv a youth standing on the corner
o the main street of the Bosnian
capital was the signal this morn.ns
for a serious anti-Servian outbreak.
I PENNANT WEEK
Loyal Fans, Turn Out in Force.
OGDEN vs. HELENA. Game called at
3 :30 daily
Thrilling field sports each day at three
"MY BARE FEET STAINED WITH HIS BLOOD I DRAGGED HIS BODY I
DOWN STAIRS AND THREW IT INTO STREET," HER EXPLANATION
3oroj 11 'SO-r c
Airs. Helen M. .ngle, wealth) Connecticut divorcee; Waldo P.allou, city -V-A JHjflBHHPk
councilman, who met a tragic fate at the door of hoi apartment; where m Bk
That the death of Waldo R. Ballou near the don-- of her apartment was H B
accidental, is the statement of Airs. Helen M. Angle, who is under arrest' tSnSgpL
on suspicion at Stamford, Conn. She says Ballou fell to his death from the V 'sJfiEjr
door of her apartment, and that she then, with her bare feet stained with sLjdrjr
his life blood, dragged his mangled body down a flight of stairs and threw lSj2Fr
it into the street before her home. Ballou was a city councilman and he
ardent admirer. Mrs. Angle is a divorcee, and wealthy.
which the troops found considerable
difficulty in quelling
l)U
ASSASSINATION
WELL PLANNED
Murder of Francis Ferdinand
Engineered by Persons of
Mature Organizing Ability.
PAPERS FOMENT HATRED
Young Student Was Paid
Large Sum to Commit
Awful Deed.
London Tuno 2'1 Every despatch.
today r.rju) Sarayevo and Vienna
brought additional evidence that the
assassination of Archduke Francis
j Ferdinand and the Duchess of Hohon
berg was one of the most carefully
planned crimes ever carried out
against toyaltj
Indications from the scene of the
tragedy show that It was engineered I
by persons possessing more mature
organizing ability than that of the
youthful assassins. P is generally
thoupht in Austria and Hungary that,
the plotters had their headquarters j
In Belgrade, the Servian capital.
Servian hatred of Austnans, which 1
always has been violent has been fo
mented by the newspapers In Belgrade
and by the agitators throughout Scr
la and Bosnia, who have helped to In-J
flame the minds of the students and Jo i
induce them to sacrifice their lives in
the belief that they will po down to
history as patriots.
Austrlans Plan Revenge.
YesterJa's crime seems likely lo'
have a contrary effect to that desired
Dj Its authors Even before the bodies
of the murdered couple have been in
tcrred, the Austrian authorities
are contemplating severe measures!
apalnet tho Serbs in Austria and Bos
nia These measures are lik-ly fur
ther to embitter the relations be
tween the countries as well as those
between Austria and Russia, the pro
tector of all the Serbs.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand, It Is
psnerted todav, was well aware of the
dancer he was running during his tour
of Bosnia which he undertook as
inspector-general of the fdrcoa of the
empire This title was conferred on
bin last ear by Emperor Francis
Joseph. IBs chief task was to inspeet
th- Austrian arm v. which guarded the
Servian frontier during the recent Bal
kan wars and prevented an. encroach
ments by Servian tioops.
Servian Minister Warns Archduke.
Th Servian minister at Vienna told
Archduke BVancis Ferdinand of the
peril of his visit to Sarayevo at the
present time, and implored him even
if he Insisted on golnp there tumsell
at least to leave the Duchess at home.
When tho Duchess of Hohenl erq
was Informed, however, of thy danger
ous nature of the journev, the arch
duke was about to take, she said ber
place was at ber husband's Bide
When the archduke and duchess ar
rived al Sarayevo on Saturday some
signs of hostility wore shown by th
Serb portion of the population Ju.-'.t
before the couple passed through the
citv the authorities succeeded in get
ting rid of a great display ol Servian
flaps which the people had hoisted
instead of Illng the Austrian colors
I
Feeling, howeer,'was enrriod o the
extreme when at a session ot the
liosniau diet, called to express sorrow
at the death of the archduke, four
Servian deputies appeared in Ilgbl
suits in contrast to the sombre black
of tli'-ir fellow deputies
Plan to Blow Up Train
The plang of the assassins contemp
lated, It is said, th-- blowing iti ot th
royal train when -brchduke and his
wife were leaytng Sarayevo, in ease
the attempt by davrio Prinzip fa.Hi d
li was teamed that several bonil.s
were found along the Sarayevo rail
wa over which the archduke criu
his wife would have traveled.
Prinzip'8 plans were carefullj laid.
He secreted himself behind a build
ing at a spot where it was necessary
for the archduke's car to pass Some
accounts ot the crime pay that Prinzip
actually stood on the step of the ear
as he fired the shots
Against all these carefully laid pi ins
of the criminals, the e.traordlnury
precautions taken by the authorities
proved unavailing, for the murderer a
guessed rightly that the archduke
would not bc frightened Into giving
uj) hi.- program after the first bomb I
had failed.
Prinzip a Paid Assassin.
In PfinzlpJs rooms the poliee found
a large sum of money, whiih they ?av
h further proof that he was a paid
assassin of some Servian organization
The s 'upathy of not quI. the rulers,
but of the people of Europe has been
expressed to the aged Emperor Fran
cis Joseph, whose much needed rest
at his summer residence at ischl has
been broken bj the crime. He left
Ischl where he was recuperating from
bis recent severe Illness, for Vienna
this morning. Thc Imperial train
stopped at Arstetten. where the Em
peror was joined by Archduke Francis
Salvator and bv his only daughter, the
Archduchess Maria Valeria.
i ondon, Iln? 39 The Duke of Teck
accompanied by a small military mis- i
slon. including a field marshal of the1
British army, will represent King
(leorge at the funeral of Archduke
Francis Ferdinand.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88086023/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Bosnia+emperor+Emperor+Ferdinand+Herzegovina+Hungary+SERVIA+Servia+Sophie</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>SERAJEVO, June 29 As a sequel to
Sunday's assassinations, pro-Austrian
mobs began rioting today. The peo
ple charged an extensive Servian con
spiracy existed against the archduke
and Auetrlans generally. Mobs sacK
ed scores of Servian shops and are
reported to have killed several Ser
vian residents. It Is feared there will
be a general slaughter when the mur
dered duke and his wife are removed
from the army hospital for shipment
to Vienna. The fury of the crowds
Is increasing.
In several encounters with troops
and police, the rioters had the better
of the fighting. The official account
was that the archduke's last words
were: "Sophie, you must live for
our children."
Dr. Dynes, commander of the ar
srmy hospital, embalmed the bodies.
Arrangements are being made to ship
the bodies to Vienna tonight
They will be taken by special train
to Metkovltch, where they will be put
on board an Austrian battleBhlp and
escorted by a squadron of warships to
Trlete. thence by rail to the capital,
where they will arrive Thursday.
It was announced the archduke will
not be burled In the Imperial crypt
at Capuchin church. Vienna, but be
side his wife In a private crypt In the
castle of Amstetten. overlooking the
Danube river.
LONDON. Jpne 29. An unexplod
ed bomb found by the- police at Sera
jovo. unquestionably Is one of those
Intended for Archduke Ferdinand, ac
cording to a Vienna dispatch. It was
made in a Servian gun factory at
Ktagujevac, said the message, which
added that a large sum of money was
found in the room of the assassin,
Prinslp.
LONDON. June 29 King George
designed Prince Arthur of Connauaht
to represent England at the arch
duke's funeral. A number of British
noblemen Is expected to accompany
him to Vienna.
CROW NOF SERVIA
A
Crown Prince) Alexander.
BELGXtADMjWune 9. King Peter
I. of Servla. has abdicated the throne
In favor of his second son, Prince
Alexander, because of ill health. The
king left Belgrade for Vranya baths
and a royal proclamation was Issued.
It said: "Owing to ill health I am
unable to perform my duties and
In accordance with paragraph 69 of
the Servian constitution I confide t
government of Servia to my heir, the
Crown Prince Alexander." Peter
Karageorgevltch, v.' "no is nearly 70
jeara of age, was proclaimed king In
1903. after King Alexander and Queen
Draga were murdered by a clique of
military assassins.
Portland millers are to be allowed
to bid for army supplies.
REBELS ABANOON CHASE
FOR LACK OF AMMUNITION
VILLA AND STAFF ARRIVE
TORREON NEW MOVE
SURPRISE TO ALL.
AT
TORREON, June 29. General Vil
la and his staff have arrived here from
the south. It Is stated his entire force
would dIso return here. This was a
surprise, since it was expected that
the federals having evacuated Aguas
Calientes and fallen back on Quere
turo. the rebels would push on In pur
suit at their best speed. The expla
nation given was they lacked ammu
nition. Hood River county will vote on a
1 75,000 bond issue for the Columbia
highway.
NEWS SUMMARY
General.
ArdMlnke Ferdinand and Ids Wire
of Austria are murdered by awasNin.
Riot break out against Servians.
Passengers on steamship Califor
nia are taken off vessel after It goes
alre.
Every precaution being taken in
European capitals to protect rulers
from assault by agitators.- Arrests be
ing made by wliolesaie.
Local.
Ijou Reed home near Gibbon burns;
suspicion points to Incendiarism.
Mcrcliaiits will dose stores on tho
Fourth.
Murum car goes Into ditch and is
wrecked.
Nebergall alleges his wife couldn't
treat him civilly for $500.
James Renner, thrown from wagon,
sustains broken bones.
Little boy burns foot badly by walk
ing on tin roof.
Religious Indians to hold big
canpnieetlng.
Panama canal may lie used for
hauling wheat this fall.
Pendleton takes complete series
from Yakima.Dispatches
from nearly every capital in Europe
told of extra precautions to protect
rulers and Important public men
against attempts like the one which
cost the lives of Archduke Francis
Ferdinand, and his consort of Aus
tria on Sunday. Guards have been
strengthened and arrests made of
known agitators and suspects. Police
and military authorities were alert In
every city. today started suit against his wife nand. his nephew next In line for the
for a divorce and the keynote to hi? j Austrian-Hungarian throne, had been
complete Is the allegation that at one slain with his wife In the streets of
time he offered his wife $500 not to'Serajevo, in Bosnia province. As th
mistreat him for a month but that she
broke her agreement in two days.
His complaint is a long tale of woe.
He charges that his wife is Insanely
jealous and has accused him, falsely
and slanderously, of undue Intimacy
with many girls and women ranging
in ages from nine to sixty.. Only 10
days ago, she accused him wrongly
of making love to her 14 -year old
grand daughter. I
As an evidence of the cruelty with
which she treated htm, he avers that
In 1912 while living In Pendleton, be
broke his leg so badly that he was
forced to use crutches for two years.
Thereafter, whenever hi wife grew
mad at him,- which was often he al
leges, she would kick him on his
broken leg. Other charges Include
tongue lashing him all night for an
act of neighborly kindness! threat
ening to poison, shoot and kill him.
abusing him before a crowd of 80
people, cursing him and driving away
his hired help. In fact, he alleges,
she" made life burdensome for every
one about the place Including the
hired help and the relatives.
The. couple were married In Baker
In September, 1S97. Plaintiff asks for
a divorce and for a restraining order
to keep her off the place during the
pendency of the suit, plaintiff being
fearful of his life. J. A. Fee Is his at
torney. Sought After 1,500,000 Years.
NEW YORK. June 29. The fossil
field at Agate, Neb., Is to be searched
for specimens of the ancient moro-
pus, a big clawed ungulate, said to
have existed 1.600.000 years ago. The
American Museum of Natural hlsUry
desires a specimen and Is to send a
party headed by Albert Thompson t J
l.ok for It.
DAILY EVENING E0ITI0.1
Forecast for Eastern Oregon. b
United States Weather Observe
at Portland,
Fair tonight and Tuesday!
CITY OFFICIAL PAPER
XO. S220
n
J
ASSASSINATION
Archduke Francis Ferdinand of
Austria-Hungary and Princess of
Hohenberg are Instantly Killed.
MANY ARRESTS ARE MADE
Widespread Servian Plot to Supcctl
by the Police l-Year-Okl Student
Fires Fatal Bullet After Royal Pair
Escape from Bomb Which Wast
Hurled at Their Auto.
ASSASSINATION WILL
PROMOTE PEACE. SAYS
ENGLISH STATESMAN
LONDON, June 2. "The
passing of Francis Ferdinand
has greatly bettered the pros
pect for continued peace in
Europe." was the statement of
Sir Thomas Barclay, England's
foremost international lawyer
and originator of the Anglo-
French "entente Cordiale."
"It seems a pitiless thing to
say," he continued, "but the
danger of war In central Eu
rope is greatly lessened by the
assassination. Francis Ferdi
nand was a bitter, bigoted man.
He leaned strongly toward mill-
tary measures to repress those
who opposed his policies which
always have aroused hatred.
Archduke Karl Is a young.
modest student of economics. He
is willing to take the advice of
his elders."
SERAJEVO. Bosnia. June 29.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand, heir to
the throne of Austria-Hungary, and
the Princess of Hohenberg. his mor
gantic wife, were shot dead yesterday
by a student in the main street of
the Bosnian capital a short tim aftr
thev ha(1 SCHwA dpat from hmh
hurled at the rovat auto
They vere knie, whlle passin3
through the city on their annual visit
th anpXfrd nPvInr.p nf Rnsml n.t
Herzegovina.
The archduke was struck full in the
face and the princess was shot through
the abdomen and throat. They died
a few minutes after reaching the pal-
T"" T
VIENNA. June 29. Emperor Fran
cis Joseph's death from the shock f
his heir's assassination Is feared. The
aged ruler seemed dazed Sunday when
told that Archduke Francis Ferdi-
weather is intensely hot. it is fearel
this will add to the collapse of the
emperor.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88078751/1914-06-30/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+Archduke+Bosnia+Emperor+Ferdinand+FERDINAND+Sarajevo+Servia</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>TRAGEDY IN BOSNIAN CAPITAL
Archduke Francis Ferdinand and Hi
Morganatic Wife Meet Death at
Sarajevo, Where a Reception Was
Jn Progress, n Their Honor Two
Attempts Made on Ferdinand's-Life)
the Duke In the First Instance
Warding Off a Bomb, Which Ex
ploded, Injuring Score of Persons.
Vienna, June 29. Archduke Francis
Ferdinand, nephew of Emperor Fran
cis Joseph and heir to the Austrian
throne, and the Duchess of Hohen
berg, his morganatic wife, were assas
sinated at Sarajevo, the capital of
Bosnia.
Two attempts were made on the
lives of the royal party. A bomb was
thrown aet thir car, which was warded
off by the archduke, and his car pass
ed before It exploded under the next
car, which contained two of his aides
who were slightly Injured.
Later on a man, said to be a young
Servian student, fired two shots from
a revolver at the royal car and the
archduke and tho duchess were killed.
This adds another sad chapter to the
lrfo of tho aged Emperor Francis Jo-
soph during whose reign many grim
tragedies have occurred.
The Archduke Francis Ferdinand
and the Duchess of Hohenberg start
ed out In their auto to attend a recep
tion in their honor at tho town hall.
Suddenly a man named Cabrlnovlcs,
from Trebinje, who was standing
among tho crowd on the sidewalk
throw a bomb at the royal car with
good aim. The archduke saw it com
ing and warded it off with his arm
and tho bomb fell to the street and
did not explode until after the arch
duke's car had passed. When the ex
plosion occurred it resulted in the
wounding of Colonel Morlzzo, aid de
camp to the archduke, and Count Bozz
Waldlok, who occupied tho car Imme
diately behind that of the archduke.
Twenty-six persons among tho specta
tors were more or less seriously In
jured. Archduke Speaks.
The archduke immediately ordered
his chauffeur to stop the car. Ho made
inquiries as to what had happened and
gave orders to have tho Injured at
tended to. After this the procession
to the town hall was continued. Here
tho town councilors with the mayor at
tholr head were awaiting the royal
party to bid them welcome. The
royal party 'entered the hall and the
mayor was about to begin his address
when Archduke Francis Ferdinand In
terrupted him and In an angry man
ner said:
"Horr Burgomaster, it is perfectly
scandalous. Wo have come to Sara
jevo on a visit and a bomb is thrown
nt us." Here ho paused a moment and
then said; "Now you canvgo on." Tho
mayor then delivered his address and
the archduke made a suitable reply.
Couple Killed.
After making the rounds of the
town hall, which occupied half an
hour, the archduke and tho duchess
startod for the garrison to visit Col
onel Morizzi. the archduke's aid, who
was injured by the bomb explosion
and who had been taUon to tho hospital
wm
Down In Street Of
erjevo
In a carrlape after the outrage. As
tif roynl car reached tho corner of
R-,uIolf strpet a man named Gavro
Pr.nzip, who was on the sidewalk,
fired two pistol shots In quick succes
sion at the archduke and the duchess
The man.Avhowas but a short distance
from the car, was a good marksman.
The first shot struck tho Duchess of
Hohenberg low down on the right
side, while the second bullet hit tho
archduke In the neck near the throat
and pierced the jugular vein.
The duchess became immediately
unconscious and fell across the knees
of her husband. The archduke lost
consciousness in a few seconds after
he. was hit. The chauffeur put on full
spce'd and rushed straight to the pal
ace, where an army of surgeons vain
ly tried first aid to the Injured.
Neither the archduke nor the duch
ess gave any sign of life and the only
tblug the head of the hospital could
do was to certify that both were dead.
Assassins In Jail.
Both assassins are In jail. Cabrln
ovlcs is a compositor who worked for
a few weeks at the government print
FRANCIS FERDINAND
Heir to Austrian Throne
the Victim of an Asssassin.
Ing works at Belgrade and returned
to Sarajevo a pronounced Servian
Chauvinist. He made no concealment
of his sympathies with the king of
Seryia. Both Cabrinovlcs and tho
actual assassin. Prlnzlp, expressed
themselves to he police in tho most
cynipal fashion about their crime,
Immediately after the assassination
the mayor of Sarajevo issued a procla
mation denouncing the crime and de
claring that by the confession of the
murderers It was beyond all doubt
that the bomb was brought from Bel
grade, Servia, to Sarajevo. Prinzlp
who fired the fatal shots, Is a student
and Is 19 years of age. He studied
for some time in Belgrado, When in
terrogated by the police he declared
that he had intended for a long time
to kill some eminent person from na
tionalist motives. He denied that he
had any accomplices.
Cabrinovlcs, who Is 21, declared
that he had received the bomb which
lie threw from an anarchist In Bel
grade, whose name he did not know.
He, too, denied that he had any ac
complices. Archduke Francis Ferdinand, who
was heir presumptive to the throne of
Austria, was born Dec. 18, 18G3. His
father, tho Archduke Carl Ludwlg,
was a brother of Emperor Francis Jo
soph, and his mother was Maria An
nunziatu, daughter of Ferdinand II.
of Naples. Francis Ferdinand was
still a hoy when his mothor died.
Francis Ferdinand became the hel:
presumptive When the Crown Prince
Rudolph, the only son of Emueror
my f f Sf -ylll
v fat 'f'MWm
SALEM, DEVASTATED BY FLAMES, BURIES
DEAD, CARES FOR HOMELESS, DIGS RUINS
i&amp;&amp;2r fitwyhi -Aft PSflfeisSBI
i ttms MffltfMW PfSSMBfBm
mi i I TV 1M'HL'J'A'i'lBTMl"'M'V't'M"' 'f "'"''"'"JLL-'J.f T. J mft WTW TP"1 P'ff."l''r'ltJ.T';'j lJ?.JJ-?T??rTWTTrT?TTTrrrH""rTM''''WI!' ''')1'''If',fMM'"w
pREFUeEES WATCHING THEiRHOMES. BURN IN SOUTH ALEH
PHOTO (s I9t 8V AMEWCftN PR833 .ASSQC1P.TIC3M
Salem, (Vlass., June 29 Thlsmlles of the city and caused a proper-various ways. Fortunately most of
famous old city of witches, one ofty loss of about $10,000,000. Relefthe old landmarks famous In New
America's oldest seaports, has startedcommlttees are at Vfork, anr" outsldeEngland history were spared. The ac
bravely to, dig away the ruins of itsaid la pouring; Iffto the city; Thecompanyihg Illustration shows some
fire horror, which claimed seyeral 10,000 persons left homeless by theof the homeless persons watching
lives, wiped out over three squareconflagratlon are being cared for inflames devouring their dwellings.
Francis Joseph of Austrla.met a tragic
death in what is known as the Jleyer
ling tragedy, the result of an uncoun
tenanced love for a young baroness.
Aged Emperor Informed.
Vienna, Juno 29. When the news
of the assassination of the Archduke
Francis Ferdinand and the Duchess of
Hohenberg was broken to Emperor
Francis Joseph, who has just recov
ered from a serious illness, ho ex
claimed: "Horrible! Horrible! I am
sorry they spared me,"</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99063957/1914-07-24/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Bosnia+demand+Demand+demanded+demanding+demands+DEMANDS+Ferdinand+Hungary+Servia+ultimatum</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Takes Advantage of Russia's
Labor Troubles to For
mulate Demand
ALL EUROPE MAY BE
DRAWN INTO WAR
Servia Given Until Saturday
Night to Answer and
Answer Right
Berlin, July 24. A "world war"
unless Servia complies with the de
mands Austria has mnde upon it, was.
boing predicted todny by diplomats and
military men here.
The Austrian ultimatum was a sequel
to the recent assassinntion of Archduke
Kraneis Ferdinand, Emperor Francis
Joseph's heir, by a Servian student at
Herajevo, Bosnia province.
It was freely asserted at the time
that the killing was the result of a
fot hntohed at Belgrade by a Pan
Hervian organization with extensive
ramifications in Austria, which has a
largo Servian population in its south
eastern provinces.
It was expected immediately after
the assassination that Austria would
demand an explanation from the Ser
vian government. It delayed so long,
however, that it began to be believed
the emperor was afraid he would preci
pitate a revolt of his own Servian sub
jects if he assumed a belligerent tone.
Late Thursday the Vienna foreign
office suddenly spoke. .Servia was
tilled on, not only to punish those con
concerned in the assassination plot
against Francis Ferdinand, but to sup
press at once the Pan-Servian move
ment. An answer was required by 6 p. m.
Saturday.
Assembles War Vessels.
The nature of the demands made and
the tone of the note caused amaze
ment in official Germany.
It was believed Servia would shape
its course in accordance with the ad
vice of its powerful friend, Russia,
(should the czar refuse to aid the
smaller country, it was agreed it would
have to yield. But it was deemed far
from certain that he would refuse.
In the event of Russian interference
between Austria and Servia it was con
ceded on all hands that Germany would
inevitably be drawn into the affair, as
Austria's ally. France and England
nre allied with Russia and might be
expected to be involved next. Italy,
os the ally of Germany and Austria,
presumably would follow.
Austrinn monitors were gathering on
the Danube today at Semlin, Hungary,
opposite Belgrade, the Servian capital.
It was reported that Baron Hoetzen
dorf, chief of the Austrian army gener
al staff, had ordered seven cjrps of
troops held in readiness to invade Ser
via at a moment s notice.
A partial censorship had been de
clared at Vienna.
It was stated here that the Austrian
government acted independently In
framing its note to Servia, Germany
not having been consulted. Though ta
ken by surprise, Germany, however, ap
proved Austria's action.
German officers absent from their
commands were ordered to prepare to
rejoin them immediately.
From the foreign office the follow
ing statement wa. issued:
"If war should be declared, Ger
many will do everything possible to
localize the conflict and confine it to
Austria and Servia, Germany keeping
its hands off, but should another pow
r seek to interfere, Germany will
promptly 'fulfill its duty as Austria's
ully."
"The Austrian note," said the Ber
liner Zeitung, "comes as a startling,
glaring lightning flash through a I
breathless, fearful cloud resting over
KiirniM. It dnzzlintf snark. imnrt from
Kurope. Its dazzling sparks spurt
every side.
"Our hearts are standing still and
a terrible crash which will shake the
world is awaited.
"It was not a diplomatic note that
Austria sent. It was almost a declara
tion of war. i
"Between the lines of the Austrian
demand spring forth in flaming red
letters mobilization orders.
"It was the general staff which
apnke.
The I.okal Anzeigrf warned Russia
not to interfere between Austria and
fervia. "The Austrian note," it said,
"was harsh but just. Servia must com
j.ry with the demands made or perish."
The market here broke from 2 to 3
joints as a result of the war scar?.
Russian petroleum fell 18 points. Quan-
t'ties of securities were unloaded.
Notifies the World.
Paris, July 24. Austria notified all
DEMANDS
THE PUNISHMENT 0
PICE'S B INS
HOT WAVE SWEEPS
THE MIDDLE STATES
Middle West Welters and Many Prostra
tions Are Reported Philadelphia
Breaks Its Record.
Chicago, July 24. A wave of in
tense heat that set new records for
the year in some places spread over
the United States yesterday.
In Chicago the mercury climbed to
100 and it was the hottest day of the
year here.
In St. Louis street kiosks registered
110 degrees and many prostrations
were reported there.
Oklahoma and Missouri also reported
many prostrations. Guthrie, Okla., for
the sixth consecutive day, showed the
mercury reaching 102 degrees.
Fort Scott and Great Bend, Kan., re
ported maximums of 103. Gritlloy, Kan.,
recorded 102, with four prostrations.
At Atchison, where the mercury reach
ed 100, several prostrations occurred.
Kansas City had the third hottest
day of the season, with a temperature
of 97.' Only one prostration was re
ported. Philadelphia, July 24. The warmest
July 23 in the history of the local
weather bureau was experienced here
today, when the thermometer registered
more than 9G degrees. It also was the
hottost day this year. Until today the
hottest July 23 was in 1883, when the
mercury registered 92.
Hot Spell Broken.
Chicago, July 24. The backbone of
the heat wave which has scorched the
middle west for. several days was bro
ken at noon today by a thunder storm.
The temporature here dropped ten de
grees within an hour. Heavy rains also
were reported from Iowa and Nebras
ka points.
the powers toilay of its demands on
Servia. With the notification it sent
a review of the circumstances attend
ing Archduke Francis Ferdinand's as
sassination, charging that Servian con
spiracies were responsible for his
death.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025121/1914-10-27/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=assassin+assassins+Ferdinand+principal+Prinzip+Serajevo</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text> In Serajevo
LONDON, October 27. (Associated Press by Federal Wireless)
Dispatches to the Daily Telegraph from Serajevo, by way
of Rome, say that Bavrio Prinzip, the assassin of Archduke
Francis Ferdinand of Austriai and his wife together with twenty
three accomplices, were found guilty of treason yesterday.
Sentence will be pronounced tomorrow. V
.CRIME PRECIPITATED AWFUL WAR
Prinzip, the principal actor In a tragedy which has thrown all
Europe into the most destructive and sanguinary war of all time,
is an eighteen-year-old Servian student.
On June 29, while the Austrian royal couple were at Serajevo,
Prinzip shot and killed the archduke and bis wife, after his accom-
Elice Gabrinovecs had wrecked their automobile by throwing a
omb, which wounded some of the archduke's aides.
V The assassins were captured and barely saved from the fury
of. the mob. ,t a i J vs'-y..,.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1914-07-28/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Archduke+Austria+Austria-Hungary+Austro+Austro-Hungarian+Bosnia+Ferdinand+Hungarian+Hungary+Serbia+Servia+SERVIA</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>FROM SERVIA
Belgrade. July 28. Many Servian
families have left the capital for the
country districts, in spite of the ad
vice of the authorities, while there
hns been a grent exodus of Austrlans
and Hungarians from Belgrade and
other parts of Servia.
Although perfect order prevails In
the capital, military preparations are
being carried out with feverish activ
Ity. The troops have been concen
trated in fortified points, the head
quarters of the army being establish
ed at Kraguyevotz, but in the event
of necessity they will be transferred
to Krusbcvatz 90 miles southeast cf
Belgrade.
TROOPS RUSH
T0JR0NT1ER
Unconfirmed Despatch Tells
of Prompt Mobilization of
Russian Forces at Border.
Berlin, July 28. An unconfirmed
dispatch from Gutnbingen, eastern
Prussia, to the Taegliche Rundschau,
today 82 ys Russia has occupied Wir
balleu, Russian Poland, with a force
of engineers, cavalry, artillery and
two regiments of Infantry, while Rus
sian guards have been placed along
all ioads on the frontier The dis
patch adds that a squadron of Ger
man Uhlans has advanced to Eydtkuh
nen, on the Russian, frontier.
AUSTRIAN COUNT
IS ORDERED HOME
New York, July 28. Count Otto
Salm Hoogstraston of Vienna, who
has been in this country several
months, today sailed on the Kron
prinsesriin Cecilie lu response to a
fable message from his father in
structing him at once to rejoin his
company of dragoons, of which he is
a captain.
The count and his brother Alexan
der were the tennis champions or
Austria Last February they played
in the indoor tournament In the Sev
enth Regiment armory here with suc
cess. The count is 32 years old and
adrpi at mo6t outdoor sports.
PEOPLE CLEARING
FLOOD WRECKAGE
Known Dead From Cloud
burst at Telluride Still
Stands at Two.
Telluride, Colo, July 28. Telluride
residents, assisted by volunteers from
other parts of the district, spent o
day in clearing, up the wreckage left
by yesterday's cloudburst and flood
and searching for bodies At noon
the number of known dead still stood
at two Mrs. E. E. Blakley, and Mrs.
John Johnson
The damage proved to be greater
than at first believed, and was esti
mated at $300,000.
Powerful hoisting machinery from
nearby mines was brought to the
town and used to raise the ruins of
demolished buildings.
ZAPATA FORCES
DRIVEN BACK
i Mexican Federals Take Action
Against Bandit Leader's
Armies Independent
Bands Active.
Washington. July 28. Brigadier
General Funston reported today that
the Mexican federal forces In Mex
ico Clt had taken the offensive
agamst the Zapatistas and driven
them from nearby towns He says
there are 30,000 federals in the Mex
ican capital
Constitutionalist troops have be
come very active along the railroad
between Soledad and Orizba. but are
acting in independent bands. Rlcardo
Lopez, at the head of a band of some
200 peons, Is said to be laying waste
to the section south of Vera Cruz,
towards the sea coast.
MRS. ANGLE IS
HELD FOR MURDER
Caused Death of Prominent
Connecticut Politician Is
Finding of Coroner's
Jury.
Stamford Conn.. July 28. Mrs. Hel
en M. Angle is held criminally respon
sible for the death of Waldo R. Bal
lou. a prominent politician here, on
the night of June 23. in a finding
made by Coroner John J Phelan to-
day.
At the coroners inquiry Mrs. An
gle refused to make a statement and
Coroner Pbelan announced that If, by
I Friday last, she failed to do so he
would hold her for trial He admit
ted Mrs Angle to bail, owing to her
nervous state, and she was taken by
her father Leonard Blondell. to
Southport Maine
Man Found Dying by Door.
Ballou was discovered in a dying
condition outside a downtown busi
ness building in which Mrs. Angle
had apartments. To the police that
night. Mrs. Angle said she found Bal
lou at the foot of a flight of stalr.i
in the building, after he had left her
and In the belief that he was dazed
from a fall or from liquor, she carried
him outside and left him on the door
I step of the entrance
Ballou died from a fractured skull
uu
SHAMROCK ARRIVES AT AZORES.
Horta Fabal, Azores. July 28
Shamrock IV., Sir Thomas Lipton 'a
new challenger for the America's cup.
arrived here today, having taken sev
en days and three hours for the voy
age from Falmouth, England.
4 P. M. CITY EDITION I H
TEN PAGES
WEATHER Generally fair tonight
and Wednesday. H
m 'H
Class Matter at the Poitoffice. Ogden. Utah. HH
Austro-Hungarian Government I
Has Declared War on Servia I
All Europe Prepares for War

American Wheal Takes Wild Jump
WAR DECLARATION CREATES
TUMULT THROUGHOUT WORLD
Germany and Austria-Hungary Refuse to Participate in Med
iation Conference Over Austro-Servian Trouble and
Battle Squadrons of All Countries on Continent Are
Being Mobilized in Readiness for General
War Eventualities.
j AUSTRIA TO HAVE FREE HAND IN CONFLICT
Imperial Foreign Office at Vienna Determined Declares
Servia's Compliance Would Have No Influence on
Empire's Course of Action Army Moving to
FrontierNo Traffic Except Troop Trains on
Bohemian Railroads Telegraphic
Service Demoralized.
Vienna. July 2S Official notiflca-1
tion of the declaration of war was
sent to Servia today by the Austria
Hungarian government.
The declaration of war was gazetted
here late this afternoon. The text Is
as follows
"The Royal government of Servia.
not having replied In a satisfactory
manner to the note remitted to It bv
tli Austro-Hungarian minister in Bel
grade on July 113, 1914. the imperial
nnd rcyal government finds itself
compelled to proceed to safe
puard its rights and interests and to
have recourse for this purpose to
k force of arms
"Austria Hungary considers itself
therefore from this moment in a slate
of war with Servia
ifS'gnea) r.uuis i rmiuL,u,
'Minister Foreign Affairs of Austria
Hungary." The Militaerischp Rundschau re
ports artne movements of both Serv
ian and Montenegrin troops, which
are in close touch at Prlboj, near the
frontier of Bosnia.
Nish. Servia, July 28. The Servian
p steamers Ueligr:l and Morava were
seized ioda at Orosava on the Dan
ube by Austrians. The Servian col
ors were hauled down and the Aus
trian flag hoisted. The passengers
were detained.
England Notified of War
London, July 2S. Announcement of
the declaration of war by Austria
Hungary on Servia came today al
most immediately after Germany and
Austria had notified Sir Edward Grey
the Brlti6h foreign minister, of their
refusal to join in a mediation con
ference. It is assumed here that the efforts
Ls of the European nations will now be
I i i i-li,(Tier (hp hostlll-
ties.
Cause of Hostilities.
The actual cause of Austria Hunga
ry's decision to enter into hostile con
flict with Servia was the reply sent
by the Balkan stale to the note from
Vienna demanding that Servia take
BtepB to put a stop to the pan-Servian
propaganda on Austrian territory
and also punish those Servians Indi
rectly concerned in the assassination
in Bobnia on June 22 of Archduke
Francis Ferdinand, heir to the Aus-
tro-Hungartan throne
The response of Servia was conslo
ered by the foreign office In Vienna
"unsatisfactory" and in a semi-official
communication made public yes
terday, the Austro-Hungarian govern
ment said that the reply was "filled
Germany Supports Ally
In the meantime Sir Edward Grey
took the initiative of requesting the
European powers to permit their am
bassadors in London to confer with a
vew to a peaceful solution of the
controversy. Italy and France at
once consented to Join thrir efforts
l those of Great Britain, but Germa
ny aud Austria icfused. Germany sup
porting her allv in the contention mat
It would be undignified for a great
Power like Austria to appear before a
y tribunal of European powers on the
jJY "ame status a? the little Balkan na
W,i4 lln
Austria-Hungary in the interval had
FEARLESS, INDEPENDENT! PROGRESSIVE NEWSPAPER
1 OGDEN CITY, UTAH, TUEAYEVENING, JULY 28, 1914. Entered a. second
proceeded rapidly with the mobiliza
tion of her great army The entire
railroad system was utilized for tha
movement of troop trains, the tele
graph system was virtually monopol
ized for government business and a
strict censorship was Imposed.
Servia also has mobilized her for
ces and had withdrawn the garrison
of Belgrade the capital to the interi
or, as the chief city of Servia occu
pied a position too vulnerable to be
held.
Every War Office Busy.
Every war office and admiralty in
Europe was occupied in preparations
for eventualities, even the Bmaller
countries such as Holland. Belgium
and Switzerland taking precautionary
m pa icii rrc
Then today came the formal decla
ration of war by Austria-Hungary',
one of the members of the Triple
Alliance, the other two countries In
which are Germany and Italy.
The notification of the fact was
sent to the Serian government,
which has its temporarv headquarters
at Kraguyevatz.
It was announced here that a dec
laration of the beginning of hostili
ties would follow quickly on Germa
ny's decision to hold aloof from any
scheme of mediation The German
foreign office had said that a confer
ence of ambassadors would in ita
opinion serve no useful purpose while
"conversations" between Vienna and
St. Petersburg were still in progress
Attitude of Russia Watched.
The attitude of Russia was watched
carefully today in official circles here
and the firm belief was expressed
thai Russia would enter the lists Ity I
support of the little Slavic kingdom
as soon as fighting started in earnest.
l.nndnn. Julv 28 The. refusal bv
Germany and Austria Hungary to par
ticipate in a mediation conference on
the Austro-Servian conflict, reports of
tho rapid movement of Austro-Hun-gar'an
troops and the persistent
downward trend of European stock
markets were the outstanding devel
opinents of the European situation to
day.
Preparations for war proceeded on
all sides. Even England s battle
squadrons have all been mobilized In
readiness for eventualities and the
publication of official news as to the
movements of British warships has
ceased. The first and second battle
squadrons have taken on their full
war stores and are ready to slip their
anchors at a moment's notice, the de
stroyer flotillas around the coast also
have been prepared and armed guards
were piacea tunny iirminu an iut
magazines and oil depots.
Gcrraan's definite decision against
participation in the ambassadorial
conference proposed bv Sir Edward
Grey, the British foreign secretary
in an effort to maintain peace, is re
garded here as tantamount to a dec
laration of Germany's determination
that Austria-Hungary shall have an
entirely free hand in chastising Servia
unless tne tsaiKan Kinguom accedes in
full to the demands of the dual mon
archy.
According to advices received here,
Germany' refusal was couched in
terms of sympathy with Sir Edward
Grey's object, but contended that the
suggested conference would place
Vustria-Hungary in the invidious posi
tion of appearing like the Balkan
states before a European tribunal to
explain her actions and therefore
likely to increase, rather than de
crease, the difficulties of the sltua
tion.
Apparently authentic reports cur
rent here assert that Russia has been
ghen positive assurances that Austria-Hungary
has no intention of an
nexing Servian territory. If true, this
might, it is thought, help the efforts
to localize the war should it break
out.
So far there has been no official
confirmation of the reports of hostili
ties between Austria and Ser'la, but
a number of rumors have been pub
libhed, including one of the seizure
of Servian ships carrying contraband
by an Austrian patrol on the Danube.
Austria-Hungary Determined.
Vienna, July 28 The imperial Austro-Hungarian
foreign office declared
today that, even should Servia now
comply with the demands contained
111 the Austrian note, the government
of the dual monarchy would not be I
satisfied Officials at the ministry
stated that Serbia's repl had made
It impossible for Austria Hungary to
adhere to her former stand point, and
compliance by Servia with the de
mands made on her could no longer
influence the course of action Of the
Austro-Hungarian empire.
Army Moving to FronVer.
Berlin. July 28. Reports from the
Austrian border today state that the
transport of the Eighth and Ninth
Austrian army corps from Bohemia to
ward the Servian frontier began yes
terday and that there was no other
tralfic on the Bohemian railroads ex
cept that of troop trains
The two corps consist of 32 batta
lions of infantry, with a large num
ber of quick-firing machine guns, six
regiments of cavalry, two regiments
of field artillery and two regiments
of the army service corps.
Telegraphic Service Demoralized.
Telegraphic communication with
Carlsbad and Marlenbad was still
open today but the telegraphic serv
ice between Berlin and Vienna was
demoralized and on some lines was
completed interrupted.
The Mllitaer Wochenblatt, the of
ficiai military weekly newspaper, to
day prints a noteworthy article com
paring the Austro-Hungarian and Rus
sian armies to the disadvantage of the
latter It says the fighting strength
of the Russian army is usually over
estimated and that numbers alone arc
not decisive</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84022396/1921-08-05/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=archduke+franz+ferdinand+dead&amp;st=image&amp;r=-1.011,0.232,3.022,1.16,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text> THE DEATH OF FRANZ FERDINAND
S»von Y*ari Siact iK* Austrian Arekduk# Wa# Killed Mr• X
and How tk# News Came to Bor* —A Story of tk# Boy nning of tkel
War,——How tlir Destruction of tk# ’’Firebrand of Lsroyr Was R#
coivod By His Own Subject*.
If hr should livr to be a hundred,
almost any man who had reached the
think age in 1914 will recall through
the remainder of his allotted life
some emotional reaction from those
days that intervened in that summer
between the murder of the Archduke
Ferdinand at Sarajevo and the actual
outbreak of the war on August 4th,
just seven years ago this week. If he
were in New York he will recall the
cloud and the tension that fell over
the business world, the extras of the
newspapers, the crowds about the
bulletin boards, the hush that fell over
restaurant and club as a great and
widespread war became more and
more of a certainty. If he were in the
country he will recall the eagerness
with which the daily papers were read
and conjecture upon conjecture was
built from the meagre facts that lay
beneath the innumerable rumors com
ing out of a world completely awry
To the man in Indianapolis or the
farmer in Windham county as they
look back over the seven years that
have passed it did not seem that the
murder of a single Hapsburg royalty
could have any effect upon the life
and being of an American, yet he, too,
lived to hear the echo of the shot that
truly did ring round the world
Sidelights on the war and its caus- 1
es, its personalities and it* conduct,
we shall have for many years. The
truth probably will come to our chil
dren or children's children, kor us.
who lived through the struggle, the
farts will always have a tinge of the
personal and we shall ever be incapa
ble of the calm judgment and analysis
of the contest which will come to lat
er generations. We must wait for me
moir and letter, for diplomatic docu
ment and a clear summary of actual
fact to be blended into a single whole
before the true estimate of the
world’s greatest war can be told or
understood.
Of Franz Ferdinand."the Firebrand
of Europe”—or of the world, if we
prefer,—we in America knew little
before his assassination There had
been newspaper yarns of his morgan
atic marriage, his scheming with the
Kaiser for the dominance of Europe,
his unpopularity in the Dual-Empire
But in the daily life of Indianapolis
or Windham Founty, we repeat, he
was a figure of little interest, merely
a marionette in the European puppet
ishow dangled before our eyes now and
then by the efforts of this or that col
orful newspaper correspondent.
In 1917, a few months after Ameri
ca hail entered the war, there came to
New York an American woman, whom
'we shall cell Mr*. X She had spent
most of her life in Europe and for
some fifteen years had been a promi
nent re-ident of Vienna Very rich,
beautiful and a distinguished linguist,
he had made for herself a definite and
unique place in Viennese society. She
entertained lavishly at her Hingstrasse
apartment and also at a romantic old
castle which she owned midway be
tween Vienna and Budapest From
her we heard much of Franz Ferdi
nand, his life and above all a fascin
ating story of his death.
Mr*. X., in the la*t week of July,
lit 14, wa* alone with her companion
at Bora, her old Magyar castle. Sht
awaited the arrival of Viennese
friend*, a certain Count and Countest
who were lord and lady in waiting
to the Archduke On Friday evening
there came a telephone message sav
ing that the guest* could not come a.«
they were commanded unexpectedly
to accompany Ferdinand and his wife
to Sarajevo Mr- gathered about
herself that fateful Sunday evening a
guy company of the Magyar nobility
from the -tit i hitu^iih: country They
were some twenty odd in number and
t he re was a brilliant oinner party as
sembled in the age-old banquet hall of
the castle
There was old t'ount l.etza, two
member* of the Cabinet, a number of
the younger nobility ef the country
side, a general, two diplomats and
their wive« The conversation wni*
i scintillating, the dinner perfect and
Mr*. wa* proving herself tl host
ess of her reputation
Shortly before the dinner etided and
the ladles were about to leave the
room a footman whispered t. Mrs
that she was wanted on the telephone
It wa* a long distance from Vienna
and most important Mr- V hurried
from her guests, grasped tin rereiver
and heard from a prominent friend at
court the new* that was calling all
Kurope to combat Franz Ferdinand
wa* dead I
In the moment that the telephone
clicked off something of the terror of
what was to come in the next few
year* swept over her She sat for a
moment petrified with horror The
heir to the throne had been killed’
Similar news hsd rocked the empire
years before when the Crown Pnnce
Rudolph wa* killed But this wa* an
other matter- Ferdinand wa* killed
and in Serbia. She thought of her
guest* many of them enemies of the
arrogant prince For a brief moment
there arose a menacing vision of the
iron hand of Germany Thu* she sat
meditating in silence Then Mr* X
returned to her guest*, and took her
place at the head of the table. She
was in an agony of fear and excite
ment The laughter and the gayety
were at its height Suddenly giving
way to a temptation for the dramatic,
Mr* X called out
'Attention, please, for I have ter
rible news."
Then in the silance that followed
I she xaid
"Franz Ferdinand is dead, killed at
Sarajevo."
For a moment her guests were like
graven images, but only a moment
and then with a quirk glance from one
to the other, every Hungarian at the
table «rr*ni? to his feet and raising
hi* ala** eried: "Thank God! Long;'
live Hungary”' There were excited;
question*, conjecture* the trayety of
ten minutes before had disappeared
forever. The world of each individu
al present had changed in a moment.
The talk took a more serious turn and j
finally it wai the old Count Letza.
veteran diplomat of them all, who
said the words which voiced the fear
in every heart. "ThU," he said,
“mean* war, illimitable war."
Four weeks later Mr*. X. was at
the front with the Auitnan troops.
She had already seen two battle*, she
had gone nights without sleep, she
had comforted the dying and ban
daged the wounds of those who had
a chance to live Tne prophecy of
that Sunday night at Bor* had been
fulfilled But meanwhile she had
lived through many things—the ‘‘sec
ond class” court funeral of the dead
archduke and hi* wife, the twin cof
fin* followed by the pathetic figures
of the two little neglected *on*. Then
a week had passed and the thousands
had stormed about the f’alace de
manding war and the old Emperor
had appeared and stirred them on to
further madness and finally the troops
had passed in a never ending line and i
the bloodshed had begun, and Mrs X
and her hospital followed on down the
road to the Silurian marshes.
Two years later or more and Mrs
X. was in America, a refugee from
her adopted home Of that gay July
dinner in If* 14 scarcely a happy
thought remained. Franz Ferdinand
was forgotten dust. Of the handsome
young officers who had sat about her
table, only two remained alive. Her
friends were scattered and lost and
Mrs. X herself, far removed from th«
old life of the gayest city in Europe,
found herself an enemy to those who
had been her friends. Back at home,
she worked without ceasing in
spreading the propaganda of true
Americanism among the non-English
speaking classes of Austrians and
Hunganans whose various dialects she
spoke so fluently.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045293/1914-07-03/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=archduke+franz+ferdinand+dead&amp;st=image&amp;r=-1.379,0.32,3.759,1.442,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>VIENNA, July 3. —Even death, the
leveller, today proved powerless to
Ureak the iron rank distinctions of
the Austrian court. The royal birth
of Archduke Franz Ferdinand was
emphasized over that of the Countess
Hohenberg, his morganatic wife, as
the bodies of the two victims of as
sassin’s bullets lay in state here in
the little chapel of the Royal Palace
of the Hofburg.
High on black catafalques, the cask
ets of the dead heir to the Haps
burg throne and his wife towered in
the little chapel. But the archduke’s
body lay in a golden coffin, while that
of his life’s partner was silver gray.
And the remains of royalty were
raised one step higher than those of
the woman who gave him her love
and life, who bore his children and
whose hands stanched the blood
which poured forth to the shot of the
assassin while hen own life ebbed
to another leaden call.
Wealth’s Glitter Reigns.
Guards stood beside the catafalques
■which were crowned by the richest of
fabrics. Glittering steel flashed in all
the courts of the ancient palace and
representatives of almost every noble
Austrian house which owed fealty to
The Milwaukee Leader
VOL. 3—NO. 177.
ENGLISH STATESMAN
WHO PASSED AWAY IN
HIS HOME IN LONDON
Ml: is
Mr J
H Jjyjß
Wm
f -rp. %mMW
JOSEPH CHAMBERLAIN.
LONDON, July 3.—The Right Hon.
orable Joseph Chamberlain, for many
years the most commanding figure in
British national and international
politics, died here at 10:16 p. m. yes
terday in his home in Prince’s Gar
dens, S. W.
For several years on account of his
age and feebleness, he seldom was
seen on the floor of the commons
where his tall form, and the ever
present monocle in his eye made him
a landmark.
Chamberlain was born in 1*836 in
the city of Birmingham which for
many years he held, politically, ill the
hollow of his hand. He was variously
known as “Brummagen Joe” and as
the “king of Birmingham.”
His power in the midland city was
almost absolute. All the seven parlia
mentary of the great manufacturing
city are held by Chamberlain nomi
nees and a politician he opposed was
simply wasting time when he trade
the race for parliament. Chamber
lain had huge commercial interests
throughout England and was enor
mously wealthy.
At one time Chamberlain was
looked upon as a Socialist of the Fa
bian type. When active in Birming
ham local politics he led the forces
that municipalized a large number of
industries. Later, when he became
prominent in imperial politics he lost
his radicalism.
The dead statesman started political
life as a radical but left Glandstone’s
party on the question of home rule for
Ireland, to which he was bitterly op
posed. He held the highest posts in
conservative administrations and was
secretary to the colonies from 1895 to
1903.
His imperialistic policy, which led
to the South African war, was bitterly
attacked and at times there were as
saults on his person, although none
of them ever were successful.
the line of Franz Ferdinand trooped
in and out of the little chapel.
In the whole district about the
palace, funeral bells tolled and great
throngs of the populace, held in check
by serried lines of halberdiers and
cuirassiers, watched the procession of
notables pass to view the remains of
the man who was to have worn the
double crown of Austro-Hungary.
In the chapel the sanctuary’s re
ligious gloom was barely lightened by
the flare of huge waxen candles which
burned on each side of the casket.
Beside them stood a guard of honor
of officers from the crack regiments
of the army.
All the stillness "within and from the
outside only the dull murmur of the
thousands penetrated faintly as they
shuffled on the pavements awaiting
their opportunity to look their last on
the mortal remains of the man who
was to have been their emperor.
Emperor Near Collapse.
While his dead heir lay’ still in the
Hofburg palace, Francis Joseph, the
aged emperor," was being attended by
physicians in his beautiful palace at
Schoenbrunn.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063952/1903-03-24/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=archduke&amp;r=0.073,0.251,1.501,0.576,0</id>
				<rel>0</rel>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038411/1914-06-29/ed-1/?sp=9&amp;q=archduke&amp;r=0.033,0.504,0.655,0.251,0</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>Archduke and Dutchess
Were Shot While on
an Errand of Mercy
By Associated Press
Sarajevo, Bosnia, June 29.—Arch
duke I 1 rancis Ferdinand, nephew of
i Emperor Francis Joseph I and heir
to the Autro-Hungarian throne, and
the Duchess of Hohenberg, his mor
gantic wife, were assassinated yester
day while driving In the main street
of the capital of Bosnia by a student.
A short time before they had es
caped death from a bomb hurled at
the royal automobile while passing
through the city on their annual visit
to the annexed province of Bosnia,
and Herzegovina.
The archduke was struck in the
face and the duchess was shot through
the abdomen and throat. They died
a few minutes after reaching the pal
ace to which they were hurried with
all speed.
Those responsible for the assassina
tion took care that it should prove ef
fective, as there were two assaults, the
first armed with a bomb and the second
with a revolver. The bomb was thrown
at the royal automobile as it was pro
ceeding to the Town Hall, where a
reception was to be held. The arch
duke saw the deadly missile hurling
through the air and warded it off with
his arm. It fell outside the car and
exploded, slightly wounding two aides-
Business Jjocals
TOO MUCH STARCH
If your negligee shirts have too
much starch In them they will be un
comfortable on hot summer days. This
is one of the things wo try to give
especial attention to; just enough
starch to give the shirt a proper ap
pearance consistent with cool and com
fortable wearing qualities. For good
laundry work try the Troy. Either
phone brings our wagon. Hoffman
Schooley.
SPOT-MAKING DAYS
Summer vacations and picnic parties
are days when clothing gets spotted
worse than any other time of year.
You have a Jolly good time and are
care free about everything but the
social feature of the occasion. When
you come home you find that, your suit
or dress has been receiving pretty
rough service. Phone for Flnkclstlne,
and It will soon be like new. i
s de-camp in a second car and a dozen
t spectators.
It was on the return of the proces-
I sion that the tragedy was added to the
long list of those that have darkened
i the pages of the recent history of t,he
Hapsburgs. As the royal automobile
reached a prominent point in the
route to the palace, an eighth grade
student, Gravlo Prlnzlp, sprang out
of the crowd and poured a deadly
fusillade of bullets from an automatic
I pistol at the archduke and the
duchess.
Prinzip and a fellow conspirator, a
compositor from Trebinje named
i Gabrinovics, barely escaped lynching
by the infuriated spectators. They
finally were seized by the police, who
afforded them protection. Both -are
natives of the annexed province of
Herzegovina.
On Errand of Mercy
On leaving the hall the archduke
and his wife announced their Intention
of visiting, the wounded members of
their suite at the hospital on their
way back to the palace. They were
actually bound on their mission of
mercy when, at f-.e corner of Rudolf
strasse and Franz Josel strasse, Prin
zip opened fire.
The archduke apparently saw the
glint of the heavy revolver'and faced
the youth, partly shlldlng the duchess.
Before he could do more the student
fired, the first bullet hitting the arch
duke in the face. Francis Ferdinand
managed to remain upright a moment
and then, as the second shot hit him,
he fell back against the cushions of
ti.e carriage. So close now that he
could almost touch the duchess, the
youth continued shooting, the bullets
taking effect in the abdomen. Each
bullet he flred had hit a vital spot.
Those nearest the assassin in the
throng who had started to flee stood
paralyzed for a moment, and then,
with shouts for vengeance and of exe
cration, flung themselves on the young
student, who was seeking to mingle
with the crowd and make good his es
cape. He was thrown down and men
and women were fighting to get at
him when the police and military
charged. His clothes were nearly
stripped off, and ue was bruised anil
cut by sturdy Bosnian peasant hands.
The assassins were interrogated by
the police and both seemed to glory
In their exploit.
Prinzip said he had studied for a
time at Belgrade. He declared he
had long intended to kill some emi
nent person from Nationalist motives.
When news of the assassination
reached the Emperor he exclaimed:
"Horrible! Horrible! I am sorry they
spared me!" There Is much concern
over the possible effect of the tragedy
on the health of the Emperor, who
has been 111 since early Spring.
The murders add another to the list
of tragedies which have marked the
life of Francis Joseph. The emperor's
own wife, Empress Elizabeth, was
killed by an assassin in 1898. His
brother Maximllien, for a short time
Emperor of Mexico, was executed in
that country. Ills only son died un
der mysterious and scandalous cir
cumstances at Meyerling in 1 889, and
is generally believed to have been
murdered.
The heir to the throne Is now Arch-
duke Charles Francis Joseph, eldest
son or Archduke Francis Ferdinand's j
younger brother, late Archduke Otto.
The heir is now in his twenty-seventh
year.
Empire Must Soon Be
Governed by Man Who
Has No Experience
Vienna, June 29-—The tragedy at
Sarajevo yesterday is bound to have a
momentous political effect on the dual
monarchy. The situation produced
by the equally tragic death of Arch
duke Rudolph repeats ItAelf to-day.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand, when
he became heir presumptive, was as
comparatively unknown as is Arch
duke Karl to-day, but with this im- 1
portanl difference that Emperor Fran-
cis Joseph then had prospects of many
years til reign. Now in the nature of
things, the empire must In a compara-
lively short lime be governed by an i
inexperienced prince instead of a ruler
wit. htwenty years' close acquaintance
with State affairs and second only in
influence to the emperor himself.
Archduke Francis Ferdinand on be
coming heir to the throne formally
renounced ail title to the throne on
behalf of his children. This was nec
essary because Austrian laws debar
the off-spring: of morganatic marriages
becoming rulers of the country. No
such disqualification exists under the
Hungarian laws and lit the event of a
division of the monarchy without such
voluntary renunciation of the son
Francis Joseph might succeed to the
Hungarian throne.
Burdens on Kmpei-nr
The death of Francis Joseph will
throw all burdens of government upon
the aged Emperor and at the moment
it is next to impossible to predict
what political results will follow yes
terday's tragic events. The late arch
duke had a tremendously strong per
sonality and wielded an enormous In
fluence in every department of politi
cal, military and naval affairs. He
possessed a temperament of fiery
energy and had strong clerical sym
pathies. He was bitterly opposed to
Hungary and all separatist move
ments. He was in favor of the restor
ation of temporal power of the Pope
which made him unpopular with
Italy endangered Italian alliance and
is believed to have looked to an alli
ance with southern Slav races to
wwh raC iv Hun sartan influence.
Whether this was true or not he cer
tainly was anxious to increase Aus
trian influence in the Balkans and
worked energetically with that aim in
view which is held as explaining Ser
vian antagonism toward him
Little is known of Archduke Karl
rands Joseph s political leanings,
but it is supposed that with the disap-
SUAustria maj soon enter upon a period
of greater quietude than she would
have experienced under Archduke
1> rancis Ferdinand.
Archduke Was Warned
of Feeling Against Him
by Minister in Vienna
By Associated Press
London, June 29.—Every dispatch
to-day from Sarajevo and Vienna
brought additional evidence that the
ass issination of Archduke Francis
Ferdinand and the Duchess of Hohen
berg yesterday was one of the most
carefully planned crimes ever carried
out against royal personages.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063952/1903-03-24/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=archduke&amp;r=-1.575,-0.087,4.15,1.592,0</id>
				<rel>0</rel>
			</result>
		</results>
	</topic>
	<topic>
		<id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-ping-pong-craze</id>
		<results>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1900-12-23/ed-1/?sp=29&amp;q=TABLE+TENNIS</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>TABLE TENNIS.
HI'LKS OF TLAY FOR THE NKW INIM>OR
GAME. AI^SO CALLED POMPOM."
Table tennis is the name of a new game which
was introduced in England a short time ago.
and has already become one of the most popu
lar of indoor amusements. It is the came
of lawn tennis in miniature, played on an or
dinary dining table. The net is a tiny one, made
of gauxe stretched between two uprights, which
rest on a bar laid across the table. The balls
are made of the thinnest kind of pyroxyline ma
terial, and are consequently very light. The
racquet has a slender handle and a blade with
a frame about one-half inch thick, which Is cov
ered on both sides with thin drumhead Material.
The play and counting are practically the satnas in lawn tennis, but, according to the rules,
'•the player serving must not put his racquet
over the table nor have it above his wrist." That
is, he must serve underhand and never over
hand, but after service he may hit the ball as he
likes, but he most not volley.
The contact of the light ball with the drum
head racquet produces a pleasant sound, and
because of this sound th(» game received the
name "pompom."
Among the rules for playing the game are the
following:
No faults are allowed: if a fault is served.
that is, the ball does not go over the net or goes
off the table without touching the opposite side
to the server, a |M>int is counted to the non
server.
If the net is touched by the l»all. and the ball
goes over, and otherwise the service is correct,
it is a let. and counU nothing to either side.</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1902-01-05/ed-1/?sp=26&amp;q=PING-PONG</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>AN ABSORBING HEW INDOOR GAITS
WHICH HAS ATTAINED GREAT
POPULARITY IN LONDON;
The three men who occupied the studio flat
were having their quiet end-afternoon srnoks
together. There was the artist, w hose hair haj
turned gray after long years of painting an*
black and white doings; the youth who, fcesi
from art school, was just making a start, and
the man of business, who was the saving clause
of the combination. He put up the money wh»3
black and whites would not sell and the youths
checks from home were delayed In the mails.
"I wish people would find something new wia
which to entertain us, said the man of buij.
ness, in a bored tone.
"New Year is coming," chirped the youth, aa
obvious statement, setir.g that Christmas «xj
just one day past. "Perhaps Santa Claus tLpgti
off' the dear girls to a new game."
There*! nothing new under the sun. Billy*
said the •Id artist. "If taert was I'd draw it jj
hurry."
Then there came a knock on the door, and a
messenger appeared with a dainty note. Billy
grasped it hastily. Billy was in love.
"It's addressed to all of us," he said, with di*.
appointment.
"All the more reason you should hurry up aaj
lead it,"' commanded the man of business.
"It's from Harriet," he murmured, as he read
it to himself.
"Head out loud, uli>.t"" commanded one of the
older men.
"Won't you ccme up to-morrow night and
play ping-pong." read Billy. "Now, what is
ping-pong?"
"Search me?" remarked the one who was nut
artistic, except when it came to making money.
"Sounds Chinese," said the artist.
"I've heard of 'pom-pom,' remarked BiUy.
"That's a sort of big gun which makes a funny
noise." Billy had ence had the idea of beeoininj
a military man. "But ping-pon^r— that's a new
one on me."
"Some new style of bridge. I suppose." mut
tered the artist. "It's not for me. I've sacri
ficed enough on that altar."
"Well. I'm going up to play ping-pong," an
nounced the youth. "I don't care what it is, tit
name's new. Better come along. Jack. You
were growling a minute ago about there being
nothing new, and here you are."
Dilly went to Harriet's and played ping-pong,
and when he had not retumeO by midnight th«
other fellows knew that he was enjoying it. H«
would not tell them what the new game was
when he finally put in an appearance, but ad
vised them to find out for themselves.
An indoor edition of tennis is ping-pong, til*
name coming from the curious sound which tie
parchment rackets give forth when they striis
the little balls. It is played on the dining room
taMe, across the centre of which a low net is
stretched. Th> rules are almost the same as
in tennis, and the points are counted tennis
fashion. There is even mure chance for skilful
handling of the ball than In outduor game*
and there are tricks innumerable which add
interest and variety. Skilful players can ii??
up the volleying process until interest reaches
fever pitch. It is almost as exciting for tie
spectators as for the players, which U core
than can be said of tennis.
It is an absorbing game, as the EngHsh S«l
tell you. It his been played i:i London ilisisj
romis for the last two or three years; but ha
never been strictly in vogue until this winter
The ollieers of the British army carried pir.g
peng sets to South Africa with t'.u-m. and have
set up their tab) on tho wldt when the Ecea
let them remain Ln camp long enough.
Why the game has not taken hold in tiia
country is something which Americans who live
In London cannot understand. They have writ
ten home about the beauties and delisht3 o! v
ping-pong. They laud it to the skies for tie
exercise it affords to busy c.tn who have o
work in offices all day. and to women who
occupied with a round of teas a^d recepucsi
PING-PONG.
Continued on Seventh I'agc*</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86071197/1902-03-02/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=fad+table+tennis</id>
				<rel>1</rel>
				<text>w
HE ALL ABSORBING FAD
fg very body as Is Anybody Plays Ping
Pong Directions for Playing
Jlf you would be the proper thing
With progress keep along
Do you ping pong
Shakespeare
4amtnai G4 S
b then I rede ye learn to pips
And also learn to poug
VVell well well go and pine pongl
Xhe only reason that ping pong Is not
ntentloned In Shakespeare Is probably
wjug to tho fact that the game was jot
Invented In Shakiispeares time Toor
lng pong li lawn tenuis little brother
f
Bi Is the latest little International baby
Sthjt has found Its way Into the lap of so
fclety If you belonged to the hoi pollol
faiijl wero quartered n Londons White
Sfchjpel or New Yorks tendetloln and
fnappeiicd to be a champon ping pouger
utho doors of tho most eNCluslve society of
Jboth cities would swing open to aduit yon
Fqr ping pong Is strictly the thing and
Jytha Hkllleil player U at present It
Being little It Is played Indoors and
ujbecausjc of the moving about which It
Permits It Is rapidly superseding euchro
hlgh Uvb and bridge whist as a means of
jrepreatlon and entcitalnmcnt In the games
rjut mentioned one must sit In one position
throughout the tedious cveuing llng pong
isKillfferent In ping pong one must t tlr
constantly
tiding pong Is usually played on a dining
jtable with a specially piepured celluloid
ball Instead of the India rubber one iw
Jnglawn teunls It requires some little
praetIco before the proper strength Is at
jitalped with which to strike tho ball but
tea minutes or so Is suflielont as a rule
rtoinabIc the plajcrs to keep the ball within
fch space of the table top The ping pong
foil does not fly easllv
mA dining tablo about seven feet to nine
feet long by half the width without a
idoth is thp best place to play the giie
toj and when the room Is lighted from
febtvo tho table by a chandelier tho tnbf
M uld be moved a little to the sldo of tha
lrm
PWThe height of the net can be varied from
Jcp inches to Ave Inches the lower It Is
stftpa more difficult the strokes can be made
ito return
iKThe racquets are Tellum covered bats of
I
Thc Home of the Patrician
Patrician
Shoes for Women
350
kn Eloquent Tribute
Is on the lips of every woman yho
has worn the Patrician They
are a 20thcentury product in every
particular of style workmanship
and service and their fitting quali
ties are little short of marvelous
atrician
SHOES
re made from the choicest and
nost fashionable Icatiers hey aie
modeled by artists and aie put to
feci her by expert craftsmen Ex
cept onal facilities and an imme se
Jotiput enable us to sell the
Patrician at
ISole Acency
the kind that used to be known as battle
dores
Warming tho battledores slightly before
tho tiro will lmptovo their elasticity but
caic must be taken not to overheat them
When wlogs are used wlb the net these
should bo died up on the posts so that
they project out beyond the edge Of the
table aaid thus prevent n ball being re
turned tound the sides of the posts Instead
of over the net
1 The game Is for two players They
shall stand one at each end of the tabic
The plajer who lirst delivers tho ball shal
i e called tho server and the other the
sttikorout
2 At the end of tie first game tho
strlkorout shall become tho server and the
sirvei shall become the strikerout una
so on alternately
a The service shall bo strictly under
hand und delivered from beyond tha end
of the table
4 The ball served must drop anywhere
ou the table top beyond the net and Is then
In play If It drops Into the net or off the
tabie It counts to the striker out There is
no second son lie as In lawn tennis
0 In fretting It Is a let If the ball touch
the net lu parsing over
0 If the ball in play htrllscg any obiect
above or around the table beloro it bounces
on tho table top Itself net or post except
ed It counts against the player
7 The berver wins a stioku If the strlker
out fulls to return the service or return
the service or ball In play off the table
b The strikerout wins n stroke If the
server bcrve a fault or falls to return the
ball In play or return the ball In play so
that It falls off the table
0 No volleyllng Is allowed hut as long
as the ball touches the table top It Is In
play aud can be taken at half volley
10 On either player winning his rtrst
stroke the score is called 15 for that
plajer on either player winning his sec
ond stroke the score Is called SO for that
player on either plajer winning his third
stroke the score is called 40 for that play
er and tha toiuth stroke won by either
player Is scoied game for that player ex
es pt as below
11 If both players have w n three
stiokes 40 all the score Is called deuce
snd the next stroke won by either player is
scored advantage to thit player If tho
same player wl the nest stroke he win
the game If hi loses the next stroke the
store is again called deuce and so on
until either player wins the two strokes lm
mediately following the score of deuce
when the game is scored for that player
12 The player who flist wins six games
wins a set
13 The game may nlso be scored by
points twentytwo up The players lu this
cn e change the service aucr every tive
points scoied like overs at cricket
The apparatus of the game costs about
260 i
A pingpong dance In which the women
wear pingpong patches and powdeted hair
Is the latest development of the present
mania Tho women carrying white balls
with a red number on each and each gen
tleman a scarlet ball with a corresponding
fluro in white walk down the ball room
and meet at a silken net Batting begins
Af soon as each dancer secures the ball the
numbers are called out pairing oft begins
and the couples glide down the room hand
in hand in minuet style The latest rival
of pingpong bv the wnv Is table bowls
which has Just been exhibited at the Alex
andra palace</text>
			</result>
			<result>
				<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059523/1902-04-06/ed-1/?sp=23&amp;q=ping-pong+table+tennis</id>
				<rel>1</rel><text>From present indications society will
no longer be divided upon the lines of
birth, l)i ceding or wealth, but the quail-
Jiciition for membership in the innermost
circle will )m- ability to play "ping pong,"
that fascinating parlor game that has
recently come over the seas to us from
aristocratic London.
Age. sex. color or previous condition
inaki no difference with the devotees of
the game and in England duchesses have
been known to struggle for the honor of
having a champion ping pong player from
some suburb at their receptions. Success
ful authors, artists and actors are no
longer being: lionized and made to roar
for the benefit of society. Their place ,s
but secondary now to the man who can
make the highest score with the bellum
covered racquet* and the celluloid balls.
The craze has but just struck the West,
although in New York, and. in fact, in
all of the Eastern cities, it is raging al
most as widely as it does in England.
The dealers say they are unable to keep
up with the demand for the game and
that thousands of sets have been sold,
v.ith the demand still increasing. "Pins
pong" parties are taking the place of
bridge whist and cinch contests and even
of bowline tournaments. No longer does
the Western swain sit contentedly in the
parlor with the girl of his heart, discuss
ing the weather undisturbed by the other
members of the family. Now the parlor
is in use. Father and mother and the
neighbors are "serving" and "returning"'
and calling love 15, love 30, deuce ad
vantage, etc.
i'iiiK pong is Bimply modified tennis
played upon a ta-ble in the houft« instead
of a court in the open air and is, in fact,
table tennis. Bui when the little celluloid
ball strikes the hard surface of a table
the contact prodapes a sound best
d&lt; scribed by the word "ping" and as it
bounds against the viium racquet the
Bound "pong," a full note lower, issues.
Some person with a quick ear and a
quicker imagination translated these
sounds and the gamfe was christened with
the catchy name "ping pong," a name
tnat has helped to call attention to it.
The balls are very light, much like blown
birds' iggs to the touch, and there is no
possibility of their breaking or of injur
ing anything they may strike except, of i
course, fragile bric-a-brac. The racquets
are light rattan affairs, covered with
vellum. In this respect they differ from j
those used in ordinary tennis, although
ih>- dealers are showing some specially
constructed ones strung with catgut, as j
are tennis racquets. They were ordered
by ]>ing pong players' who are also tenn:s
experts and who believe they can play
In tter with the strung racquets than with
the vellunf-covered ones. Any table
about the height of a billiard table and
jn the neighborhood o. nine feet long by
five feet wide will do for the game. Many
use dining tables. To be correct one
should have a table, the surface of which
has been painted dark green, or covered
With biliard cloth, it makes no difference
in the game whether it is played with or
Without a cloth upon the table. Without
a cloth the balls will, of course, bounce
higher. The game is played by two or
Jour persons, usually by two. For the
at in which thfe are two players,
and this is the game in high favor, each
player stands art one end of th&lt;- table.
The one first delivering the ball is called
the "serve;;" t):.- other person is th-e
".■strikeout." At the end of the iirst game
the "strikeout"-becomes the "server' and'
00 on alternately to the end of the sets.
As soon as theball is served and drops
nnywlK re on the table top beyond the t.et
it is 'play." if it drops Into the net-or
off the table it counts to the "strike out."
I i&lt; re is no second service as in lawn ten
jus. On either player winning the first
strike, the score is called fifteen for that
fourth stroke won by either player is sac
ond "game," unless both players have
yon three strikes, "forty all," whsn the
scon- is called deuce, and the next stroke
v.on by either player is scored "advan
tage" to that player.
[f the same player wins the next stroke
the game Is his: If he loses the next
eiroke the score is again deuce, and so i
on until either player wins the two
Strokes imediately following the score
player; on either player winning his or
her second stroke, the score for that play
er is thiity. On either player winning- the
third stroke, the score is forty, and the
of deuce, and the "game" is scored for
that player. The player who lirst wins
six games wins the set. In tourna
ments usually three sets are played by
each &lt;.im;)etitor against each other one.
The rules for playing are similar to
those in lawn teunis, except that no over
hnnd service is allowed. There are no
urts marked as in lawn tennis, the
~"\i of the table forming the court, so
that the ball striking any part of the ta
ble is in play. The strokes, apart from
the service, are divided into two main
lasses—the half volley and all other
Etrokee. The half volley is when the bull
,~i~.v.T.T.~.ViV.riT.*»i"iT.r.r. .-■"..-,—.:.v.~...
Rheumatic
1
Sciatic. Sharp and Shooting Pains. 3!
Strains, Weaknessand ail bodily aches it&gt;
and pains relieved almost instantly. Ql
Backache.- Headache. FaceaChe. 3&gt;
Chest Pains, and all Nervous Pains 91
and Muscular Weakness cured by
St Jacobs Oil f

After all other rerr.edics fail.
i -.-Acts like magic 1 .jjr
Conquers Pain I
I
Price, 25c and 50c.
?f
SOLD D-AALL DEALERS IS MEDICINE.
is taken' immediately after striking the
table. The player hits where he thinks
the ball will be, not at the ball itself,
and it is, therefore, almost impossible
to actually hit is half voiieyin^. Ji is the
ball which hits the racket, and not the
racket that hits the ball. This ia en
tirely defensive play. To attack, the
ball must be struck after it has reached
the top of the bound, or even later, for on
ly then has the player complete control of
the ball. When the ball bounds high it
may be smashed straight on the table,
but if your opponent gets back so as to
make the return, twist your wrist BO that
the ball is hit at right angles to the
flight or even somewhat underneath; it
will drop close to the net and come
straight up or even bounce back over the
net. An effective stroke in reply to a
hard (irive is that called the "crouch
smash." As the ball cornea toward you,
crouch down and hit It at the edge of the
table. This is a good return for a hard
service, but it is most difficult to ac
complish. All these strokes can be done
■backhanded— -in fact, some are such
easier, as, owing to the wrist having
more play in the proper direction, a (,-rtat
er twist can be imparted to the ball.
In addition a ball falling on the right
hand side»f the table can be driven with
the back of the hand in any d-esircu di
rection. This stroke should only Le used
when pressed by a hird ball.
It will be gathered from th&lt;^ strokes
described that play can be made both
back and forehand. This gives many
more opportunities for deceiving an op
ponent. Variety is the secret of success.
Nev&lt; r let your opponent anticipate your
intention. When driven to swing, after
hitting the ball, do not stop and turn
back, but continue the swing the same
way, bo as to make a complete circle.
The player i an get square with the table
much quicker by doing this. Ping pong
sets may be had to suit any fancy or any
THE HEAVENS
IN APRIL
April, the fourth month in the year.
presents many attractions for those who
follow with unwavering interest the ever
changing movements of the heavenly
bodies. The scene of beauty has, how
ever, shifted to the early morning hours,
if one would see the planets in their glory.
So that it takes an early riser to glean
from the heavens the really choice bits,
unless a telescope is at hand. The stars
are, however, always to be relied upon,
and just now in the northern section of
the heavens we see the Little Bear pass
ing above the horizontal position which he
had not quite reached last month, while
the Great Bear is overhead and inverted.
King Cepheus is now immediately below
the pole, and, like some earthly monarchs,
is standing on his head in a most un
kingly attitude. Cassiopeia is where it
always can be found, on the opposite side
of the pole from that occupied by the
Great Bear, so that the Lady in the
I'hair need never fear being hugge.i by
this fierce dcniz&lt; n of the Arctic regions.
In the southern sky the great sea serpent,
Hydra, occupies the leading position, ihis
is the longest and nearly the largest of
the constellations. The ruling elliptic
constellation for the month is the Lion,
easily distinguished by the Sickle, in the
handle of which is the bright star R» gu
lus. In the cast there is Bootes, Under
neath which are the stars of the Serpent,
but the fangs of the latter are innocuous,
for presumably they cannot pierce the
boots of the former, who tramples fear
lessly upon him. In the west Taurus is
passing from fcight. The Twins, followed
by Procyon, the Lesser Dog, are ap
proaching the mid-west, or prime ver
tical, and hanjj like glorious crowns over
Orion, as he pas-:cs to his setting place,
says the New York Sun.
While contemplating these worlds, shin
ing so brightly in the morning and in the
evening, we may. without too great an
effort of the imagination, think that iTley
contain beings moving with all the activ
ity of life; nations, civilizations, cities
like Babylon, Thebes. o r even something
approaching our own cosmopolitan Gotfi
am—human beings, in a word, who are
everything that we are, under different
physical forms, but no doubt reasoning
by the aid of the same principles of logic
which govern our thought, though their
manner of perception may be totally dif
lt rent from our own. Perhaps they have
escaped more quickly from the limbo of
barbarism and form intelligent, enlight
ened, pacific and fraternal societies, wor
shipping the beautiful, the true, and the
good.
The month opens with the sun 4 de
grees north of the equator, and the days
twelve hoLrs forty-one minutes in length.
The declination increases more than 10
degrees to the northward, with the addi
tion of one hour and nineteen minutes to
the day"s length. This should cause all
nature to bloom and p:jt on its lovely
spring coloring. On the Sth there is a par
tial eclfpsa of the sun, one of three allot
td to this year. We are not among the
favored this time, however, as the vari
ous phenomena attending the en
trance into the shadow and the depart
ure therefrom are not visible in our lati
tude.
The moon Is quite generous with us this
month, as it presents five phases, the last
quartering taking place on the first and
last days of the month. thcoming on the Bth, the day of Ihe partial
eclipse of the sun. first quartering coming
on the 15th, and the full moon coming on
the 226. People are wont to judge of trie
chances of there being a dry or we?
month throughout April by the Pos'tion~t>f
the horns of the crescent moon. It is an
excellent illustration of the persistence
with which the belief in lunar influence
upon mankind still lingers, thougCi re
peatedly proved to be false. The early
Chaldeans believed in the influence of the
position of the heavenly bodies upon hu
man life, and their system was later
elaborated by the Greeks. If we once as
sume that there is a relation between the
configuration of stars and planets in the
sky and affairs on the earth, it Is not
difficult to find coincidences which ap
parently prove that relation. It is a curi
ous fact that the Greek astrology ascrib
ed an influence to the appearance of the
moon's horffs. which the later belief in
its effect on rainfall seems to have sup
planted. Saturn is twice in conjunction
with the moon, once on the 2d and again
en the- 29th. On the 18th the planet is in
quadrature, or half-way between conjunc-
THE ST. PAUL, GLOBE, vSUNDAY, APRIL 6, 1902.
pocketbook. Some of the tables are col
lapsible, with folding supports, and may
be stowed in small space. The bats or
racquets are already acquiring as great
variety as golf clubs. There are already
tournament bats, club bats and other
kinds. The best have vellum drums, al
though drums are also made in parch
ment and wood. Good players prefer the
short-handled bats to those of regulation
length. Ping pong- balls are largely im
ported, although American manufactur
ers are experimenting with various mate
rials in hope of improving the celluloid
spheres now in use, giving the regula
tion s|ze and weight. The net is usually
hand-made, of from five to seven inches
In height, linen bound, with a fair de
gree of elasticity. The poles on which it
is stretched are shapely wooden pegs,
with leather bottoms, which protect the
table, to which they are fastened with
clamps. In each outfit there are usually
a half dozen bats or battledores and one
dozen balls. Whether the game Is to
have permanent place among the amuse
ments is a question that i&lt; being discuss
ed by those who have watched and ana.
lyzed the rise and fall of fads in the way
of indoor and outdoor amusements. Its
champions_ contend that it has every pos
sible requisite for the proper exercise of
body and mind that young women who
are noj equal to the roughing and phys
ical strain entailf-d by golf, tennis and
kindred strenuous sports will be heartily
and healthfully benefited by ping pong.
Others contend that the craze now
sweeping over Europe and America Is
but a passing fancy that will be rh&lt;-te&gt;
lived than the bicycle vogue, and that
the new amusement will die out with the
coming of the outdoor reason, and tb^f
ore another w'nter arrives its hold win
have been broken and the devotees of
other pleasures will return to their old
gods and idols.—Milwaukee Senfinel.</text>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016357/1902-05-03/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=PING-PONG+ping+pong+craze</id>
			<rel>1</rel>
			<text>P1NGPONO IS A CRAZE GRAZEHAS CRAZEHAS CRAZEHAS
HAS INVADED ALL SORTS OF PLACES PLACESFROM PLACESI PLACESFROM
FROM CLUBS TO HOTELS HOTELSOne HOTELSOne HOTELSOne
I
One Factory U I Timilnjr TlIrnln Out n Tl TIu Tlrogand TlrogandSets unand unandScti jflnll jflnllSet
Sets Set n l DnyTho Lay nj Tho 1ainlon l 1assinn lon For fie Sport StiortHas SOItIInOrown SportIIas
Has IInOrown Grown Up Siicldtnlj 6llItltenlllo Ilc urcsrj ureerue ureerueLnnJunlo uroalueLanguage ue ueLanguage
Language For Carne Term TermIn TennIn TermsIn
In the past few days persons walk walking walkIng walkIng
ing through the quiet uptown streets streetshave streetshave streetshave
have remarked about the number of ofhouses ofhouses ofhouses
houses through whose open windows windowscame windowscame windowscame
came the staccato pins pln 1 pong pongl ot the thexylonite thexylonlte thexylonlte
xylonlte table tennis ball Accordlug Accord AccordIng According
Ing to the stories which aro told by bydealers bytJealers bydealers
dealers In sporting goods thousandsotsets thousands thousandsof
of otsets sets of this game hare ha e been sold to tofamilies totam tofamilies
families tam Illes in the city and the demand demandappears tJemantJappears demandappears
appears to be increasing One taco factory tacotory fuetory
tory at Ohlcopee Falls alone is turn turnlug turn turning turnIng
ing out 1000 sets dolly and Is far t l be behind bebind behind
hind Its orders Pingpong Ptng poug outfits arc arcgoing arcgoing aregoing
going iu numbers now to suburban suburbangolf sulmrbangolf suburbangolf
golf clubs It shows what a bold the thesport thesport thesport
sport has taken on Its devotees that thateven tlUltoen thateven
even the golfing enthusiast must take takehis takehis takehlsping
his hlsping pingpong pIngp pnng ng to flu iinks links with him himOur hImOur himOur
Our greatest demand for complete completesets completesets completesets
sets including the regulation tables tableshas tableshas tableshas
has of course come from the clubs clubssaid clubssnld clubssaid
said a dealer yesterday But the thewomen thcwomcn thewomen
women women and children hare got the thefever thetever thefever
fever as bad ba as their brothers and andfathers andtathers andfathers
fathers If youre writing about the thepingpong theplngl1011g theping
pingpong ping pong craze you cant make it t too toostrong oo oostrong oostrong
strong So far as I know we havent haventsold haventsold haventsold
sold a set to any old ladles la les home yet yetbut yetbut yetbut
but I dare are say the game will reach reachthem reachthem reachthem
them in time This craze beats any anything anything anything
thing I ever heard of Our belief is isthat Isthat Isthat
that its only beginning Hot weather weathermay weathermay weathermay
may affect our sales somewhat but butwo butwe
wo look for an increased demand next nextfall nextfall nextfall
fall fallOur
Our indoor putting green In the theback theback theback
back of the th store has been occupied by bya bya
a pingpong ping poug table for several weeks weeksLfits weeksL weeksLets
Lets L ts of people who never saw the thegame thegame thegame
game come In here and watch a few fewsets fewsets fewsets
sets get fascinated by the play and nndcud riudend andend
end by buying racquets and balls anda and anda anda
a net to take home and set up on their theirdiningroom theIrdlnlngroom theirdining
diningroom dining room or billiard table Theres Theresa
a game going on here almost every everyhour ceryhOUl everyhour
hour of the day People cant seem to toget toget toget
get enough of IL ILThe It ItTho ItTho
Tho clubs have been and are still stilltlys stillt10 stilltl
tlys t10 tl o stronghold of the craze although althoughthe nlthouhtho althoughthe
the newspapers have had more to say sayabout sayabout sayabout
about the play In brokers ofllces of lces and andon andon andon
on ocean steamers So sudden has been beenthe beenthe beenthe
the passion for the sport and so much muchroom muchroom muchrOonl
room does a regulation table take up upthat upthat upthat
that most of the clubs have had to togive togive togive
give up some other sport in whole or orIn 01In orin
In part for a time or else sacrifice sacrificepart sacrltleepart sacrificepart
part of their diningroom space No Nobody Nobody Nobody
body seems to object however Even Eventho Erentho Eventhe
tho most sedate of club loungers al although nltbough although
though he may begin by scoffing at atthe atthe atthe
the childs play ends in becoming becomingcither becomIngeither becomingeither
either an enthusiast entllUslastor or a disappointed disappointedbut lsappolnledbut
but persistent duffer dufferCollege dufferCollega dufferCollege
College clubs or other clubs fre frequented tree treequented frequented
quented by younger men are the worst worstsufferers worstsufferers worstsufferers
sufferers from the pingpong ping pong malady maladyTho maladylo maladyI1he
I1he Tho lo Harvard 1 alvald Club early In Inthcwlutol Inthcwlutolput the winter winterput winterput
put up the little nets on its billiard billiardtables bllliardtables billiardtables
tables and billiards have scarcely
been played there since Members Memberspay Memberspay Iemberlpay
pay the same amount per hour for forplaying forplayIng forplaying
playing pingpong ping pong that they formerly formerlywere 1ormerl 1ormerlwero formerlywere
were cbnrgdtl for fortbe the use of the bit billiard bllliard bitHard
liard tables The club has since set up upIn upIn upin
In addition a veal ping pingpong pong board boardThe boardThe boardThe
The Yale Club has four tables in one oneof oneot oneof
of the class diningrooms on the ninth ninthfloor ninthfioor ninthfloor
floor The Cornell University Club Clubgives Clubgives Clubgives
gives up half Its diningroom to the thopastime thepastime thepastime
pastime and the House UouseOommlttee UouseOommltteenow Committee Committeenow Committeenow
now talks of letting the whole apart apartment apattment apartment
ment bo used for It so many of the themembers themembers themembers
members want to play and pingpong pingpongtables plngpongtables ping pong pongtables
tables can be used ns dining lnlnl tables if ifit ItIt ifit
it takes too long to make the change changeIn changeIn changeIn
In n Brooklyn Droold n athletic club the ping plugpongcrs pingpongers pingpongers
pongers have Invaded the the handball handballcourt handballcourt handballcourt
court Most of these resorts Ies rts have had hador hador hador
or are having pingpong ping pong tdurnamentsand tdurnaments tournamentsnnd
nnd clever players bare Jave been dowel developed deeloped doweloped
oped in the course of a few weeks weeksBoardinghouses weeksBoardinghouses weeksBoardinghouses
Boardinghouses In all parts of town townhave townhave townhave
have been hard hit by the craze The Thelong ihelong Thelong
long table ta ble in the back parlor l llor makes a agood agood agood
good pingpong pl ping gllong pong board and a till the young youngman youngman youngman
man In the hall bedroom two flights flightsup filghtsup flightsup
up takes delight In making the star starboarder starboatder starboarder
boarder look like thirty cents The Thelandladies Thelandladies rholandladIes
landladies are arc rc not enthusiastic overthe over overthe 001the
the game because when played In the theevening theevening theevening
evening it has a n tendency to develop developa developrobust
a robust appetite for late suppersThe suppers suppersThe suppersThe
The vernacular of tbo sport has not notyet notyet notyet
yet reached a l high degree of development develop development oelop11ent
ment For the present as Is the case casewith casewltbany casewith
wltbany with any new game players make free freewith treewltb freewith
with words nnd phrases plll ses proper to toother toother toother
other branches of sport Expressions Expressionslike Expressionslike
like You dealt cm the last time timeThis timeThis timeThis
This cue Is rotten Off side are areheard areIleard areheard
heard around the board Picturesque Picturesquelanguage Plctulesquelanguage Picturesquelanguage
language of n different character is isalso Isnlso isalso
also common The elusive celluloid celluloidsphere celluloidsphere celluloidsphere
sphere is as conducive to profanity as nsthe asthe asthe
the guttn guttnpercha percha A well known lawn lawntennis lawntennis lawntennis
tennis player has n novelty in the way wayof wayof wayof
of pingpong ping pong profanity When he hemakes hemakes hemakes
makes a fault he shouts Fudge I or orGoodness 01Goollness oreGoodness
Goodness gracious He explains that thatho thatbo thatlie
ho learned the game by playing with wltl1his withbis withhis
his sisters and it Isnt worth cussln cusslnabout cusslnabout cussinabout
about anyway anywaNew New York SunSmall Sun</text>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1902-07-13/ed-1/?sp=39&amp;q=ping-pong&amp;r=-0.06,0.725,0.801,0.419,0</id>
			<rel>1</rel>
			<text>THE REPUBLIC: SUNDAY. JULY 13, 1902.
  PING-PONG 15 THE WARM-WEATHER DIVERSION OF YOUNG 5T. LOUIS SOCIETY MATRONS.
  POLISHED TABLES IN CENTER OF REAR
  LAWNS AFFORD CONVENIENT COURTS.
  WITH STARS AND ELECTRIC LIGHTS FOR ILLUMINATION
  THE GAME BECOMES AN EVENING PASTIME.
  VELVETY GRASS PROVES RESTFUL TO
  THE EYES and COOLING TO TIRED FEET
  AiiFS
  S?
  L
  a Srrrm mrvyis
  
  
  imiiniiiiHiiiiiui
  i n a f liiii it- j-
  uiinmiuimm'1'"'"
  ll,,r-- CUM II f UV -Hl frf2.JtTrTr Ufl
  iwS55jw?S
  lumuiim'iiiiiiiin'iinim
  srJ""'ltt''u,ZZz?? 'Th?
  ""ni)iii,i,.Tl '."'WrUCfTfiC?!
  Zr"","H7WJlni .7- UUjm
  i
  i
  I
  fa
  SkV
  1
  
  i
  It
  r
  I
  V
  ;&amp;s1
  K
  .t;
  Mrs. Craufnrr? n..,-
  Donovan and Mr; -Frnpc
  the' table. Mrs. Ralph
  Mrs. Mae W;ggs looking
  i n h wrwrtp'gnF,TTi
  Kr C?.wford Ptttv-iti ef St. Lool has
  ohrtd Q problem o tni-Wng hnsbaad.
  fT7illy cad irlenfti, eomfort&amp;blt at boma,
  rn tn tbe hottest -weather. At her beau
  tiful Mxideaoe. No. C27 West Plus bonle
  Trt3. gmrTrr has so terrors for tho:a who
  Uv thero.
  rtec uuidtwr of 7esra Mrs. Dcncaa has
  rtfoxtd to shut tip her hcrass In tha t-ora-aa;
  cr It her hcsfcond behind to itais
  tfi trlth tha dlscoroforU of a loaeljr ex
  irtzDoa. As Mr. Bcccan's business keeps
  htm la tha eitr tha best part of tha hot
  twin, lira. Duncan declines to co away
  br heraalf. In tha month of August they
  go toxsthtr to some Northern or Eastern
  raajJt and com hack together, irben vaca
  tlsn thsa is ep.
  Tha roolt of tM thourhtfolners and tm
  Mtflshaass oa Mrs. Duncan's part Is trrat
  tlMraJs a yerr channlnr. comfortabla
  hocashold erst on the boulevard, where so
  zsasr bosses have tha blinds drawn and
  tha windows tUhtlr dosed.
  While the front ef the Duncan rxrese has
  that gs!al aspect of epenesa In tha after
  Tmwtt. wbca tha sun Is coins down. It is in
  the back yard that tha Duncans find their
  real enjoyment.
  FingpPong Transplanted to
  tha Cool Back Yard.
  Th4 irrely rame of plac-pcnt, to which
  n" "''"sal
;4?
M
the game. Mrs. Crawford .1
Mrs. Dan Donovan and Mrs. 7,p
Boogher umpiring.
-?'o
N
NS
44
bA
ki
m
V..
,.VW
1U .1
niij
4
fe7-Jf(f

''r2
w
H"
n
Ji
is:
r
m
,uV

X?
BrVT

io
-Vft n
a rause in the Oame.
wigg; and Mrs. Ernest Boogher ap
propriating the candy.
i
eToady aftemoea hrrax to Mrs. Daacsrfs
home her little cotarie of pInsponf friends
for practice or recreation. The youns; ma
trons of this particular summer plng-pons
party are Mrs. Ralph Orthwein. Mrs. Daa
Donovan. Mrs. Mae WIks, Mrs. Ernest
Boogher and their hostes. Duncan. In
the eveninr the husbands Join the rame
r-V
:t
Sgi
ISS

ru .-.j3
ESS
82
'S47
tt
V',??
VY. "rv! .A
wm,jjxw
Mrs- Crawford Duncan's St. Bc.
wi. yVV "ard. Prince, taking his bath.
g


usa
Mrs. Mae r
ef theta are s1ay-t-htJices this seasoa, for
if any cf them so away at an it win sot be
tin the summer la nearly oxer.
The Udlee generally wear their shirt
waist suits for the gama.
linmimiiiL
n n
A-I
-r VJ.5
?3P1
v7B!f9
riaV&amp;'f
nmaott,
'ttnrauiiiit
Mrs. Dan
a.
r
"Atf vj w: fc, gk ---3

l"X1j
,E;
7' V.
sissi

5fV?ZL-jl:35
i zl- Mre- fr,(nA n.. J A I
rr- iiiij. uiawiuiu- LSUlliail dllU iil'.
Jj an Donovan playing Pin--F 0.
fc-i'
scr uuiwiTs, TirTea tns Bisxaaur
sotony f this summer idyl among society
folks, who seem to have banded them
selves together for the purpose of making
the season as socially agreeable as the
long winter months. The Fourth of July
was one of those delightful plcnlo days.
Tennis a Featnre on
the Orthwein Lawn.
Jest now Mrs. Ralph Orthwein is having
laid out at her home en Bartmtr avenue
a tennis court, and that game will also he
played with the stars and electrlo lights
for an illumination,
Mrs. Duncan's ptcg-pocg set win he the
i principals of the tennis games to be played
at sight tn Cabasne, With so much to en
tertain the younger society element, it Is
doubtful if many more will Join the earlier
exodus during the month of August. Mrs,
Mae Wiggs has decided to remain at home
to keep house for her father, the genial Pat
Short, who has rent his wife and grand
son away, hut prefer for himself the
comforts of his charmingly appointed
home. Mrs. Wiggs. who calls her father
"son," looks after the cooking herself, an!
leaves even the fascinating ping-pong, at
which she is a adept, to return home n
Mrs. Duncan's home. Way hack la tha
yard, under a shady tree is a, large atrsara
tank with a canopy oa top to protect tha
bather frost the sun. This Is tha tab la
which Prise. Mrs. Duncan's Mr St. Bs
t.t. takes his dally plunge, The tns Ja
filled with fresh water three times s week.
At the bottom tha tub has a flow-oS. fas
tened with a ecrfc. Any handy hoy eoaW
construct one of these tubs, which has re
tin lining to keep the wood from rottls-g.
Whlle Mrs. Duncan's friends were playing
ping-pong the other afternoon. Prince had
his bath. As he Jumped out and among
tha guests he was not very careful of their
fresh and crisp toilets, but sprayed thira
with the water, which lie shook oat of his
shaggy mane. However, these are incidents
that make things all the more pleasant far
the young matrons, whose healthful recre
ation is the admiration of the few neigh
oars, who, like them, are remaining at
home.
</text>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1902-05-18/ed-1/?sp=46&amp;q=PING+PONG+ping+pong+ping-pong&amp;st=text&amp;r=0.408,0.646,0.693,0.724,0</id>
			<rel>1</rel>
			<text>SUMMER DELIGHTS OF
  B1 LJ
  ti
  I
  F. L. VA3IDEVEER &amp;SV HARRY BLO(
  Two well-known young attorneys, who are experts at the
  Written for the Sunday Republic.
  I ping We tear our clothes.
  Thou pongst You raise the deuce, if
  He pongs They fall In a faint.
  Verb, Irreg. Origin, Japan. Inf,
  s to ping-pong.
  St. Xiouls is ping-pong maa. Everybody
  plays It; and so enthusiastic are the de
  votees of the game that It is now assured
  that the game will run through the sum
  mer. But it Is a winter game, declares some
  one. We will make It a summer jjame, fben,
  is the ifsponse.
  PING PONG.
  E.ETT,
  game of Ping-Pong.
  In Its Indigenous clime it is a game for
  all the year. Summer and winter alike, it
  is a game, not only for men, but also for
  women and children.
  Tor more than three centuries how much
  more no one knows ping-pong has been a
  game of great Importance.
  Of course, the name is inane, but there is
  I
  a lot to tho game besides tho name; and
you may call it with perfect propriety, "ta
ble tennis." That will save your feelings.
Tor tho game is nothing moro or less
than a diminutive gamo of tennis It is
counted exactly like tennis; requires as
many players; furnishes as much exercise,
and offers as great an opportunity for tho
practice of subtle heart-charms.
Who plays ping-pong? The answer is
easy: Kverybody. The popularity- of tho
gamo has increased so much in tho last
few months that it has become necessary
to manufacture the racquets and balls in
St. Louis; tho foreign markets are unablo
to furnish even half of what Is required
It is not only a fad, but has undoubtedly
como to stay as much as tennis did years
ago
Tennis is still a popular game. We have
champions; national and local. So It will
bo with ping-pong before another year has
rolled around. Already In St Louis me
have tournaments, championships and
prizes at ping-pong parties. There is great
rivalry between clubs and between mem
bers of clubs. One cannot go to dine now
adays without having to tako part in a
gamo of ping-pong after the dinner. It Is
everywhere and all-absorbing.
Not only men of leisure and ladies of
quality aro indulging In it, hut business
men and college stoudents and women
mho have to busy themselves about a hun
dred and one things during the day. Hv-
erybody has the fever. A ping-pong parlor
on Locust street is crowded every day for
several hours with players and there Is no
sign of any loss of Interest In the game.
Bankers and brokers find that the gamo
gives them moro and better exercise in a
short time that they have been able to get
in any other way. Among the devotees of
the game are Allen West, Dwight Davis,
Harold Kauffman, Hunt Turner and Jim
Drummond. They frequently find tlmo to
meet during the day for a game. Usually
it Is for but a short time, but occaslonaily
they become so Interested that tfcey finish
the afternoon at the table.
But the season for ping-pong Is after
dinner. Then at private residences and at
the clubs there is Invariably a game In
progress. Special rooms have been fitted up
in houses large enough to accommodate
them, and In the clubhouses where the par
ticularly ardent worshippers at tho shrine
of the celluloid ball and the racquet may
commune with their own kind.
Stuart Stlckney, he of golf fame, is a
"fiend" at ping-pong. He says himself that
he has to struggle to keep away from a table
during tho day In order that he may devote
himself to business. But at night and on
Saturdays he gives may to th desire and
Instead of playing golf he stands at a ping
pong table until he is about ready to drop.
The exercise In the game will be ac
knowledged when It Is known that a tennis
and a golf champion have almost forsaken
their favorite game for the enticing ping
pong. Dwight Davis does not play tennis
as much as he used to; and Stuart Stlckney
is rarely seen with his clubs Yet. both ex
celled in their special branches of athletic.
But ping-pong is a winter game, said one
who was only half converted. Needless to
say he could play only fairly. A host rose
to contradict him. Already many lawns are
being prepared for a table during the um
mer. All that is necesasry 1 an even place I
for the table and light enough so that the'
balls may be seen In the evening. In Japan 1
and in England the game Is played the year
'round. Why not In St. Louis?
Evening ping-pong parties during the
summer are already assured. It Is not dis
tinctly a rich man's or woman's game, ai
has often been sapposed. but almost every
one may havo a set Tha sets aro cheap
even as compired with tennis sets. Wher
ever there is room for a dining table therfj
is room for ping-pong, and tho fascination
that the gamo nor. holds, especially amon
tho smart set. cannot bo downed by warn;
m cather.
Among tho particularly pood plng-ponr;
rooms in bt, Louis, asldo from tho clubs,
are those at tho Drummond's. Mis Wtck
him's and at tho McKittrick's. Cvery evo
ning ping-pong holda sway. It is proper
nowadays for young ladies to take soma
form of physical exercise, and ping-ponB
combines all the pleasure that they- may
find in any exercise and affords all tha
sport of play. j
Ralph and Walter McKittrlck, Arthua
Shepley and Dan KIrby- are among the best
and most enthusiastic players In the city.
The Country Club and tho Florissant Club
are utterly crazed over tho game. At pres
ent It holds the trumps over all other
games, and from Indications it will be tha
popular game of the summer at both clubs.
Of course, this does not mean that tenn!
and golf and polo will not havo their de
votees, but ping-pong will bo tho most frequently-
played gamo of tho season.
The women of the city are us enthusias
tic .as the men-possibly more so. and they
havo their claims upon the attention of tho
men and their sports. Ping-pong looks and
sounds llko a game that does not requira
as much cndtiranco and strength as other11
spons anu tint is sid to bo tho reuson
that the women have taken It up. As t,
matter ot fact. It is as violent as nlmnst
any gamo th it Is popular with many peo
ple, but It seems so playful that tho weaker
be. have seized upon It.
It is a fact that one business man of this
c ty a man or more than usual corpulence-
has reduced his weight by forty pounds
playing ping-pong. And If the truth mi.ro
known, it is probably true tint several
women have been enabled to become mora
sylph-like through the medium of the game.
But that Is .v matter concerning which
women will not talk.
Women who are onenlv .anient nl.-ners
of
ny
ping-pong are rot the ones of whom any
one can say they play to reduce thel
weight. They- are modern women In every
may, and have taken up tho game not only
because it Is tho fad, but also because it
Is a g ime that enables them to keep In
good physical condition It is proper no
longer for momtn to be weak and requiring
the attention of maids and menr but they
mut be able to cope with the strongest.
Accordingly, they tako as much exercise,
comparatively, as men And ping-pong of
fers them something in the way of a gam
that has not been offered by any thins
else.
Among the more prominent women play
ers of ping-pong are Mrs. James Drurr
mond, Mrs. William' Gregg, Mri. Laurence
J. Mornn MIs ickham. Mis Mitchell.
Mrs. E O. Stanard, Mrs. W. II. Walker
and Mrs. Goodman King. Each of theso
has an elaborate ping-pong room fitted up
nt her house, and parties are frequent. It
is not at nit unusual for them to meet in
the morning and play arduously befora
luncheon. It serves as an excellent appe
tizer. The game was hroiight 'to St. Louis by
two people at about the same time. Mrs.
E. H. Semple ot Westminster place be
came enamored of the game while abroad
last summer, and when she returned she
set up a table at once. Sirs. Sidney Walker
appeared on the scene at about the sama
time, an enthusiastic player of the game.
That mas its start In thi3 city. It did not
take long to bring the sport to its present
position, but these two St. Louisans havo
been instrumental In making it a fad.
One of the best players among the women
is Mrs. Lewis Haywood She has for sev
eral months been a devotee, and lias ac
quired remarkable 'kill in handling tho
racquet. Mrs. John Fowler Is another ex
cellent player, and Mrc Dan Taylor, Mrs,
Campbell Smith and Mrs. Frank HammeS
are also in the first class. I
V
1
W-u&amp;gg
&amp;gj&amp;4. &amp;JS3figgi3g3
j' m t.
:-x&amp;ft73aBSflffi h. "W g.fe-tgp
ing&amp;&amp;$&amp;ifjser
itt4&amp;ss.-2S</text>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059523/1902-05-25/ed-1/?sp=21&amp;q=daft+ping-pong&amp;st=text&amp;r=-0.259,-0.201,1.07,1.07,0</id>
			<rel>1</rel>
			<text>DAFT ON PING-PONG
  Washington Entranced With
  Game, Which Is Played
  in Many Homes
  'fcOOM OF TIGHT CORSET
  f(Xew Diversion Has Phenotncnal
  Hold on All Sort* and Condi-
  tion*. From 9teM Senators
  tv DudtliiiK Debutantes.
  Special to The Globe.
  WASHINGTON, D. C. May 21.—Mover
  j lias the national capital been so com-
  T-letely enslaved by the fascinations of a
  game, indoor or outdoor, as it has fallen
  (under the seductive influence of the won
  jdc-rful new game, which, having set all
  J l^ngland crazy, has come with- a power
  to] stride across the Atlantic to exercise
  its potent influence upon our social life.
  i As a prominent leader of Washington
  I society remarked the other day, "Wash
  ington has fairly gone ping-pong mad."
  Conversation in capital society has now
  i foe-come impregnated with the peculiar
  I terms of the new pastime. Where for
  merly one would hear "social precedence"
  and "rising man," one now hears "clever
  i (half volleyer" and "invincible striker
  I out."
  "Love" and "advantage" as topics of
  social conversation have now a ping-pong
  significance entirely foreign to their for
  xtx-r meaning among the capital gossips.
  The ping-pong party has entirely sup
  planted the whist party arid the bridge
  circle.
  The peculiar ping-pong of the celluloid
  balls as they are beaten to and fro (from
  ■which the game derives its name) is now
  to be heard j in every Washington home
  from the palatial mansion of the fam
  -1 ily of the men who shape the nation's.
  I destiny on Pennsylvania avenue to the
  humble residence of the congressional
  I bootblack in the eastern section of the
  i city. Years are a matter of no consid
  ©ration among the devotees of the sport.
  The mature matron whose nod or frown
  I Oias settled one way or the other the so
  cial aspirations of mar.v- a newcomer
  .at the capital is as frequently to be seen
  i exerting herself in a manner wonderful
  to behold, to keep the little swiftly pass- j
  ing celluloid ball from dropping on her
  I side of the net, as is the beautiful bud
  ding debutante who, with flushed face,
  eyes sparkling with enthusiasm- and ex
  citement. and bared arms wildly but
  Withal skillfully circling the air, is a
  cSaily testimonial to the aethestic features
  of the game.
  Strike* nil Classes.
  Nor are the enthusiasts of the new
  gam" to be found only among the fairer
  sex, Washington masculinity has given
  itself to ping-pong with an abandon
  ,Nor ar^ the enthusiasts .of the now
  which would furnish a profitable study to
  the seeker- of pysehologieal phenomena.
  Staid congressmen, dignified senators.
  Learned members of the bench and bar
  When they meet together nowadays dis
  cuss not, the political significance of the
  lim.s. but the latest-make of ping-pong
  racquet.
  This -may be regarded as gross exagger
  ation. It is a potent fact, however, that
  ping p has attained a surprising vogue
  ■among Washington's public men.
  All the leading hotels and cafes are
  hastening to open up ping-pong parlors
  on their premises, so that their distin
  guished patrons may indulge .to their
  heart's content in the game.
  Senator Maur.a. when asked the other'
  ■day whether he favored the. erection of aj
  ping-pong parlor in the national capital,
  l>uckercd up.his brow* and gave the mat
  tor a few minutes' serious consideration
  before discussing the idea with a smile.
  Congressman Sulzer, when asked to ex
  plain the tremendous hold that ping-pong
  has taken upon members of the-house,
  said that it is a wonderful game for~ex
  erclse. and gives one a good hand to
  sustain the handshaking proclivities of
  the vast army of well meaning citizens
  who swoop down upon unwilling repre
  sentatives of the people with all the re
  lentless energy of the notorious New
  Jersey musquito upon its helpless victim.
  As may be supposed, the stores have
  not been slow to take advantage of the
  commercial possibilities of the craze. In
  -addition to the fact that some of the
  larger dry goods emporiums are opening
  up ping-pong saloons for the accommo
  dation of their patrons, the new game
  has an important bearing upon the latest
  styles. The ping-pong waist is prom
  inently- displayed in the shop windows,
  find is a phenomenal seller; while the
  new forms of neckwear for women and
  men bear handsomely embroidered figure.*
  ■of ping-pong racquets and balls upon
  their silken folds.
  Doom of the Tight Corset.
  One important reform the game prom,
  ises to effect, which may render rational,
  the development which has been lavished'
  upon it by England and America and im
  mortalize the new game as one of the
  most valuable and beneficent reform fac
  tors of the century.
  Ping-pong may abolish the tight laced
  ■corset.
  Ping-pong is essentially an informal
  game to be played at the spur of the
  moment, as the whim seizes. It is a
  game to be introduced by the smiling
  hostess after the last vestige of the din
  "■ner has been cleared away and ti;o
  white table cloth is removed to make
  way for the ping-pong net. Consequently
  as the rapid movement and freedom of
  body S necessary to me ping-pong player
  renders the corset impossible, the charm
  ing diner out has either to leave off her
  corsets when she dresses to attend a
  modern dim party or run the risk of
  having to stand against the wall in ail
  the-prim symmetry of a corseted waist
  and, watch the merry movements of her
  more fortunate sisters who, with grace
  fully swing forms, keep the merry cellu
  loid ball ping-ponging across the table
  at a lively pace to the intense admira
  tion of the man with the racquet on th^
  other side of the table and .every other
  man In the room. v
  This good may ping-pong do; bu other
  wise what peculiar qualities has the same
  to '-rive it phenomenal popularity? Strict
  ly speaking it is nothing more or less
  then a table adaptation of lawn tennis
  and tennis, while possessing to an equal
  and even greater degree the same physi
  cal benefits and sporting fascinations of
  its replica has never attained the vogue
  which has been vouchsafed to ping-pong.
  Played on Dining Table.
  Ping-pong is played on an ordinary din-
  Ing table and its only accessories are
  posts tp hold the net, the net itself
  vellum string or wood-racquets and cellu-
  loid balls: The game is for two people
  one standing on one end of the table,
  the other opposite. The player who first
  delivers the ball is called the server The
  Other the striker out. i The service is
  strictly underhand and is delivered from
  beyond the end of the table.
  The: ball served must drop on the table
  beyond the net and is then in piav. if
  it dops into the net or off the table it
  counts to the striker out
  The server wins a stroke if the striker
  out fails to return the service or ball in
  play of the table.
  The striker out wins a stroke If the
  server fails to return the ball in play or
  makes a foul in service.
  On either player winning his first stroke
  the score la 15. The second stroke brings
  the score to 30; the third stroke is called
  •40 and the fourth stroke wins a game
  The player who wins the first six games
  -wins a set.-
  This is all there really is to the game
  of ping-pong. Certainly it Is a skill de
  manding and skill acquiring game. It
  lias simplicity and cheapness to recom
  mend it. It is far better from a hygenie
  standpoint than a majority of parlor
  prames and is an extremely socialble and
  interesting pastime. It is. for these rea
  sons and its similarity to tennis, a game
  calculated to prove attractive to the"
  younger members of both sexes.
  But why It has set the people of two
  countries almost crazy: why old as well
  as young-have taken up ping-pong when
  they would not as much as look at an
  other form of sport; why the game
acquired such a vogue on the other side
that one serious British magazine writer
has accused; English society of being
more interested in the records of ping- j
pong champion than in the fortune of
the British troops in South Africa and
has prophetically croaked of Nero fid
dling, while Rome is burning— are
phenomena that: it would puzzle the
average human being to account for; and
the answer is certainly not forthcoming
from the devotees of the game.
9 -—Bertram Lebhar.</text>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1902-06-01/ed-1/?sp=13&amp;q=PING-PONG&amp;st=text&amp;r=0.096,0.478,0.828,0.866,0</id>
			<rel>1</rel>
			<text>ECHOES FROM PING -PONG
  IT was a glorious meet."
  "How much did you lose?"
  "It is to be hoped that King Ed-
  ward will patronize the game ex-
  warn -wm c*
  tensively."
  "It was so thoughtful In the" genial
  hostess to pass around chewing gum and
  chicken salad."
  "Mr Leon Lilac opened a costly snuff-
  ln the shape of a racque, and Mr.
  Harry Heart wore a pair of ping-pong
  trousers."
  "It is much to be commended that,
  thoueh there were numerous bad plays,
  all strenuous language was eliminated,
  The strongest expression was 'Oh,
  fudge!' by Mr. Charley Callow, after
  he had driven the ball through a thin
  mirror."
  "It is not known as yet. if the different
  *y.a Hoiie-h'tful
  churches will sanction the dengntiui
  game. Many of the fellows hope not.
  There is always so much spice in any-
  thing a little wicked." j
  "Ping-Pong has eclipsed bridge whist
  for parlor gambling Severa^
  young ladies present -lost their matinee
  allowances for a year. It is also whis-
  pered that certain mesfiames will not be
  able to contribute toward charity func-
  tions for some time."
  "Of course, the inevitable wit waa
  present. Mr. Freddy Wages remarked
  that while table tenn.s was a quiet pame,
  it could not be played without a racquet,
  For this outburst of brilliancy he was
  rewarded with loud and continuous ap-
  DJ ause
  ..The' re has been much discussion as
  t0 wnether a physical culture course is
  essential to those intending to take the
  game up. We think it is. Mr. Harold
  m&amp; limlted hlmself t0 ten clgar.
  eUeg per day and only chewed g.um after
  meals. He also says that he takes vig
  orous exercise by dressing himself, in
  stead of allowing his valet to do so, as
  previously.There can be no doubt," said an ex
  pert the other day, "that the constant
  watching- of the ball which is required in
  the game tends to aggravate a^eakneaw
  of the eyes. The moving of the muscUf
  which control the eye3 wearies them after
  an ordinary game. The control of. the
  eyes is really the most essential part, for
  the game calis into requisition compara
  tively few muscles.
  "I have heard much of the ping-pong
  ankle, but as the ankle is used compara
  tively little in playing I do not think that
  the maiaUy is one.v/hich the player need
  count. Some players find that the dorsal
  muscles arc easily tired, and the man
  who stoops a great deal in his effort to
  find the balls which have been knocked to
  the carpet is lijtcly to suffer from sore
  ness and inflammation of the muscles
  alrout the pftins. There is in my opinion
  j. ping-pong eye, although I deny that
  there is si ping-pong face.
  "It has been said that the muscles of
  the legs and arms are often wearied By
  the game. This .is true in a. sense, but I
  think that the eye and the brain -will be
  exhausted :n ping-pong long before the
  muscles used in sending and returning
  balls can be affected to any appreciable
  extent."
  ISEASES with strange names have
  Dloliowtd in the wake of ping-pong,
  J.ut the real pang is not a fanciful
  une. for the watching of the cellu
  loid* sphere really strains the eyes.
  Let London surgeons talk as they will
  about tei.dosyr.ovitis "and p^ig-ponS an
  kles: all these are as nothing compared
  to tho'strair.ed muscles of the eye of the
  Ail ping-pong devotees, even experts,
  suffer from the ping-pong eye more or
  Jess. Other muscles employed to playing
  th* game are ""speedily co-ordinated. To
  develop a proper technique is^ing-pong
  is no easy matter, and in the endeavor
  the eye suffers the most.
  There is a ping-pong wrist, of course,
  and a ping-pong back, but the player who
  can return a ball a hundred times or so
  suffers comparatively little from these.
  The tyro who bends often to pick up the
  balls -which bound upon the carpet is the
  one who is most likely to complain of
  In time he learns, however, to make the
  optical nerves save the exertions of the
  muscles. Then he requires a ping-pony
  i ji^jlimii
  Not much strength is required in tho
  game. A little more vigorous than bil
  liards and not quite bo arduous as tennis.
  of which it is a cousin german, pins-
  THE S U^J)AY CALL.
  pcng appeals to those who have the quick
  eye.
  The skillful player can keep his body
  almost rigid, and standing In front of the
  table send the ball backward and forward
  with scarcely a movement of a muscle
  except those of the wrists. Many or the
  players are able- to sit In one of the
  chairs such as are used by spectators in
  billiard games, and still keep the ball go
  ing rapidly.
  Physicians say that many ping-pong
  players suffer from an inflammation of
  the eye. and champion players add their
  Testimony. The constant watching of the
  ball is liable to cause heaoaclies, or, 'in
  other words, to cause irritation to spread
  from the overworked optical mu.-des.
  The pir.g-ro"g eye is often bloodshot.
  The only way to cure it is to stop play
  ing and to give the overworked eye a
  chance to rest. Th!s the ping-pong devo
  te*- objects to doing. When ho becomes
  absorbed in the game he persists in play
  ing it in season and out of season.
  There are many ping-pong table's which
  served originally in dining-rooms. The
  man who plays upon them is prone fo
  contract the ping-pong eye. The ideal
  table should be dark green^This color is
  easy on the eye. A retired billiard or
  poo! table is well adapted to the game,
  as far*"as the effect upon the eye is con
  cerned. The ball is dazzling white. It
  THE PING PONG
  STRAIN ON THE EYE
  MUSCLES</text>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1902-09-21/ed-1/?sp=11&amp;q=ping-pong&amp;r=-0.92,-0.035,2.841,1.485,0</id>
			<rel>0</rel>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1900-06-21/ed-1/?sp=12&amp;amp;q=history+of+table+tennis&amp;r=-0.239,0.058,0.977,0.353,0</id>
			<rel>0</rel>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86090528/1916-06-22/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=history+of+table+tennis&amp;r=-0.175,0.63,1.151,0.417,0</id>
			<rel>0</rel>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1912-06-15/ed-1/?sp=9&amp;q=history+of+table+tennis&amp;r=0.443,0.381,0.609,0.22,0</id>
			<rel>0</rel>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89053684/1902-05-15/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=ping+pong</id>
			<rel>0</rel>
		</result>
		<result>
			<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016413/1902-07-12/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=ping+pong&amp;st=text&amp;r=0.386,0.457,0.553,0.579,0</id>
			<rel>1</rel>
			<text>PING-PONG IN PORT.
  (Continued from Page 1
  few minutes now and tden In mutinl
  reminiscence, si)s that he himself has
  dabbled n little In the game He baa
  not ct advanced far enough to tell a
  ping from a pong houewi but Is will
  ing to learn, If onlv from 1I.4 phig
  pongy conversation of others
  A half dozen oases of ping-pong sets
  arrived from Sin Francisco In the
  American batk. Knlulani )esterd.i)
  morning The rfame is evltlentl) gain
  ing In favor In Honolulu when tho
  paraphernalia begins to come Into the
  Paradise ofths Pacific in such bulk
  Knthuslasti slorj In the fact that
  Hawaii Is ar. American tcnltui), 11
  for no other reason than that they
  would be compellel to pj) tint) oil Me
  tools of ping-pong If the count!) stood
  to Ameilia Ir tre relation of n foieign
  land
  Numbers of tl.r members of the cus
  tom house foi i- have Invested In ping
  pong outfits and off hours at home aie
  imbued very pleasantl) except when It
  tomes to g'ovelllng on the floor and
  under furniture for the balls. It Is even
  hinted tint a fondness for the game
  has devolujied in quatteta hlghei than
  the foiee of Inspectors In the custom
  house. ThU rumor, howevci. has not
  )ct been verified
  The new Sprei kels boats are up to
  date ns far as ping-pong Is contented
  The Sierra, Sonoma ami Ventuti 111 e
  all mined with plug-pong outfits and
  when the Sonouu and Ventuia weie in
  port a few dajs ago many people fiom
  nshoro noticed the tables and othei gear
  rigged out on the piomenade decks of
  these elegant steamets
  It Is said that uffle-boaid aboaul tho
  boats of the 'jtiJiIlun-Austrullan lino
  will soon give phce to ping-pong la
  fact tho game ha.i ahead) been inlro
  ducetl aboard one of the boats, tin Mo
  ana,
  Sailing vessels Ibeused to cam pas
  sengers, sin h as the Kalulanl and th
  Coronatlo, will not maintain their
  popularity unless the) Invest In ping
  pong outfits
  There is tome talk of Inttocliiclng
  ping-pong aboard the Kinnii Admiral
  Jleckley Is heaitll) In favoi of tho
  scheme. It Is suggested however, that
  n rule should be made that the captain
  refrain from playlngthe game, as It nas
  n faculty of so absorbing tho attention
  that other Ideas aie llkel) to suffer In
  consequence
  What If It should tome to the pass
  when two pln?s of the bell meant
  "go ahead" to tie ei.g.neer, while a
  "pong" signified stophei'" There la
  a possibility that the lolling of the
  Klnau would Interfere with the gamo
  aboaid that vessel in this ease many
  balls would decorate the walo of tlm
  speedy craft all the wa) from Hono
  lulu to Hllti
  Puibei Slmeison of the steamer Man
  lia Loa belli ves In ping-pong, nccoid
  lug to his fi lends, and Inasmuch as his
  fatbei Is master of that splendid
  paektt bo might he nble to Induct) his
  parent to entourage the game an ong
  the passengem aboard the steamer-
  In the event o- the game continuing
  In Its populnilty on the wateifiont tho
  tiny Is likely to soou come when tho
  WANTS
  For Want Column See Page Six
  FOR SALE.
  RESTAURANT FOR SALE Com
  pletely equipped; best location In
  Honolulu: for sale at a Largaln. Hn
  qulru at once at California Lunch
  Room, cor. Hotel and Union Sts.
  219C-1W
  sailors will make a demand for ping
  pong outfits In the forecastle. All kinds
  of possibilities loom up on the horl
  zon of the now almost universal game.
  It would be a dreadful thing If a vessel
  should arrive here from Newcastle, for
  example', and tne crew snoulil lodge a
  complaint with the Federal authorities
  to the effect that the master of that
  vessel had cut down the sailors' sup-
  pi) of ping pong balls during the voy
  ugo.
  Frank J. Turk, tho handsomo nnd
  popular sailor shipping agent of Queen
  street, when caked as to his views on
  ping pong, said that he was too busy to
  pluy tho game, besides Oscar Lewis,
  his former partner. Is now In business
  on the Coast, nnd lfu Is about tho only
  man who would have an) chance in
  the game with Turk
  Severn! old captains who havo not
  pln)ed a game of nny kind sinco they
  sported with whales In tho Arctic
  have tnken up plug pong with their
  grandchildren and no longer complain
  of rheumatism, gout, lame backs, or
  that tired feeling
  Ping pong has the waterfront In Its
  grip. How long will It last?</text>
		</result>
	</results>
</topic></topics>
